<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="337" name="Biodiversity and Conservation">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of ex situ conservation?</text>
            <option id="A">National Park</option>
            <option id="B">Wildlife Sanctuary</option>
            <option id="C">Seed Bank</option>
            <option id="D">Sacred Grove</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Ex situ conservation involves the preservation of components of biological diversity outside their natural habitats, such as in seed banks, botanical gardens, and zoological parks. National parks, sanctuaries, and sacred groves are examples of in situ conservation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The most important cause driving animals and plants to extinction is:</text>
            <option id="A">Alien species invasions</option>
            <option id="B">Habitat loss and fragmentation</option>
            <option id="C">Over-exploitation</option>
            <option id="D">Co-extinctions</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Habitat loss and fragmentation is the primary cause of biodiversity loss. This is the first of the "Evil Quartet" described by ecologists.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The term "Biodiversity" was popularized by:</text>
            <option id="A">Paul Ehrlich</option>
            <option id="B">David Tilman</option>
            <option id="C">Edward Wilson</option>
            <option id="D">Alexander von Humboldt</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The term 'Biodiversity' was popularized by the sociobiologist Edward Wilson to describe the combined diversity at all the levels of biological organization.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered the most important cause driving animals and plants to extinction?</text>
            <option id="A">Over-exploitation</option>
            <option id="B">Alien species invasions</option>
            <option id="C">Habitat loss and fragmentation</option>
            <option id="D">Co-extinctions</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Habitat loss and fragmentation is the most important cause driving animals and plants to extinction. The most dramatic examples of habitat loss come from tropical rain forests.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The total number of biodiversity hotspots identified in the world so far is:</text>
            <option id="A">12</option>
            <option id="B">24</option>
            <option id="C">34</option>
            <option id="D">40</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Initially 25 biodiversity hotspots were identified but subsequently nine more have been added to the list, bringing the total number of biodiversity hotspots in the world to 34.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of an ex situ conservation method?</text>
            <option id="A">National Parks</option>
            <option id="B">Biosphere Reserves</option>
            <option id="C">Wildlife Sanctuaries</option>
            <option id="D">Botanical Gardens</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Ex situ conservation involves taking threatened animals and plants out from their natural habitat and placing them in special setting. Zoological parks, botanical gardens and wildlife safari parks serve this purpose.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered an ethical argument for conserving biodiversity?</text>
            <option id="A">Nature provides direct economic benefits like food and medicine.</option>
            <option id="B">Nature provides ecosystem services like pollination and oxygen.</option>
            <option id="C">Every species has an intrinsic value, and we have a moral duty to care for them.</option>
            <option id="D">Biodiversity is necessary for maintaining a stable global temperature.</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The ethical argument for conserving biodiversity relates to what we owe to millions of plant, animal and microbe species with whom we share this planet. We need to realise that every species has an intrinsic value.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to David Tilman's long-term ecosystem experiments using outdoor plots, increased species diversity contributed to:</text>
            <option id="A">Lower total biomass</option>
            <option id="B">Higher year-to-year variation in total biomass</option>
            <option id="C">Higher productivity and less year-to-year variation in total biomass</option>
            <option id="D">Increased susceptibility to alien species</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Tilman found that plots with more species showed less year-to-year variation in total biomass. He also showed that in his experiments, increased diversity contributed to higher productivity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a 'broadly utilitarian' reason for conserving biodiversity?</text>
            <option id="A">Pollination of crops by bees</option>
            <option id="B">Production of oxygen by Amazon forest</option>
            <option id="C">Aesthetic pleasure of walking through woods</option>
            <option id="D">Harvesting timber and firewood</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The broadly utilitarian argument says that biodiversity plays a major role in many ecosystem services that nature provides (oxygen, pollination, aesthetic pleasure). Harvesting timber and firewood is a 'narrowly utilitarian' reason.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who among the following popularized the term 'Biodiversity' to describe the combined diversity at all levels of biological organisation?</text>
            <option id="A">Paul Ehrlich</option>
            <option id="B">Edward Wilson</option>
            <option id="C">David Tilman</option>
            <option id="D">Alexander von Humboldt</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In our biosphere immense diversity exists at all levels. Biodiversity is the term popularised by the sociobiologist Edward Wilson to describe the combined diversity at all the levels of biological organisation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Rauwolfia vomitoria growing in different Himalayan ranges shows variation in the potency and concentration of the active chemical (reserpine) that it produces. This is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Species diversity</option>
            <option id="B">Ecological diversity</option>
            <option id="C">Genetic diversity</option>
            <option id="D">Ecosystem diversity</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Genetic diversity: A single species might show high diversity at the genetic level over its distributional range. The genetic variation shown by the medicinal plant Rauwolfia vomitoria growing in different Himalayan ranges might be in terms of the potency and concentration of the active chemical (reserpine) that the plant produces.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which region of the earth has the greatest biodiversity?</text>
            <option id="A">Temperate deciduous forest</option>
            <option id="B">Tropical Amazonian rain forest</option>
            <option id="C">Taiga</option>
            <option id="D">Coral reefs</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The largely tropical Amazonian rain forest in South America has the greatest biodiversity on earth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered an 'in situ' conservation approach?</text>
            <option id="A">Botanical gardens</option>
            <option id="B">Zoological parks</option>
            <option id="C">Biosphere reserves</option>
            <option id="D">Seed banks</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>When we conserve and protect the whole ecosystem, its biodiversity at all levels is protected - we save the entire forest to save the tiger. This approach is called in situ (on site) conservation. Biosphere reserves, national parks and sanctuaries are examples of in situ conservation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What was the primary objective of the historic Convention on Biological Diversity ('The Earth Summit') held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992?</text>
            <option id="A">To establish global seed banks</option>
            <option id="B">Conservation of biodiversity and sustainable use of its benefits</option>
            <option id="C">To ban the use of chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)</option>
            <option id="D">To reduce greenhouse gas emissions</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The historic Convention on Biological Diversity ('The Earth Summit') held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992, called upon all nations to take appropriate measures for conservation of biodiversity and sustainable utilisation of its benefits.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following represents 'ex situ' conservation?</text>
            <option id="A">National Parks</option>
            <option id="B">Sacred groves</option>
            <option id="C">Wildlife safari parks</option>
            <option id="D">Wildlife Sanctuaries</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In this approach, threatened animals and plants are taken out from their natural habitat and placed in special setting where they can be protected and given special care. Zoological parks, botanical gardens and wildlife safari parks serve this purpose.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered the most important cause driving animals and plants to extinction?</text>
            <option id="A">Over-exploitation</option>
            <option id="B">Alien species invasions</option>
            <option id="C">Habitat loss and fragmentation</option>
            <option id="D">Co-extinctions</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Habitat loss and fragmentation is the most important cause driving animals and plants to extinction. The most dramatic examples of habitat loss come from tropical rain forests.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When a host fish species becomes extinct, its unique assemblage of parasites also meets the same fate. This is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Over-exploitation</option>
            <option id="B">Alien species invasions</option>
            <option id="C">Habitat loss and fragmentation</option>
            <option id="D">Co-extinctions</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>When a species becomes extinct, the plant and animal species associated with it in an obligatory way also become extinct. When a host fish species becomes extinct, its unique assemblage of parasites also meets the same fate. This is called co-extinction.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following represents an ex situ conservation method?</text>
            <option id="A">National Parks</option>
            <option id="B">Biosphere Reserves</option>
            <option id="C">Wildlife Sanctuaries</option>
            <option id="D">Botanical Gardens</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>In ex situ conservation, threatened animals and plants are taken out from their natural habitat and placed in special setting where they can be protected and given special care. Zoological parks, botanical gardens and wildlife safari parks serve this purpose.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following describes genetic diversity?</text>
            <option id="A">Diversity at the species level</option>
            <option id="B">Variation shown by a single species at the genetic level over its distributional range</option>
            <option id="C">Diversity at the ecosystem level</option>
            <option id="D">Diversity of habitats in a geographical area</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Genetic diversity: A single species might show high diversity at the genetic level over its distributional range. The genetic variation shown by the medicinal plant Rauwolfia vomitoria growing in different Himalayan ranges might be in terms of the potency and concentration of the active chemical (reserpine) that the plant produces.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Western Ghats have a greater amphibian species diversity than the Eastern Ghats. This is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Genetic diversity</option>
            <option id="B">Species diversity</option>
            <option id="C">Ecological diversity</option>
            <option id="D">Biome diversity</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Species diversity: The diversity at the species level. For example, the Western Ghats have a greater amphibian species diversity than the Eastern Ghats.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>India has a greater ecosystem diversity than a Scandinavian country like Norway. This is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Genetic diversity</option>
            <option id="B">Species diversity</option>
            <option id="C">Ecological diversity</option>
            <option id="D">Population diversity</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Ecological diversity: At the ecosystem level, India, for instance, with its deserts, rain forests, mangroves, coral reefs, wetlands, estuaries, and alpine meadows has a greater ecosystem diversity than a Scandinavian country like Norway.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to IUCN (2004), what is the total number of plant and animal species described so far?</text>
            <option id="A">Slightly more than 1.5 million</option>
            <option id="B">About 5 million</option>
            <option id="C">Exactly 7 million</option>
            <option id="D">More than 10 million</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>According to the International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources (IUCN) (2004), the total number of plant and animal species described so far is slightly more than 1.5 million, but we have no clear idea of how many species are yet to be discovered and described.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Out of all the described species on Earth, plants (including algae, fungi, bryophytes, gymnosperms, and angiosperms) comprise no more than what percentage?</text>
            <option id="A">12%</option>
            <option id="B">22%</option>
            <option id="C">50%</option>
            <option id="D">70%</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>More than 70 per cent of all the species recorded are animals, while plants (including algae, fungi, bryophytes, gymnosperms and angiosperms) comprise no more than 22 per cent of the total.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which group among vertebrates has the highest number of species globally?</text>
            <option id="A">Fishes</option>
            <option id="B">Amphibians</option>
            <option id="C">Reptiles</option>
            <option id="D">Birds</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Among vertebrates, fishes have the maximum number of species, followed by birds, reptiles, amphibians, and mammals in that order.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Robert May's global estimate, what is the total number of species on Earth?</text>
            <option id="A">1.5 million</option>
            <option id="B">7 million</option>
            <option id="C">20 million</option>
            <option id="D">50 million</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some extreme estimates range from 20 to 50 million, but a more conservative and scientifically sound estimate made by Robert May places the global species diversity at about 7 million.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In India, what is the approximate number of animal species described so far?</text>
            <option id="A">More than 1,00,000</option>
            <option id="B">More than 90,000</option>
            <option id="C">Exactly 45,000</option>
            <option id="D">Less than 50,000</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Nearly 45,000 species of plants and twice as many of animals have been recorded from India. This means there are more than 90,000 species of animals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Applying May's global estimate, what percentage of the total species have been recorded so far?</text>
            <option id="A">More than 50%</option>
            <option id="B">Exactly 30%</option>
            <option id="C">Only 22%</option>
            <option id="D">Less than 10%</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>If we accept May's global estimates, only 22 per cent of the total species have been recorded so far.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT one of the 'Evil Quartet', the four major causes of biodiversity loss?</text>
            <option id="A">Habitat loss and fragmentation</option>
            <option id="B">Over-exploitation</option>
            <option id="C">Alien species invasions</option>
            <option id="D">Ex situ conservation</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The four major causes of biodiversity loss ('The Evil Quartet') are: 1) Habitat loss and fragmentation, 2) Over-exploitation, 3) Alien species invasions, and 4) Co-extinctions. Ex situ conservation is a method of saving biodiversity, not losing it.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the most important cause driving animals and plants to extinction?</text>
            <option id="A">Over-exploitation</option>
            <option id="B">Habitat loss and fragmentation</option>
            <option id="C">Alien species invasions</option>
            <option id="D">Co-extinctions</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Habitat loss and fragmentation: This is the most important cause driving animals and plants to extinction.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Amazon rain forest, which is so huge that it is called the 'lungs of the planet', is being cut and cleared primarily for what purpose?</text>
            <option id="A">To build cities</option>
            <option id="B">For cultivating soya beans or for conversion to grasslands for raising beef cattle</option>
            <option id="C">To extract timber for export</option>
            <option id="D">To search for oil</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Amazon rain forest (it is so huge that it is called the 'lungs of the planet') harbouring probably millions of species is being cut and cleared for cultivating soya beans or for conversion to grasslands for raising beef cattle.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When we conserve and protect the whole ecosystem, its biodiversity at all levels is protected. This type of conservation is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Ex situ conservation</option>
            <option id="B">In situ conservation</option>
            <option id="C">Cryopreservation</option>
            <option id="D">Captive breeding</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When we conserve and protect the whole ecosystem, its biodiversity at all levels is protected - we save the entire forest to save the tiger. This approach is called in situ (on site) conservation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is 'in situ' conservation?</text>
            <option id="A">Conserving organisms in a zoo or botanical garden</option>
            <option id="B">Conserving organisms by protecting their natural habitat</option>
            <option id="C">Preserving genetic material in liquid nitrogen</option>
            <option id="D">Cloning endangered species</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In situ conservation: Faced with the conflict between development and conservation, many nations find it unrealistic and economically not feasible to conserve all their biological wealth. Invariably, the number of species waiting to be saved from extinction far exceeds the conservation resources available. To protect the whole ecosystem is called in situ conservation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Regions with very high levels of species richness and high degree of endemism are identified for maximum protection. These regions are called:</text>
            <option id="A">National parks</option>
            <option id="B">Biodiversity hotspots</option>
            <option id="C">Biosphere reserves</option>
            <option id="D">Wildlife sanctuaries</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>They identified for maximum protection certain 'biodiversity hotspots' regions with very high levels of species richness and high degree of endemism (that is, species confined to that region and not found anywhere else).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of an ex situ conservation method?</text>
            <option id="A">National park</option>
            <option id="B">Wildlife sanctuary</option>
            <option id="C">Biosphere reserve</option>
            <option id="D">Botanical garden</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Ex situ Conservation: In this approach, threatened animals and plants are taken out from their natural habitat and placed in special setting where they can be protected and given special care. Zoological parks, botanical gardens and wildlife safari parks serve this purpose.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Animals that have become extinct in the wild but continue to be maintained in zoological parks are examples of which type of conservation?</text>
            <option id="A">In situ conservation</option>
            <option id="B">Ex situ conservation</option>
            <option id="C">Cryopreservation</option>
            <option id="D">In vitro conservation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Ex situ Conservation: ...There are many animals that have become extinct in the wild but continue to be maintained in zoological parks.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In recent years, ex situ conservation has advanced beyond keeping threatened species in enclosures. How can gametes of threatened species now be preserved?</text>
            <option id="A">By keeping them in a warm, dry environment</option>
            <option id="B">By cryopreservation in viable and fertile conditions</option>
            <option id="C">By treating them with strong radiation</option>
            <option id="D">By preserving them in alcohol</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In recent years ex situ conservation has advanced beyond keeping threatened species in enclosures. Now gametes of threatened species can be preserved in viable and fertile condition for long periods using cryopreservation techniques.</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>According to Alexander von Humboldt's species-area relationship, the relationship between species richness and area for a wide variety of taxa turns out to be a:</text>
            <option id="A">Straight line</option>
            <option id="B">Rectangular hyperbola</option>
            <option id="C">Sigmoid curve</option>
            <option id="D">Parabola</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Alexander von Humboldt observed that within a region species richness increased with increasing explored area, but only up to a limit. The relationship is a rectangular hyperbola. On a logarithmic scale, it is a straight line.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a criterion for identifying a biodiversity hotspot?</text>
            <option id="A">High levels of species richness</option>
            <option id="B">High degree of endemism</option>
            <option id="C">Accelerated habitat loss</option>
            <option id="D">Large geographical area</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Biodiversity hotspots are regions with very high levels of species richness and a high degree of endemism, but they are also under severe threat of habitat loss. A large geographical area is not a defining criterion.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The introduction of the Nile perch into Lake Victoria in East Africa led to the extinction of an ecologically unique assemblage of more than 200 species of:</text>
            <option id="A">Cichlid fish</option>
            <option id="B">Catfish</option>
            <option id="C">Tilapia</option>
            <option id="D">Salmon</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The Nile perch introduced into Lake Victoria in east Africa led eventually to the extinction of an ecologically unique assemblage of more than 200 species of cichlid fish in the lake.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following represents the correct sequence of the number of species (highest to lowest) among global biodiversity?</text>
            <option id="A">Fungi > Angiosperms > Algae > Lichens</option>
            <option id="B">Angiosperms > Fungi > Algae > Lichens</option>
            <option id="C">Fungi > Algae > Angiosperms > Lichens</option>
            <option id="D">Angiosperms > Algae > Fungi > Lichens</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Among plants and fungi, Fungi have the maximum number of species, followed by Angiosperms, Algae, Mosses, Ferns, and Lichens.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The term "Evil Quartet" refers to:</text>
            <option id="A">The four major threats to ozone depletion</option>
            <option id="B">The four main causes of biodiversity losses</option>
            <option id="C">The four greenhouse gases</option>
            <option id="D">The four mega-diverse countries</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The "Evil Quartet" is the sobriquet used to describe the four major causes of biodiversity losses: (i) Habitat loss and fragmentation, (ii) Over-exploitation, (iii) Alien species invasions, and (iv) Co-extinctions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following represents the correct sequence of taxa in terms of decreasing species diversity in the world?</text>
            <option id="A">Insects > Molluscs > Crustaceans</option>
            <option id="B">Crustaceans > Insects > Molluscs</option>
            <option id="C">Molluscs > Crustaceans > Insects</option>
            <option id="D">Insects > Crustaceans > Molluscs</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Among animals, insects are the most species-rich taxonomic group, making up more than 70 per cent of the total. That means, out of every 10 animals on this planet, 7 are insects. Molluscs are the second largest.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Alexander von Humboldt observed that within a region species richness increased with increasing explored area, but only up to a limit. The relationship between species richness and area for a wide variety of taxa turns out to be a:</text>
            <option id="A">Straight line</option>
            <option id="B">Rectangular hyperbola</option>
            <option id="C">Sigmoid curve</option>
            <option id="D">Parabola</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>On a logarithmic scale, the relationship is a straight line, but on a normal scale, the relationship between species richness and area for a wide variety of taxa turns out to be a rectangular hyperbola.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The extinction of Steller's sea cow and Passenger pigeon is primarily attributed to:</text>
            <option id="A">Habitat loss</option>
            <option id="B">Over-exploitation by humans</option>
            <option id="C">Alien species invasions</option>
            <option id="D">Co-extinction</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Over-exploitation by humans leads to extinction of many species. Steller's sea cow and passenger pigeon were driven to extinction due to overexploitation by humans.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following describes the Rivet Popper Hypothesis proposed by Paul Ehrlich?</text>
            <option id="A">It explains how new species are formed by mutation.</option>
            <option id="B">It compares the ecosystem to an airplane and species to rivets, showing that loss of key species causes ecosystem collapse.</option>
            <option id="C">It states that biodiversity increases as we move from the poles to the equator.</option>
            <option id="D">It explains the relationship between species richness and area explored.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Paul Ehrlich used the 'rivet popper hypothesis' to explain the importance of biodiversity. In an airplane (ecosystem) all parts are joined together using thousands of rivets (species). Popping rivets eventually makes the plane dangerously weak.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Amazon rain forest is often referred to as the:</text>
            <option id="A">Kidneys of the planet</option>
            <option id="B">Lungs of the planet</option>
            <option id="C">Heart of the planet</option>
            <option id="D">Brain of the planet</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The fast dwindling Amazon forest is estimated to produce, through photosynthesis, 20 per cent of the total oxygen in the earth's atmosphere. Hence, it is often referred to as the 'lungs of the planet'.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Sacred groves are an example of which type of conservation?</text>
            <option id="A">Ex situ conservation</option>
            <option id="B">In situ conservation</option>
            <option id="C">Cryopreservation</option>
            <option id="D">Gene banking</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In situ (on site) conservation involves protecting the whole ecosystem. In India, ecologically unique and biodiversity-rich regions are legally protected as biosphere reserves, national parks, sanctuaries, and sacred groves.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a critically endangered animal in India?</text>
            <option id="A">House sparrow</option>
            <option id="B">Indian peafowl</option>
            <option id="C">Great Indian Bustard</option>
            <option id="D">Common crow</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The Great Indian Bustard is a critically endangered bird species found in India, severely threatened by habitat loss and hunting.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Alexander von Humboldt observed that within a region, species richness increased with increasing explored area, but only up to a limit. The relationship between species richness and area for a wide variety of taxa turns out to be a:</text>
            <option id="A">Straight line</option>
            <option id="B">Sigmoid curve</option>
            <option id="C">Rectangular hyperbola</option>
            <option id="D">Parabola</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>During his pioneering and extensive explorations in the wilderness of South American jungles, the great German naturalist and geographer Alexander von Humboldt observed that within a region species richness increased with increasing explored area, but only up to a limit. In fact, the relation between species richness and area for a wide variety of taxa turns out to be a rectangular hyperbola.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the species-area relationship equation log S = log C + Z log A, what does 'Z' represent?</text>
            <option id="A">Species richness</option>
            <option id="B">Y-intercept</option>
            <option id="C">Slope of the line (regression coefficient)</option>
            <option id="D">Area</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>On a logarithmic scale, the relationship is a straight line described by the equation log S = log C + Z log A. Here, Z represents the slope of the line (regression coefficient).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered the most important cause driving animals and plants to extinction among the 'Evil Quartet'?</text>
            <option id="A">Over-exploitation</option>
            <option id="B">Alien species invasions</option>
            <option id="C">Co-extinctions</option>
            <option id="D">Habitat loss and fragmentation</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Habitat loss and fragmentation is the most important cause driving animals and plants to extinction. The most dramatic examples of habitat loss come from tropical rain forests.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The extinction of the Dodo bird from Mauritius is a recent example of extinction. The Dodo belonged to which group of animals?</text>
            <option id="A">Reptiles</option>
            <option id="B">Mammals</option>
            <option id="C">Birds</option>
            <option id="D">Amphibians</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Some examples of recent extinctions include the dodo (Mauritius), quagga (Africa), thylacine (Australia), Steller's Sea Cow (Russia) and three subspecies (Bali, Javan, Caspian) of tiger. The Dodo was a flightless bird.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How many biodiversity hotspots have been identified globally to date?</text>
            <option id="A">25</option>
            <option id="B">34</option>
            <option id="C">43</option>
            <option id="D">52</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Initially 25 biodiversity hotspots were identified but subsequently nine more have been added to the list, bringing the total number of biodiversity hotspots in the world to 34. These hotspots are also regions of accelerated habitat loss.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following biodiversity hotspots covers regions in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Western Ghats and Sri Lanka</option>
            <option id="B">Indo-Burma</option>
            <option id="C">Himalaya</option>
            <option id="D">All of the above</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Three of these hotspots - Western Ghats and Sri Lanka, Indo-Burma and Himalaya - cover our country's exceptionally high biodiversity regions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Sacred groves in India are an example of which type of conservation?</text>
            <option id="A">Ex situ conservation</option>
            <option id="B">In situ conservation</option>
            <option id="C">Cryopreservation</option>
            <option id="D">In vitro conservation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In India, ecologically unique and biodiversity-rich regions are legally protected as biosphere reserves, national parks and sanctuaries. India also has a history of religious and cultural traditions that emphasised protection of nature. Sacred groves are found in Khasi and Jaintia Hills in Meghalaya, Aravalli Hills of Rajasthan, etc., and represent in situ conservation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cryopreservation of gametes of threatened species is done in liquid nitrogen at what temperature?</text>
            <option id="A">-196°C</option>
            <option id="B">-100°C</option>
            <option id="C">-273°C</option>
            <option id="D">0°C</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In recent years ex situ conservation has advanced beyond keeping threatened species in enclosures. Now gametes of threatened species can be preserved in viable and fertile condition for long periods using cryopreservation techniques (at -196°C).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The 'Evil Quartet' is a sobriquet used to describe:</text>
            <option id="A">The four major causes of biodiversity losses</option>
            <option id="B">The four largest national parks in India</option>
            <option id="C">The four most endangered species of big cats</option>
            <option id="D">The four major components of an ecosystem</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The accelerated rates of species extinctions that the world is facing now are largely due to human activities. There are four major causes ('The Evil Quartet' is the sobriquet used to describe them): Habitat loss and fragmentation, Over-exploitation, Alien species invasions, and Co-extinctions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The historic Convention on Biological Diversity ('The Earth Summit') held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992 called upon all nations to:</text>
            <option id="A">Ban all hunting activities</option>
            <option id="B">Take appropriate measures for conservation of biodiversity and sustainable use of its benefits</option>
            <option id="C">Reduce carbon emissions to zero</option>
            <option id="D">Establish a global seed bank in the Arctic</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The historic Convention on Biological Diversity ('The Earth Summit') held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992, called upon all nations to take appropriate measures for conservation of biodiversity and sustainable use of its benefits.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following approaches is aimed at conserving the entire ecosystem to protect its biodiversity?</text>
            <option id="A">Ex situ conservation</option>
            <option id="B">In situ conservation</option>
            <option id="C">Cryopreservation</option>
            <option id="D">Tissue culture</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When we conserve and protect the whole ecosystem, its biodiversity at all levels is protected - we save the entire forest to save the tiger. This approach is called in situ (on site) conservation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In India, ecologically unique and biodiversity-rich regions are legally protected as:</text>
            <option id="A">Biosphere reserves</option>
            <option id="B">National parks</option>
            <option id="C">Sanctuaries</option>
            <option id="D">All of the above</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>In India, ecologically unique and biodiversity-rich regions are legally protected as biosphere reserves, national parks and sanctuaries. India now has 14 biosphere reserves, 90 national parks and 448 wildlife sanctuaries.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Robert May's global estimate, what is the total number of species of plants and animals on Earth?</text>
            <option id="A">1.5 million</option>
            <option id="B">7 million</option>
            <option id="C">20 million</option>
            <option id="D">50 million</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A more conservative and scientifically sound estimate made by Robert May places the global species diversity at about 7 million.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Out of every 10 animals on this planet, how many are insects?</text>
            <option id="A">3</option>
            <option id="B">5</option>
            <option id="C">7</option>
            <option id="D">9</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Among animals, insects are the most species-rich taxonomic group, making up more than 70 per cent of the total. That means, out of every 10 animals on this planet, 7 are insects.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which region in South America has the greatest biodiversity on Earth?</text>
            <option id="A">The Andes</option>
            <option id="B">The Amazonian rain forest</option>
            <option id="C">The Pampas</option>
            <option id="D">The Atacama Desert</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The largely tropical Amazonian rain forest in South America has the greatest biodiversity on earth- it is home to more than 40,000 species of plants, 3,000 of fishes, 1,300 of birds, 427 of mammals, 427 of amphibians, 378 of reptiles and of more than 1,25,000 invertebrates.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the relationship between species richness and area for a wide variety of taxa, as observed by Alexander von Humboldt?</text>
            <option id="A">A straight line on a linear scale</option>
            <option id="B">A rectangular hyperbola</option>
            <option id="C">A parabolic curve</option>
            <option id="D">An exponential curve</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>During his pioneering and extensive explorations in the wilderness of South American jungles, the great German naturalist and geographer Alexander von Humboldt observed that within a region species richness increased with increasing explored area, but only up to a limit. In fact, the relation between species richness and area for a wide variety of taxa turns out to be a rectangular hyperbola.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>India has only 2.4 per cent of the world's land area, but its share of the global species diversity is an impressive:</text>
            <option id="A">4.1 per cent</option>
            <option id="B">8.1 per cent</option>
            <option id="C">12.5 per cent</option>
            <option id="D">22.4 per cent</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Although India has only 2.4 per cent of the world's land area, its share of the global species diversity is an impressive 8.1 per cent. That is what makes our country one of the 12 mega diversity countries of the world.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What happens to species diversity as we move away from the equator towards the poles?</text>
            <option id="A">It increases</option>
            <option id="B">It decreases</option>
            <option id="C">It remains constant</option>
            <option id="D">It first increases, then decreases</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In general, species diversity decreases as we move away from the equator towards the poles. With very few exceptions, tropics (latitudinal range of 23.5° N to 23.5° S) harbour more species than temperate or polar areas.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Colombia located near the equator has nearly 1,400 species of birds. How many species does New York at 41° N have?</text>
            <option id="A">1,400</option>
            <option id="B">500</option>
            <option id="C">105</option>
            <option id="D">56</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Colombia located near the equator has nearly 1,400 species of birds while New York at 41° N has 105 species and Greenland at 71° N only 56 species.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a proposed reason for the higher biodiversity in the tropics?</text>
            <option id="A">Tropical environments are more seasonal and unpredictable</option>
            <option id="B">Tropical latitudes have remained relatively undisturbed for millions of years</option>
            <option id="C">Less solar energy is available in the tropics</option>
            <option id="D">Frequent glaciations have wiped out species regularly</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Ecologists and evolutionary biologists have proposed various hypotheses; some important ones are (a) Speciation is generally a function of time, unlike temperate regions subjected to frequent glaciations in the past, tropical latitudes have remained relatively undisturbed for millions of years.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Based on May's estimate, how many plant and animal species are yet to be discovered and described in India?</text>
            <option id="A">1,00,000 plant species and 3,00,000 animal species</option>
            <option id="B">50,000 plant species and 1,00,000 animal species</option>
            <option id="C">10,000 plant species and 20,000 animal species</option>
            <option id="D">1 million plant species and 2 million animal species</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Applying this proportion to India's diversity figures, we estimate that there are probably more than 1,00,000 plant species and more than 3,00,000 animal species yet to be discovered and described.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Why is the biodiversity of prokaryotes not properly estimated by biologists?</text>
            <option id="A">They are too small to count</option>
            <option id="B">Conventional taxonomic methods are not suitable for identifying microbial species</option>
            <option id="C">Prokaryotes do not have DNA</option>
            <option id="D">Prokaryotes reproduce too slowly</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Biologists are not sure about how many prokaryotic species there might be. The problem is that conventional taxonomic methods are not suitable for identifying microbial species and many species are simply not culturable under laboratory conditions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Amazonian rain forest in South America has the greatest biodiversity on earth. It is home to how many species of fishes?</text>
            <option id="A">1,300</option>
            <option id="B">3,000</option>
            <option id="C">427</option>
            <option id="D">378</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The largely tropical Amazonian rain forest in South America has the greatest biodiversity on earth- it is home to more than 40,000 species of plants, 3,000 of fishes, 1,300 of birds, 427 of mammals, 427 of amphibians, 378 of reptiles and of more than 1,25,000 invertebrates.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Tropical environments, unlike temperate ones, are less seasonal, relatively more constant and predictable. What is the effect of this on speciation?</text>
            <option id="A">It leads to fewer species</option>
            <option id="B">It stops speciation completely</option>
            <option id="C">It promotes niche specialisation and leads to a greater species diversity</option>
            <option id="D">It only favors animal diversity, not plants</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Tropical environments, unlike temperate ones, are less seasonal, relatively more constant and predictable. Such constant environments promote niche specialisation and lead to a greater species diversity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When large habitats are broken up into small fragments due to various human activities, which types of animals are worst affected?</text>
            <option id="A">Insects and small rodents</option>
            <option id="B">Mammals and birds requiring large territories and certain animals with migratory habits</option>
            <option id="C">Fishes and amphibians</option>
            <option id="D">Reptiles</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When large habitats are broken up into small fragments due to various human activities, mammals and birds requiring large territories and certain animals with migratory habits are badly affected, leading to population declines.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The extinction of Steller's sea cow and the passenger pigeon in the last 500 years were primarily due to:</text>
            <option id="A">Habitat loss</option>
            <option id="B">Over-exploitation by humans</option>
            <option id="C">Alien species invasion</option>
            <option id="D">Climate change</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Over-exploitation: Humans have always depended on nature for food and shelter, but when 'need' turns to 'greed', it leads to over-exploitation of natural resources. Many species extinctions in the last 500 years (Steller's sea cow, passenger pigeon) were due to overexploitation by humans.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What was the cause of the extinction of the endemic cichlid fish in Lake Victoria in East Africa?</text>
            <option id="A">Introduction of the Nile perch (an alien species)</option>
            <option id="B">Over-fishing by locals</option>
            <option id="C">Drying up of the lake</option>
            <option id="D">Pollution from nearby industries</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Alien species invasions: When alien species are introduced unintentionally or deliberately for whatever purpose, some of them turn invasive, and cause decline or extinction of indigenous species. The Nile perch introduced into Lake Victoria in east Africa led eventually to the extinction of an ecologically unique assemblage of more than 200 species of cichlid fish in the lake.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following invasive weed species caused environmental damage and posed a threat to native species in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Carrot grass (Parthenium), Lantana, and water hyacinth (Eicchornia)</option>
            <option id="B">Neem, Banyan, and Peepal</option>
            <option id="C">Tulsi, Aloe vera, and Mint</option>
            <option id="D">Mango, Guava, and Papaya</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>You must be familiar with the environmental damage caused and threat posed to our native species by invasive weed species like carrot grass (Parthenium), Lantana and water hyacinth (Eicchornia).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What does the term 'endemism' refer to in the context of biodiversity hotspots?</text>
            <option id="A">Species that are facing a high risk of extinction</option>
            <option id="B">Species confined to that region and not found anywhere else</option>
            <option id="C">Species that migrate to the hotspot during winter</option>
            <option id="D">Alien species introduced into the hotspot</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>They identified for maximum protection certain 'biodiversity hotspots' regions with very high levels of species richness and high degree of endemism (that is, species confined to that region and not found anywhere else).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Initially, 25 biodiversity hotspots were identified globally. How many have been added subsequently, bringing the total number of hotspots in the world to 34?</text>
            <option id="A">5</option>
            <option id="B">9</option>
            <option id="C">10</option>
            <option id="D">15</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Initially 25 biodiversity hotspots were identified but subsequently nine more have been added to the list, bringing the total number of biodiversity hotspots in the world to 34.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following are the three biodiversity hotspots that cover India's high biodiversity regions?</text>
            <option id="A">Western Ghats and Sri Lanka, Indo-Burma, and Himalaya</option>
            <option id="B">Eastern Ghats, Thar Desert, and Sunderbans</option>
            <option id="C">Deccan Plateau, Gangetic Plain, and Andaman Islands</option>
            <option id="D">Aravalli range, Vindhya range, and Satpura range</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Three of these hotspots – Western Ghats and Sri Lanka, Indo-Burma and Himalaya – cover our country's exceptionally high biodiversity regions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Although all the biodiversity hotspots put together cover less than 2 percent of the earth's land area, strict protection of these hotspots could reduce the ongoing mass extinctions by almost:</text>
            <option id="A">10 per cent</option>
            <option id="B">20 per cent</option>
            <option id="C">30 per cent</option>
            <option id="D">50 per cent</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Although all the biodiversity hotspots put together cover less than 2 per cent of the earth's land area, the number of species they collectively harbour is extremely high and strict protection of these hotspots could reduce the ongoing mass extinctions by almost 30 per cent.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Using cryopreservation techniques, gametes of threatened species can be preserved. How are eggs typically fertilised in this context?</text>
            <option id="A">By introducing them into a wild population</option>
            <option id="B">Through in vitro fertilisation</option>
            <option id="C">By artificial insemination only</option>
            <option id="D">By cloning</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Now gametes of threatened species can be preserved in viable and fertile condition for long periods using cryopreservation techniques, eggs can be fertilised in vitro.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How can plants of threatened species be propagated under ex situ conservation?</text>
            <option id="A">By cross-pollination with weeds</option>
            <option id="B">By tissue culture methods</option>
            <option id="C">By exposing them to high temperatures</option>
            <option id="D">By preventing their seed dispersal</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>...eggs can be fertilised in vitro, and plants can be propagated using tissue culture methods.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Seeds of different genetic strains of commercially important plants can be kept for long periods in:</text>
            <option id="A">Seed banks</option>
            <option id="B">Botanical gardens</option>
            <option id="C">National parks</option>
            <option id="D">Sacred groves</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Seeds of different genetic strains of commercially important plants can be kept for long periods in seed banks.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Biodiversity knows no political boundaries, and its conservation is therefore a collective responsibility. Which historic convention called upon all nations to take appropriate measures for conservation of biodiversity?</text>
            <option id="A">The World Summit (2002)</option>
            <option id="B">The Earth Summit (1992)</option>
            <option id="C">The Kyoto Protocol</option>
            <option id="D">The Montreal Protocol</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The historic Convention on Biological Diversity ('The Earth Summit') held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992, called upon all nations to take appropriate measures for conservation of biodiversity and sustainable utilisation of its benefits.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>In the Rivet Popper hypothesis proposed by Paul Ehrlich, the "rivets" on the wings of the airplane represent:</text>
            <option id="A">Keystone species</option>
            <option id="B">Endemic species</option>
            <option id="C">Extinct species</option>
            <option id="D">Invasive species</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In the Rivet Popper hypothesis, rivets represent species. Rivets on the wings represent key species (keystone species) that drive major ecosystem functions. Losing them is an immediate threat to flight safety (ecosystem stability).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Read the following statements (A-D):\nA. The Amazon rain forest is estimated to produce 20% of the total oxygen in the earth's atmosphere.\nB. The historic Convention on Biological Diversity ('The Earth Summit') was held in Johannesburg in 2002.\nC. Dodo (Mauritius), Quagga (Africa) and Steller's Sea Cow (Russia) are examples of recent extinctions.\nD. The current species extinction rates are estimated to be 100 to 1,000 times faster than in the pre-human times.\nHow many of the above statements are correct?</text>
            <option id="A">One</option>
            <option id="B">Two</option>
            <option id="C">Three</option>
            <option id="D">Four</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Statement B is incorrect because The Earth Summit was held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992. The World Summit on Sustainable Development was held in Johannesburg in 2002. Statements A, C, and D are correct.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When a host fish species becomes extinct, its unique assemblage of parasites also meets the same fate. This is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Alien species invasion</option>
            <option id="B">Co-extinction</option>
            <option id="C">Over-exploitation</option>
            <option id="D">Habitat fragmentation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Co-extinction refers to the phenomenon where the extinction of one species invariably leads to the extinction of another species with which it is intimately associated in an obligate manner.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following statements about endemic species is TRUE?</text>
            <option id="A">They are found universally across all continents.</option>
            <option id="B">They are species with very broad niches.</option>
            <option id="C">They are confined to that region and not found anywhere else.</option>
            <option id="D">They are introduced species that have become invasive.</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Endemism refers to species confined to a particular region and not found anywhere else. Hotspots are regions with very high levels of species richness and high degree of endemism.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The historic Convention on Biological Diversity ('The Earth Summit') held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992 called upon all nations to:</text>
            <option id="A">Eliminate the use of CFCs by 2000.</option>
            <option id="B">Take appropriate measures for conservation of biodiversity and sustainable use of its benefits.</option>
            <option id="C">Reduce greenhouse gas emissions to 1990 levels.</option>
            <option id="D">Significantly reduce the current rate of biodiversity loss at global, regional and local levels by 2010.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Earth Summit held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992 called upon all nations to take appropriate measures for conservation of biodiversity and sustainable use of its benefits. The 2010 target was set at the World Summit on Sustainable Development in Johannesburg in 2002.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cryopreservation of gametes of threatened species in viable and fertile condition can be referred to as:</text>
            <option id="A">In situ conservation</option>
            <option id="B">Advanced ex situ conservation</option>
            <option id="C">In vivo conservation</option>
            <option id="D">Sacred groves</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In recent years, ex situ conservation has advanced beyond keeping threatened species in enclosures. Now gametes of threatened species can be preserved in viable and fertile condition for long periods using cryopreservation techniques.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The introduction of which predatory fish into Lake Victoria in East Africa led to the extinction of an ecologically unique assemblage of more than 200 species of cichlid fish?</text>
            <option id="A">Clarias gariepinus</option>
            <option id="B">Nile perch</option>
            <option id="C">Water hyacinth</option>
            <option id="D">Parthenium</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Nile perch introduced into Lake Victoria in east Africa led eventually to the extinction of an ecologically unique assemblage of more than 200 species of cichlid fish in the lake.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Bioprospecting is defined as:</text>
            <option id="A">The process of preserving seeds at very low temperatures.</option>
            <option id="B">Exploring molecular, genetic and species-level diversity for products of economic importance.</option>
            <option id="C">The illegal harvesting of wildlife.</option>
            <option id="D">The introduction of alien species for agricultural benefits.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Nations endowed with rich biodiversity expect to reap enormous benefits from bioprospecting - exploring molecular, genetic and species-level diversity for products of economic importance.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following regions exhibits the highest biodiversity on Earth?</text>
            <option id="A">The temperate forests of North America</option>
            <option id="B">The tundra regions</option>
            <option id="C">The Amazonian rain forest in South America</option>
            <option id="D">The savannas of Africa</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The largely tropical Amazonian rain forest in South America has the greatest biodiversity on earth- it is home to more than 40,000 species of plants, 3,000 of fishes, 1,300 of birds, 427 of mammals, 427 of amphibians, 378 of reptiles and of more than 1,25,000 invertebrates.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When a host fish species becomes extinct, its unique assemblage of parasites also meets the same fate. This phenomenon is termed as:</text>
            <option id="A">Over-exploitation</option>
            <option id="B">Alien species invasion</option>
            <option id="C">Co-extinction</option>
            <option id="D">Habitat fragmentation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>When a species becomes extinct, the plant and animal species associated with it in an obligatory way also become extinct. When a host fish species becomes extinct, its unique assemblage of parasites also meets the same fate. This is called co-extinction.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an invasive weed species that has caused environmental damage and poses a threat to native species in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Carrot grass (Parthenium)</option>
            <option id="B">Lantana</option>
            <option id="C">Water hyacinth (Eichhornia)</option>
            <option id="D">All of the above</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Some alien species introductions turn invasive and cause decline or extinction of indigenous species. The environmental damage caused and threat posed to our native species by invasive weed species like carrot grass (Parthenium), Lantana and water hyacinth (Eichhornia) are well known.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the primary purpose of identifying certain regions as 'Biodiversity Hotspots'?</text>
            <option id="A">To establish large agricultural farms.</option>
            <option id="B">To promote international eco-tourism exclusively.</option>
            <option id="C">To prioritize conservation in regions with very high levels of species richness, high degree of endemism, and accelerated habitat loss.</option>
            <option id="D">To relocate indigenous people from these areas.</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Conservationists identified for maximum protection certain 'biodiversity hotspots' regions with very high levels of species richness and high degree of endemism (that is, species confined to that region and not found anywhere else). These hotspots are also regions of accelerated habitat loss.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The World Summit on Sustainable Development held in 2002 in Johannesburg, South Africa, resulted in 190 countries pledging to achieve a significant reduction in the current rate of biodiversity loss by the year:</text>
            <option id="A">2010</option>
            <option id="B">2015</option>
            <option id="C">2020</option>
            <option id="D">2030</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In a follow-up, the World Summit on Sustainable Development held in 2002 in Johannesburg, South Africa, 190 countries pledged their commitment to achieve by 2010, a significant reduction in the current rate of biodiversity loss at global, regional and local levels.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a broadly utilitarian argument for the conservation of biodiversity?</text>
            <option id="A">Pollination</option>
            <option id="B">Aesthetic pleasures of walking through thick woods</option>
            <option id="C">Obtaining oxygen from the Amazon forest</option>
            <option id="D">Deriving drugs and medicines</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Deriving economic benefits like food, firewood, fibre, construction material, industrial products and products of medicinal importance is a 'narrowly utilitarian' argument. Broadly utilitarian arguments focus on ecosystem services like oxygen production, pollination, and aesthetic value.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The introduction of the Nile perch into Lake Victoria in East Africa led eventually to the extinction of an ecologically unique assemblage of more than 200 species of which fish?</text>
            <option id="A">Salmon</option>
            <option id="B">Cichlid fish</option>
            <option id="C">Catfish</option>
            <option id="D">Trout</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Nile perch introduced into Lake Victoria in east Africa led eventually to the extinction of an ecologically unique assemblage of more than 200 species of cichlid fish in the lake. This is a classic example of alien species invasion leading to extinction.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Sacred groves are forest patches where all the trees and wildlife within are venerated and given total protection. Which of the following is NOT an example of a sacred grove in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Khasi and Jaintia Hills in Meghalaya</option>
            <option id="B">Aravalli Hills of Rajasthan</option>
            <option id="C">Western Ghat regions of Karnataka and Maharashtra</option>
            <option id="D">Sundarbans in West Bengal</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Sacred groves are found in Khasi and Jaintia Hills in Meghalaya, Aravalli Hills of Rajasthan, Western Ghat regions of Karnataka and Maharashtra and the Sarguja, Chanda and Bastar areas of Madhya Pradesh. Sundarbans is a mangrove forest, not a legally defined sacred grove by indigenous tribes in this context.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Nile perch introduced into Lake Victoria in East Africa led to the extinction of an ecologically unique assemblage of more than 200 species of:</text>
            <option id="A">Cichlid fish</option>
            <option id="B">Lungfish</option>
            <option id="C">Catfish</option>
            <option id="D">Tilapia</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The Nile perch introduced into Lake Victoria in east Africa led eventually to the extinction of an ecologically unique assemblage of more than 200 species of cichlid fish in the lake. This is an example of alien species invasion.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following weed species was introduced into India and caused environmental damage and threat to native species?</text>
            <option id="A">Parthenium (carrot grass)</option>
            <option id="B">Lantana</option>
            <option id="C">Eichhornia (water hyacinth)</option>
            <option id="D">All of the above</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The environmental damage caused and threat posed to our native species by invasive weed species like carrot grass (Parthenium), Lantana and water hyacinth (Eicchornia) are well known examples of alien species invasions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>On a logarithmic scale, the species-area relationship is a straight line described by the equation:</text>
            <option id="A">log S = log C + Z log A</option>
            <option id="B">S = C A^Z</option>
            <option id="C">log S = Z log C + A</option>
            <option id="D">log A = log S + Z log C</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>On a logarithmic scale, the relationship is a straight line described by the equation log S = log C + Z log A where S= Species richness A= Area Z = slope of the line (regression coefficient) C = Y-intercept.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who proposed the 'Rivet popper hypothesis' to explain the role of biodiversity in ecosystem functioning?</text>
            <option id="A">David Tilman</option>
            <option id="B">Paul Ehrlich</option>
            <option id="C">Alexander von Humboldt</option>
            <option id="D">Robert May</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>There are no direct answers to such naieve questions but we can develop a proper perspective through an analogy (the 'rivet popper hypothesis') used by Stanford ecologist Paul Ehrlich.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered the most important cause driving animals and plants to extinction?</text>
            <option id="A">Over-exploitation</option>
            <option id="B">Alien species invasions</option>
            <option id="C">Habitat loss and fragmentation</option>
            <option id="D">Co-extinctions</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Habitat loss and fragmentation: This is the most important cause driving animals and plants to extinction. The most dramatic examples of habitat loss come from tropical rain forests.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to David Tilman's long-term ecosystem experiments using outdoor plots, plots with more species showed:</text>
            <option id="A">Higher year-to-year variation in total biomass</option>
            <option id="B">Less year-to-year variation in total biomass</option>
            <option id="C">Lower productivity</option>
            <option id="D">No difference from plots with fewer species</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>David Tilman's long-term ecosystem experiments using outdoor plots provide some tentative answers. Tilman found that plots with more species showed less year-to-year variation in total biomass. He also showed that in his experiments, increased diversity contributed to higher productivity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The IUCN Red List (2004) documents the extinction of 784 species in the last 500 years. How many of these were plants?</text>
            <option id="A">338</option>
            <option id="B">359</option>
            <option id="C">87</option>
            <option id="D">784</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The IUCN Red List (2004) documents the extinction of 784 species (including 338 vertebrates, 359 invertebrates and 87 plants) in the last 500 years.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which extinct species is incorrectly matched with its region of origin?</text>
            <option id="A">Dodo - Mauritius</option>
            <option id="B">Quagga - Africa</option>
            <option id="C">Thylacine - Russia</option>
            <option id="D">Steller's Sea Cow - Russia</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Some examples of recent extinctions include the dodo (Mauritius), quagga (Africa), thylacine (Australia), Steller's Sea Cow (Russia) and three subspecies (Bali, Javan, Caspian) of tiger.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The species-area relationship on a logarithmic scale is a straight line described by the equation: log S = log C + Z log A. What does 'Z' stand for in this equation?</text>
            <option id="A">Species richness</option>
            <option id="B">Area</option>
            <option id="C">Slope of the line (regression coefficient)</option>
            <option id="D">Y-intercept</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>On a logarithmic scale, the relationship is a straight line described by the equation log S = log C + Z log A where S= Species richness A= Area Z = slope of the line (regression coefficient) C = Y-intercept.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>For a wide variety of taxa, whether they are plants in Britain, birds in California or molluscs in New York state, the value of Z lies in the range of:</text>
            <option id="A">0.1 to 0.2</option>
            <option id="B">0.6 to 1.2</option>
            <option id="C">1.15</option>
            <option id="D">0.01 to 0.05</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Ecologists have discovered that the value of Z lies in the range of 0.1 to 0.2, regardless of the taxonomic group or the region (whether it is the plants in Britain, birds in California or molluscs in New York state, the slopes of the regression line are amazingly similar).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the species-area relationship, if you analyze the species-area relationships among very large areas like the entire continents, what will the slope of the line (Z value) be?</text>
            <option id="A">Much shallower (0.01 to 0.1)</option>
            <option id="B">Unchanged (0.1 to 0.2)</option>
            <option id="C">Much steeper (0.6 to 1.2)</option>
            <option id="D">Negative</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>But, if you analyse the species-area relationships among very large areas like the entire continents, you will find that the slope of the line to be much steeper (Z values in the range of 0.6 to 1.2).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The recent illegal introduction of which fish for aquaculture purposes is posing a threat to the indigenous catfishes in our rivers?</text>
            <option id="A">Nile perch</option>
            <option id="B">African catfish (Clarias gariepinus)</option>
            <option id="C">Rohu</option>
            <option id="D">Catla</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The recent illegal introduction of the African catfish Clarias gariepinus for aquaculture purposes is posing a threat to the indigenous catfishes in our rivers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When a host fish species becomes extinct, its unique assemblage of parasites also meets the same fate. This phenomenon is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Co-extinction</option>
            <option id="B">Over-exploitation</option>
            <option id="C">Alien invasion</option>
            <option id="D">Habitat fragmentation</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Co-extinctions: When a species becomes extinct, the plant and animal species associated with it in an obligatory way also become extinct. When a host fish species becomes extinct, its unique assemblage of parasites also meets the same fate.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The arguments for conserving biodiversity are grouped into three categories. Which category argues that nature provides direct economic benefits like food, firewood, fiber, construction material, and industrial products?</text>
            <option id="A">Broadly utilitarian</option>
            <option id="B">Narrowly utilitarian</option>
            <option id="C">Ethical</option>
            <option id="D">Ecological</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The narrowly utilitarian arguments for conserving biodiversity are obvious; humans derive countless direct economic benefits from naturefood (cereals, pulses, fruits), firewood, fibre, construction material, industrial products (tannins, lubricants, dyes, resins, perfumes ) and products of medicinal importance.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In India, ecologically unique and biodiversity-rich regions are legally protected. Which of the following is NOT a category of these legally protected areas?</text>
            <option id="A">Biosphere reserves</option>
            <option id="B">National parks</option>
            <option id="C">Sanctuaries</option>
            <option id="D">Zoological parks</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>In India, ecologically unique and biodiversity-rich regions are legally protected as biosphere reserves, national parks and sanctuaries. (Zoological parks are ex situ conservation).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How many biosphere reserves, national parks, and wildlife sanctuaries does India currently have (as per the text)?</text>
            <option id="A">10 biosphere reserves, 50 national parks, and 200 wildlife sanctuaries</option>
            <option id="B">14 biosphere reserves, 90 national parks, and 448 wildlife sanctuaries</option>
            <option id="C">25 biosphere reserves, 100 national parks, and 500 wildlife sanctuaries</option>
            <option id="D">5 biosphere reserves, 20 national parks, and 100 wildlife sanctuaries</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>India now has 14 biosphere reserves, 90 national parks and 448 wildlife sanctuaries.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In many cultures, tracts of forest were set aside, and all the trees and wildlife within were venerated and given total protection. These are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Sacred groves</option>
            <option id="B">National parks</option>
            <option id="C">Botanical gardens</option>
            <option id="D">Biosphere reserves</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>India has also a history of religious and cultural traditions that emphasised protection of nature. In many cultures, tracts of forest were set aside, and all the trees and wildlife within were venerated and given total protection. Such sacred groves are found in Khasi and Jaintia Hills in Meghalaya, Aravalli Hills of Rajasthan, Western Ghat regions of Karnataka and Maharashtra and the Sarguja, Chanda and Bastar areas of Madhya Pradesh.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In which year and city was 'The Earth Summit' (Convention on Biological Diversity) held?</text>
            <option id="A">2002 in Johannesburg, South Africa</option>
            <option id="B">1992 in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</option>
            <option id="C">1987 in Montreal, Canada</option>
            <option id="D">1997 in Kyoto, Japan</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The historic Convention on Biological Diversity ('The Earth Summit') held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992...</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Following the Earth Summit, the World Summit on Sustainable Development was held in 2002. Where did this take place?</text>
            <option id="A">Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</option>
            <option id="B">Johannesburg, South Africa</option>
            <option id="C">New York, USA</option>
            <option id="D">New Delhi, India</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In a follow-up, the World Summit on Sustainable Development held in 2002 in Johannesburg, South Africa, 190 countries pledged their commitment...</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>At the World Summit on Sustainable Development in 2002, 190 countries pledged to achieve a significant reduction in the current rate of biodiversity loss by the year:</text>
            <option id="A">2005</option>
            <option id="B">2010</option>
            <option id="C">2020</option>
            <option id="D">2050</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>...190 countries pledged their commitment to achieve by 2010, a significant reduction in the current rate of biodiversity loss at global, regional and local levels.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>