<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="334" name="Biotechnology and its Applications">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>What does 'Bt' in Bt cotton stand for?</text>
            <option id="A">Biotechnology</option>
            <option id="B">Bacillus thuringiensis</option>
            <option id="C">Barium titanate</option>
            <option id="D">Bacterium thermophilus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Bt stands for Bacillus thuringiensis, a soil bacterium that produces a toxin which kills certain insects. The gene for this toxin has been incorporated into cotton to make it pest-resistant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first clinical gene therapy was given in 1990 to a 4-year-old girl with which of the following deficiencies?</text>
            <option id="A">Adenosine deaminase (ADA) deficiency</option>
            <option id="B">Tyrosine kinase deficiency</option>
            <option id="C">Phenylketonuria</option>
            <option id="D">Cystic fibrosis</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The first clinical gene therapy was given in 1990 to a 4-year-old girl with adenosine deaminase (ADA) deficiency. This enzyme is crucial for the immune system to function.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Golden rice is a promising transgenic crop. When compared to normal rice, it is enriched with:</text>
            <option id="A">Vitamin C</option>
            <option id="B">Iron</option>
            <option id="C">Vitamin A (beta-carotene)</option>
            <option id="D">Vitamin E</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Golden rice has been genetically engineered to produce beta-carotene, a precursor of Vitamin A, in the edible parts of the rice to combat Vitamin A deficiency.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which technique is based on the principle of antigen-antibody interaction?</text>
            <option id="A">PCR</option>
            <option id="B">ELISA</option>
            <option id="C">Gel electrophoresis</option>
            <option id="D">Recombinant DNA technology</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>ELISA (Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay) is based on the principle of antigen-antibody interaction. Infection by a pathogen can be detected by the presence of antigens or by detecting the antibodies synthesized against the pathogen.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Insulin originally extracted from the pancreas of slaughtered cattle and pigs caused what issue in some patients?</text>
            <option id="A">It was totally ineffective</option>
            <option id="B">It caused allergy or other types of reactions</option>
            <option id="C">It caused immediate death</option>
            <option id="D">It degraded too quickly in the blood</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Insulin from an animal source, though effective, elicited an immune response in some patients, leading to allergies or other reactions to the foreign protein.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first clinical gene therapy was given for treating:</text>
            <option id="A">Cystic fibrosis</option>
            <option id="B">Adenosine deaminase (ADA) deficiency</option>
            <option id="C">Rheumatoid arthritis</option>
            <option id="D">Hemophilia</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The first clinical gene therapy was given in 1990 to a 4-year old girl with adenosine deaminase (ADA) deficiency.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following techniques is commonly used for early diagnosis of diseases when the pathogen concentration is very low?</text>
            <option id="A">Serum and urine analysis</option>
            <option id="B">Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR)</option>
            <option id="C">X-ray imaging</option>
            <option id="D">Complete blood count (CBC)</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Presence of a pathogen is normally suspected only when the pathogen has produced a disease symptom. By this time the concentration of pathogen is already very high. However, very low concentration of a bacteria or virus can be detected by amplification of their nucleic acid by PCR.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first transgenic cow, Rosie, produced:</text>
            <option id="A">Human alpha-lactalbumin enriched milk</option>
            <option id="B">Human insulin enriched milk</option>
            <option id="C">Milk with enhanced butterfat</option>
            <option id="D">Milk containing growth hormone</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In 1997, the first transgenic cow, Rosie, produced human protein-enriched milk (2.4 grams per litre). The milk contained the human alpha-lactalbumin and was nutritionally a more balanced product for human babies than natural cow-milk.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which Indian company launched the first indigenous recombinant human insulin (Humulin)?</text>
            <option id="A">Biocon</option>
            <option id="B">Ranbaxy</option>
            <option id="C">Eli Lilly</option>
            <option id="D">Dr. Reddy's Laboratories</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Wait, Eli Lilly is an American company, not Indian. In 1983, Eli Lilly, an American company, prepared two DNA sequences corresponding to A and B, chains of human insulin and introduced them in plasmids of E. coli to produce insulin chains.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first clinical gene therapy was given to a 4-year-old girl in 1990 for a deficiency of which enzyme?</text>
            <option id="A">Tyrosine kinase</option>
            <option id="B">Adenosine deaminase (ADA)</option>
            <option id="C">DNA ligase</option>
            <option id="D">RNA polymerase</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The first clinical gene therapy was given in 1990 to a 4-year old girl with adenosine deaminase (ADA) deficiency. This enzyme is crucial for the immune system to function.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which vector was commonly used for introducing a functional ADA cDNA into the lymphocytes of the patient during the early gene therapy trials?</text>
            <option id="A">Retrovirus</option>
            <option id="B">Adenovirus</option>
            <option id="C">Agrobacterium</option>
            <option id="D">Bacteriophage lambda</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>As a first step towards gene therapy, lymphocytes from the blood of the patient are grown in a culture outside the body. A functional ADA cDNA (using a retroviral vector) is then introduced into these lymphocytes, which are subsequently returned to the patient.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Transgenic animals are those which have:</text>
            <option id="A">Undergone mutation by UV radiation</option>
            <option id="B">Been cloned perfectly from another animal</option>
            <option id="C">Had their DNA manipulated to possess and express an extra (foreign) gene</option>
            <option id="D">Only their mitochondrial DNA altered</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Animals that have had their DNA manipulated to possess and express an extra (foreign) gene are known as transgenic animals. Transgenic rats, rabbits, pigs, sheep, cows and fish have been produced.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following organisms is used to produce the Bt toxin?</text>
            <option id="A">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</option>
            <option id="B">Bacillus thuringiensis</option>
            <option id="C">Escherichia coli</option>
            <option id="D">Rhizobium leguminosarum</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Bt toxin is produced by a bacterium called Bacillus thuringiensis (Bt for short). Bt toxin gene has been cloned from the bacteria and been expressed in plants to provide resistance to insects without the need for insecticides.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Golden rice is a transgenic crop developed to combat the deficiency of which vitamin?</text>
            <option id="A">Vitamin A</option>
            <option id="B">Vitamin B12</option>
            <option id="C">Vitamin C</option>
            <option id="D">Vitamin D</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Golden rice is a genetically modified variety of rice (Oryza sativa) which has been engineered to biosynthesize beta-carotene, a precursor of vitamin A, in the edible parts of rice. It aims to combat Vitamin A deficiency.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of RNA interference (RNAi) involves the silencing of a specific mRNA due to a complementary ________ molecule that binds to and prevents translation of the mRNA.</text>
            <option id="A">ssDNA</option>
            <option id="B">dsRNA</option>
            <option id="C">dsDNA</option>
            <option id="D">tRNA</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>RNAi takes place in all eukaryotic organisms as a method of cellular defense. This method involves silencing of a specific mRNA due to a complementary dsRNA (double-stranded RNA) molecule that binds to and prevents translation of the mRNA (silencing).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a critical research area of biotechnology?</text>
            <option id="A">Providing the best catalyst in the form of improved organism</option>
            <option id="B">Creating optimal conditions through engineering for a catalyst to act</option>
            <option id="C">Downstream processing technologies to purify the protein/organic compound</option>
            <option id="D">Developing traditional agricultural tools</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The three critical research areas of biotechnology are: (i) Providing the best catalyst in the form of improved organism usually a microbe or pure enzyme. (ii) Creating optimal conditions through engineering for a catalyst to act, and (iii) Downstream processing technologies to purify the protein/organic compound.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Green Revolution succeeded in tripling the food supply but it was not enough to feed the growing human population. Increased yields were mainly due to:</text>
            <option id="A">Use of genetically modified crops</option>
            <option id="B">Use of improved crop varieties</option>
            <option id="C">Use of better management practices and use of agrochemicals</option>
            <option id="D">Both B and C</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Increased yields have partly been due to the use of improved crop varieties, but mainly due to the use of better management practices and use of agrochemicals (fertilisers and pesticides).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Plants, bacteria, fungi and animals whose genes have been altered by manipulation are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Transgenic organisms</option>
            <option id="B">Genetically Modified Organisms (GMO)</option>
            <option id="C">Mutated organisms</option>
            <option id="D">Hybrid organisms</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Plants, bacteria, fungi and animals whose genes have been altered by manipulation are called Genetically Modified Organisms (GMO).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What was the first clinical application of gene therapy?</text>
            <option id="A">Treatment of cystic fibrosis</option>
            <option id="B">Treatment of Adenosine deaminase (ADA) deficiency</option>
            <option id="C">Treatment of hemophilia</option>
            <option id="D">Treatment of sickle cell anemia</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The first clinical gene therapy was given in 1990 to a 4-year old girl with adenosine deaminase (ADA) deficiency. This enzyme is crucial for the immune system to function.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which bacterium is extensively used to produce 'Bt toxin', an insecticidal protein?</text>
            <option id="A">Bacillus subtilis</option>
            <option id="B">Bacillus thuringiensis</option>
            <option id="C">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</option>
            <option id="D">Escherichia coli</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Bt toxin is produced by a bacterium called Bacillus thuringiensis (Bt for short). Bt toxin gene has been cloned from the bacteria and been expressed in plants to provide resistance to insects.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Transgenic animals are animals that have had their DNA manipulated to possess and express:</text>
            <option id="A">Only their own genes</option>
            <option id="B">Genes from only closely related species</option>
            <option id="C">An extra (foreign) gene</option>
            <option id="D">A mutated version of their own genes only</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Animals that have had their DNA manipulated to possess and express an extra (foreign) gene are known as transgenic animals. Transgenic rats, rabbits, pigs, sheep, cows and fish have been produced.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a critical research area of biotechnology?</text>
            <option id="A">Providing the best catalyst in the form of improved organism usually a microbe or pure enzyme</option>
            <option id="B">Creating optimal conditions through engineering for a catalyst to act</option>
            <option id="C">Downstream processing technologies to purify the protein/organic compound</option>
            <option id="D">Developing new surgical techniques for transplanting organs</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Three critical research areas of biotechnology are: (i) Providing the best catalyst in the form of improved organism usually a microbe or pure enzyme. (ii) Creating optimal conditions through engineering for a catalyst to act, and (iii) Downstream processing technologies to purify the protein/organic compound.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following methods of increasing food production has the limitation of not increasing yields much further than what has already been achieved?</text>
            <option id="A">Agro-chemical based agriculture</option>
            <option id="B">Organic agriculture</option>
            <option id="C">Genetically engineered crop-based agriculture</option>
            <option id="D">Tissue culture</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The Green Revolution succeeded in tripling the food supply but yet it was not enough to feed the growing human population. Increased yields have partly been due to the use of improved crop varieties, but mainly due to the use of better management practices and use of agrochemicals (fertilisers and pesticides). However, for farmers in the developing world, agrochemicals are often too expensive, and further increases in yield with existing varieties are not possible using conventional breeding.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Golden rice is a genetically modified crop enriched with:</text>
            <option id="A">Vitamin A</option>
            <option id="B">Vitamin C</option>
            <option id="C">Vitamin D</option>
            <option id="D">Protein</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Genetically Modified Organisms (GMO) have been created for various purposes. One such example is Vitamin 'A' enriched rice, commonly known as golden rice.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In agriculture, relying only on traditional breeding techniques could not keep pace with the demand for food. This led to the adoption of:</text>
            <option id="A">The Green Revolution</option>
            <option id="B">The Blue Revolution</option>
            <option id="C">The White Revolution</option>
            <option id="D">The Industrial Revolution</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The Green Revolution succeeded in tripling the food supply but yet it was not enough to feed the growing human population.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Plants, bacteria, fungi and animals whose genes have been altered by manipulation are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Mutants</option>
            <option id="B">Hybrids</option>
            <option id="C">Genetically Modified Organisms (GMO)</option>
            <option id="D">Clones</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Plants, bacteria, fungi and animals whose genes have been altered by manipulation are called Genetically Modified Organisms (GMO).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Genetic modification in plants has been useful in many ways. Which of the following is NOT one of those ways?</text>
            <option id="A">Made crops more tolerant to abiotic stresses</option>
            <option id="B">Reduced reliance on chemical pesticides</option>
            <option id="C">Decreased the nutritional value of food</option>
            <option id="D">Helped to reduce post harvest losses</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Genetic modification has: (i) made crops more tolerant to abiotic stresses (cold, drought, salt, heat). (ii) reduced reliance on chemical pesticides (pest-resistant crops). (iii) helped to reduce post harvest losses. (iv) increased efficiency of mineral usage by plants (this prevents early exhaustion of fertility of soil). (v) enhanced nutritional value of food, e.g., Vitamin 'A' enriched rice.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In mammals, including humans, insulin is synthesised as a pro-hormone. What needs to happen for it to become a fully mature and functional hormone?</text>
            <option id="A">It needs to bind with zinc</option>
            <option id="B">It needs to undergo transcription</option>
            <option id="C">The extra stretch called the C peptide needs to be removed</option>
            <option id="D">It needs to add an A peptide</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In mammals, including humans, insulin is synthesised as a pro-hormone... which contains an extra stretch called the C peptide. This C peptide is not present in the mature insulin and is removed during maturation into insulin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What was the main challenge for producing insulin using recombinant DNA techniques?</text>
            <option id="A">Finding the insulin gene</option>
            <option id="B">Extracting insulin from bacteria</option>
            <option id="C">Getting insulin assembled into a mature form</option>
            <option id="D">Injecting it into patients</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The main challenge for production of insulin using rDNA techniques was getting insulin assembled into a mature form.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In 1983, which American company prepared two DNA sequences corresponding to A and B, chains of human insulin?</text>
            <option id="A">Pfizer</option>
            <option id="B">Eli Lilly</option>
            <option id="C">Moderna</option>
            <option id="D">Johnson &amp; Johnson</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In 1983, Eli Lilly an American company prepared two DNA sequences corresponding to A and B, chains of human insulin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>For effective treatment of a disease, early diagnosis and understanding its pathophysiology are very important. Which of the following techniques serves the purpose of early diagnosis?</text>
            <option id="A">Conventional serum and urine analysis</option>
            <option id="B">Recombinant DNA technology, PCR, and ELISA</option>
            <option id="C">X-ray and MRI</option>
            <option id="D">Gene therapy</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>For effective treatment of a disease, early diagnosis and understanding its pathophysiology is very important. Using conventional methods of diagnosis (serum and urine analysis, etc.) early detection is not possible. Recombinant DNA technology, Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) and Enzyme Linked Immuno-sorbent Assay (ELISA) are some of the techniques that serve the purpose of early diagnosis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Why are conventional methods of diagnosis (like serum and urine analysis) not suitable for early detection of a disease?</text>
            <option id="A">They are too expensive</option>
            <option id="B">By the time symptoms appear and these tests are positive, the concentration of the pathogen is already very high</option>
            <option id="C">They require highly trained personnel</option>
            <option id="D">They can only detect viruses, not bacteria</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Presence of a pathogen (bacteria, viruses, etc.) is normally suspected only when the pathogen has produced a disease symptom. By this time the concentration of pathogen is already very high in the body. However, very low concentration of a bacteria or virus... can be detected by amplification of their nucleic acid by PCR.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How does PCR (Polymerase Chain Reaction) help in the early detection of a pathogen?</text>
            <option id="A">By directly killing the pathogen</option>
            <option id="B">By amplifying the nucleic acid of the pathogen, even when its concentration is very low</option>
            <option id="C">By detecting antibodies against the pathogen</option>
            <option id="D">By sequencing the entire genome of the patient</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>However, very low concentration of a bacteria or virus (at a time when the symptoms of the disease are not yet visible) can be detected by amplification of their nucleic acid by PCR.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>For what purpose was the first transgenic cow, Rosie, produced in 1997?</text>
            <option id="A">To produce meat with less fat</option>
            <option id="B">To produce human protein-enriched milk</option>
            <option id="C">To be resistant to foot-and-mouth disease</option>
            <option id="D">To grow faster and larger</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In 1997, the first transgenic cow, Rosie, produced human protein-enriched milk (2.4 grams per litre).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What was the specific human protein present in the milk produced by the transgenic cow Rosie?</text>
            <option id="A">Human alpha-lactalbumin</option>
            <option id="B">Human insulin</option>
            <option id="C">Alpha-1-antitrypsin</option>
            <option id="D">Human growth hormone</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The milk contained the human alpha-lactalbumin and was nutritionally a more balanced product for human babies than natural cow-milk.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Transgenic mice are being developed for use in testing the safety of vaccines before they are used on humans. Which vaccine is specifically mentioned in this context?</text>
            <option id="A">COVID-19 vaccine</option>
            <option id="B">Polio vaccine</option>
            <option id="C">Rabies vaccine</option>
            <option id="D">Hepatitis B vaccine</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Vaccine safety: Transgenic mice are being developed for use in testing the safety of vaccines before they are used on humans. Transgenic mice are being used to test the safety of the polio vaccine.</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>The proteins encoded by the genes cryIAc and cryIIAb control which of the following pests?</text>
            <option id="A">Cotton bollworms</option>
            <option id="B">Corn borer</option>
            <option id="C">Aphids</option>
            <option id="D">Nematodes</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The proteins encoded by the genes cryIAc and cryIIAb control the cotton bollworms, whereas the protein encoded by cryIAb controls the corn borer.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>RNA interference (RNAi) takes place in all eukaryotic organisms as a method of:</text>
            <option id="A">Cellular division</option>
            <option id="B">Cellular defense</option>
            <option id="C">Protein synthesis</option>
            <option id="D">DNA replication</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>RNA interference (RNAi) takes place in all eukaryotic organisms as a method of cellular defense. This method involves silencing of a specific mRNA due to a complementary dsRNA molecule.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In mammals, including humans, insulin is synthesized as a pro-hormone. What needs to be removed for it to become a fully mature and functional hormone?</text>
            <option id="A">A chain</option>
            <option id="B">B chain</option>
            <option id="C">C peptide</option>
            <option id="D">Disulphide bridges</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Pro-insulin contains an extra stretch called the C peptide. This C peptide is not present in the mature insulin and is removed during maturation into insulin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Transgenic mice are primarily being developed for which of the following purposes?</text>
            <option id="A">To increase meat production</option>
            <option id="B">For use in testing the safety of vaccines before they are used on humans</option>
            <option id="C">To study the evolution of mammals</option>
            <option id="D">To produce human proteins like alpha-lactalbumin</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Transgenic mice are being developed for use in testing the safety of vaccines before they are used on humans. For example, they have been used to test the safety of the polio vaccine.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Indian Government has set up an organization that makes decisions regarding the validity of GM research and the safety of introducing GM-organisms for public services. What is it called?</text>
            <option id="A">ICAR</option>
            <option id="B">GEAC</option>
            <option id="C">CSIR</option>
            <option id="D">IARI</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Indian Government has set up organizations such as GEAC (Genetic Engineering Approval Committee), which makes decisions regarding the validity of GM research and the safety of introducing GM-organisms for public services.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which peptide is absent in mature human insulin but present in pro-insulin?</text>
            <option id="A">A peptide</option>
            <option id="B">B peptide</option>
            <option id="C">C peptide</option>
            <option id="D">D peptide</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Pro-insulin contains an extra stretch called the C peptide. This C peptide is not present in the mature insulin and is removed during maturation into insulin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>RNA interference (RNAi) involves the silencing of a specific mRNA due to a complementary dsRNA molecule. In which organisms does RNAi take place as a method of cellular defense?</text>
            <option id="A">Only in bacteria</option>
            <option id="B">Only in viruses</option>
            <option id="C">All eukaryotic organisms</option>
            <option id="D">All prokaryotic organisms</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>RNAi takes place in all eukaryotic organisms as a method of cellular defense. This method involves silencing of a specific mRNA due to a complementary dsRNA molecule.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The use of bio-resources by multinational companies and other organisations without proper authorisation from the countries and people concerned without compensatory payment is termed as:</text>
            <option id="A">Bioprospecting</option>
            <option id="B">Biopiracy</option>
            <option id="C">Bioethics</option>
            <option id="D">Bioremediation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Biopiracy is the term used to refer to the use of bio-resources by multinational companies and other organisations without proper authorisation from the countries and people concerned without compensatory payment.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>ELISA is a diagnostic technique based on the principle of:</text>
            <option id="A">Antigen-antibody interaction</option>
            <option id="B">DNA amplification</option>
            <option id="C">RNA interference</option>
            <option id="D">Radioactive tracing</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>ELISA (Enzyme Linked Immuno-sorbent Assay) is based on the principle of antigen-antibody interaction. Infection by pathogen can be detected by the presence of antigens (proteins, glycoproteins, etc.) or by detecting the antibodies synthesised against the pathogen.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Golden rice is a transgenic variety of rice, which has been genetically engineered to produce:</text>
            <option id="A">Vitamin C</option>
            <option id="B">Beta-carotene (provitamin A)</option>
            <option id="C">High protein content</option>
            <option id="D">Bt toxin</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Golden rice is a genetically modified variety of rice (Oryza sativa) which has been developed to biosynthesize beta-carotene, a precursor of Vitamin A, in the edible parts of rice. It helps combat Vitamin A deficiency.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The protein alpha-1 antitrypsin, produced by transgenic animals, is used to treat which human disease?</text>
            <option id="A">Cystic fibrosis</option>
            <option id="B">Emphysema</option>
            <option id="C">Alzheimer's disease</option>
            <option id="D">Phenylketonuria</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Transgenic animals that produce useful biological products can be created by the introduction of the portion of DNA (or genes) which codes for a particular product such as human protein (alpha-1-antitrypsin) used to treat emphysema.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>About 95% of all existing transgenic animals are:</text>
            <option id="A">Pigs</option>
            <option id="B">Cows</option>
            <option id="C">Mice</option>
            <option id="D">Sheep</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Transgenic rats, rabbits, pigs, sheep, cows and fish have been produced, although over 95 per cent of all existing transgenic animals are mice.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>For testing the safety of polio vaccines before human trials, which transgenic animal has been primarily developed and used?</text>
            <option id="A">Transgenic sheep</option>
            <option id="B">Transgenic monkeys</option>
            <option id="C">Transgenic mice</option>
            <option id="D">Transgenic rabbits</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Transgenic mice are being developed for use in testing the safety of vaccines before they are used on humans. Transgenic mice are being used to test the safety of the polio vaccine.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT an advantage of genetically modified (GM) crops?</text>
            <option id="A">Increased reliance on chemical pesticides</option>
            <option id="B">Enhanced nutritional value of food</option>
            <option id="C">Increased efficiency of mineral usage by plants</option>
            <option id="D">More tolerance to abiotic stresses (cold, drought, salt, heat)</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>GM crops actually help to *reduce* reliance on chemical pesticides (pest-resistant crops). Other options are true advantages of GM plants.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Bt cotton is highly resistant to which of the following groups of insects?</text>
            <option id="A">Lepidopterans (tobacco budworm, armyworm)</option>
            <option id="B">Coleopterans (beetles)</option>
            <option id="C">Dipterans (flies, mosquitoes)</option>
            <option id="D">All of the above</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Some strains of Bacillus thuringiensis produce proteins that kill certain insects such as lepidopterans (tobacco budworm, armyworm), coleopterans (beetles) and dipterans (flies, mosquitoes).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In humans, insulin is synthesized as a prohormone. What peptide is removed during the maturation of proinsulin into active insulin?</text>
            <option id="A">A peptide</option>
            <option id="B">B peptide</option>
            <option id="C">C peptide</option>
            <option id="D">Signal peptide</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In mammals, including humans, insulin is synthesised as a pro-hormone (like a pro-enzyme, the pro-hormone also needs to be processed before it becomes a fully mature and functional hormone) which contains an extra stretch called the C peptide. This C peptide is not present in the mature insulin and is removed during maturation into insulin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which company successfully produced the first genetically engineered human insulin in 1983?</text>
            <option id="A">Biocon</option>
            <option id="B">Eli Lilly</option>
            <option id="C">Genentech</option>
            <option id="D">Pfizer</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In 1983, Eli Lilly, an American company, prepared two DNA sequences corresponding to A and B, chains of human insulin and introduced them in plasmids of E. coli to produce insulin chains. Chains A and B were produced separately, extracted and combined by creating disulfide bonds to form human insulin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first clinical gene therapy was given for the deficiency of Adenosine Deaminase (ADA). Why is ADA crucial for the body?</text>
            <option id="A">It is essential for digestion of carbohydrates.</option>
            <option id="B">It is essential for the immune system to function.</option>
            <option id="C">It regulates blood sugar levels.</option>
            <option id="D">It is required for blood clotting.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The first clinical gene therapy was given in 1990 to a 4-year old girl with adenosine deaminase (ADA) deficiency. This enzyme is crucial for the immune system to function.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered a method of molecular diagnosis that enables early detection of diseases before symptoms appear?</text>
            <option id="A">Serum and urine analysis</option>
            <option id="B">X-ray</option>
            <option id="C">Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR)</option>
            <option id="D">ECG</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Using conventional methods of diagnosis (serum and urine analysis, etc.) early detection is not possible. Recombinant DNA technology, Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) and Enzyme Linked Immuno-sorbent Assay (ELISA) are some of the techniques that serve the purpose of early diagnosis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Genetic modification has NOT been used to:</text>
            <option id="A">Make crops more tolerant to abiotic stresses</option>
            <option id="B">Reduce reliance on chemical pesticides</option>
            <option id="C">Decrease post-harvest losses</option>
            <option id="D">Decrease the nutritional value of food</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>GM has been used to create tailor-made plants to supply alternative resources to industries, increase efficiency of mineral usage by plants, and enhance nutritional value of food, e.g., golden rice, i.e., Vitamin 'A' enriched rice. It is not meant to decrease nutritional value.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Bt toxin is produced by a bacterium called:</text>
            <option id="A">Bacillus thuringiensis</option>
            <option id="B">Escherichia coli</option>
            <option id="C">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</option>
            <option id="D">Thermus aquaticus</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Bt toxin is produced by a bacterium called Bacillus thuringiensis (Bt for short). Bt toxin gene has been cloned from the bacteria and been expressed in plants to provide resistance to insects without the need for insecticides.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Why does the Bt toxin not kill the Bacillus thuringiensis bacterium itself?</text>
            <option id="A">The bacterium has a resistant gene</option>
            <option id="B">The toxin is produced in an inactive crystalline form</option>
            <option id="C">The bacterium lacks the target receptor</option>
            <option id="D">The toxin is immediately excreted from the cell</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Bt toxin protein exist as inactive protoxins but once an insect ingest the inactive toxin, it is converted into an active form of toxin due to the alkaline pH of the gut which solubilise the crystals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The active Bt toxin binds to the surface of midgut epithelial cells in insects and creates pores that cause:</text>
            <option id="A">Cell swelling and lysis</option>
            <option id="B">Cell shrinking</option>
            <option id="C">Uncontrolled cell division</option>
            <option id="D">Immediate paralysis of the nervous system</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The activated toxin binds to the surface of midgut epithelial cells and create pores that cause cell swelling and lysis and eventually cause death of the insect.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In Bt cotton, the Bt toxin exists as an inactive protoxin. What causes its conversion to an active form in the insect's body?</text>
            <option id="A">The acidic pH of the insect's stomach</option>
            <option id="B">The alkaline pH of the insect's gut</option>
            <option id="C">Specific enzymes present in the insect's saliva</option>
            <option id="D">The high temperature of the insect's body</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Actually, the Bt toxin protein exist as inactive protoxins but once an insect ingest the inactive toxin, it is converted into an active form of toxin due to the alkaline pH of the gut which solubilise the crystals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The activated Bt toxin binds to the surface of midgut epithelial cells and creates pores. What does this lead to?</text>
            <option id="A">Rapid multiplication of the cells</option>
            <option id="B">Secretion of digestive enzymes</option>
            <option id="C">Cell swelling and lysis, causing death of the insect</option>
            <option id="D">Starvation of the insect by blocking food passage</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The activated toxin binds to the surface of midgut epithelial cells and create pores that cause cell swelling and lysis and eventually cause death of the insect.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>RNA interference (RNAi) is a method of cellular defense in all eukaryotes. It involves silencing of a specific mRNA due to:</text>
            <option id="A">A complementary dsRNA molecule binding to and preventing translation</option>
            <option id="B">A single-stranded DNA binding to the mRNA</option>
            <option id="C">Proteins degrading the mRNA</option>
            <option id="D">Ribosomes failing to attach to the mRNA</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>RNAi takes place in all eukaryotic organisms as a method of cellular defense. This method involves silencing of a specific mRNA due to a complementary dsRNA molecule that binds to and prevents translation of the mRNA (silencing).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which nematode infects the roots of tobacco plants and causes a great reduction in yield?</text>
            <option id="A">Ascaris lumbricoides</option>
            <option id="B">Wuchereria bancrofti</option>
            <option id="C">Meloidegyne incognitia</option>
            <option id="D">Ancylostoma duodenale</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>A nematode Meloidegyne incognitia infects the roots of tobacco plants and causes a great reduction in yield. A novel strategy was adopted to prevent this infection which was based on the process of RNA interference (RNAi).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Bt toxin gene has been cloned from the bacteria and expressed in plants to provide resistance to insects without the need for:</text>
            <option id="A">Fertilizers</option>
            <option id="B">Insecticides</option>
            <option id="C">Irrigation</option>
            <option id="D">Weedicides</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Bt toxin gene has been cloned from the bacteria and been expressed in plants to provide resistance to insects without the need for insecticides; in effect created a bio-pesticide.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which strains of Bacillus thuringiensis produce proteins that kill certain insects such as lepidopterans, coleopterans and dipterans?</text>
            <option id="A">Only pathogenic strains</option>
            <option id="B">Some specific strains</option>
            <option id="C">All strains</option>
            <option id="D">Genetically modified strains only</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some strains of Bacillus thuringiensis produce proteins that kill certain insects such as lepidopterans (tobacco budworm, armyworm), coleopterans (beetles) and dipterans (flies, mosquitoes).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During a particular phase of their growth, Bacillus thuringiensis forms protein crystals containing a toxic:</text>
            <option id="A">Enzyme</option>
            <option id="B">Insecticidal protein</option>
            <option id="C">Antibiotic</option>
            <option id="D">Hormone</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>B. thuringiensis forms protein crystals during a particular phase of their growth. These crystals contain a toxic insecticidal protein.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The choice of the Bt toxin gene used in a transgenic plant depends upon the:</text>
            <option id="A">Crop and the targeted pest</option>
            <option id="B">Soil type and climate</option>
            <option id="C">Irrigation facility available</option>
            <option id="D">Fertilizers used</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Specific Bt toxin genes were isolated from Bacillus thuringiensis and incorporated into the several crop plants such as cotton. The choice of genes depends upon the crop and the targeted pest, as most Bt toxins are insect-group specific.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Bacillus thuringiensis produces insecticidal proteins. Why does this toxin not kill the Bacillus itself?</text>
            <option id="A">The bacteria lack receptors for the toxin</option>
            <option id="B">The toxin exists as inactive protoxins in the bacteria</option>
            <option id="C">The bacteria have a protective cell wall</option>
            <option id="D">The toxin is immediately secreted out of the cell</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Why does this toxin not kill the Bacillus? Actually, the Bt toxin protein exist as inactive protoxins but once an insect ingest the inactive toxin, it is converted into an active form of toxin due to the alkaline pH of the gut which solubilise the crystals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What converts the inactive Bt protoxin into an active form once ingested by an insect?</text>
            <option id="A">The acidic pH of the insect gut</option>
            <option id="B">The alkaline pH of the insect gut</option>
            <option id="C">The body temperature of the insect</option>
            <option id="D">Enzymes secreted in the insect's saliva</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Actually, the Bt toxin protein exist as inactive protoxins but once an insect ingest the inactive toxin, it is converted into an active form of toxin due to the alkaline pH of the gut which solubilise the crystals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What happens after the activated Bt toxin binds to the surface of midgut epithelial cells in the insect?</text>
            <option id="A">It causes the cells to rapidly divide</option>
            <option id="B">It creates pores that cause cell swelling and lysis</option>
            <option id="C">It stops the absorption of nutrients</option>
            <option id="D">It paralyzes the insect's nervous system</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The activated toxin binds to the surface of midgut epithelial cells and create pores that cause cell swelling and lysis and eventually cause death of the insect.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which specific pest does the nematode Meloidegyne incognitia infect, causing a great reduction in yield?</text>
            <option id="A">Roots of tobacco plants</option>
            <option id="B">Leaves of cotton plants</option>
            <option id="C">Stems of maize plants</option>
            <option id="D">Fruits of tomato plants</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>A nematode Meloidegyne incognitia infects the roots of tobacco plants and causes a great reduction in yield.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How did Eli Lilly produce human insulin using E. coli?</text>
            <option id="A">By introducing both A and B sequences into the same plasmid</option>
            <option id="B">By introducing sequences for A and B chains into separate plasmids of E. coli, extracting them, and combining them by creating disulfide bonds</option>
            <option id="C">By introducing the pro-hormone gene and letting E. coli remove the C peptide</option>
            <option id="D">By chemically synthesizing the entire protein</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In 1983, Eli Lilly an American company prepared two DNA sequences corresponding to A and B, chains of human insulin and introduced them in plasmids of E. coli to produce insulin chains. Chains A and B were produced separately, extracted and combined by creating disulfide bonds to form human insulin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Gene therapy is an attempt to do what?</text>
            <option id="A">To clone a human being</option>
            <option id="B">To correct a gene defect that has been diagnosed in a child or embryo</option>
            <option id="C">To map the human genome</option>
            <option id="D">To determine paternity</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Gene therapy is an attempt to do this. Gene therapy is a collection of methods that allows correction of a gene defect that has been diagnosed in a child/embryo.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first clinical gene therapy was given in 1990 to a 4-year old girl with a deficiency of which enzyme?</text>
            <option id="A">DNA polymerase</option>
            <option id="B">Adenosine deaminase (ADA)</option>
            <option id="C">Restriction endonuclease</option>
            <option id="D">Insulinase</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The first clinical gene therapy was given in 1990 to a 4-year old girl with adenosine deaminase (ADA) deficiency.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the crucial role of the enzyme adenosine deaminase (ADA) in the human body?</text>
            <option id="A">It digests carbohydrates</option>
            <option id="B">It is crucial for the immune system to function</option>
            <option id="C">It transports oxygen in the blood</option>
            <option id="D">It builds muscle tissue</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The first clinical gene therapy was given in 1990 to a 4-year old girl with adenosine deaminase (ADA) deficiency. This enzyme is crucial for the immune system to function.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>PCR is now routinely used to detect HIV in suspected AIDS patients. What is another important clinical application of PCR?</text>
            <option id="A">To measure blood glucose levels</option>
            <option id="B">To detect mutations in genes in suspected cancer patients</option>
            <option id="C">To produce insulin</option>
            <option id="D">To determine blood groups</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>PCR is now routinely used to detect HIV in suspected AIDS patients. It is being used to detect mutations in genes in suspected cancer patients too. It is a powerful techqnique to identify many other genetic disorders.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In molecular diagnosis using an autoradiogram, a single-stranded DNA or RNA tagged with a radioactive molecule is called a:</text>
            <option id="A">Primer</option>
            <option id="B">Vector</option>
            <option id="C">Probe</option>
            <option id="D">Ligand</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>A single stranded DNA or RNA, tagged with a radioactive molecule (probe) is allowed to hybridise to its complementary DNA in a clone of cells followed by detection using autoradiography.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When using a radioactive probe to detect a mutated gene via autoradiography, why does the mutated gene not appear on the photographic film?</text>
            <option id="A">Because the probe destroys the mutated gene</option>
            <option id="B">Because the mutated gene is washed away</option>
            <option id="C">Because the probe will not have complementarity with the mutated gene</option>
            <option id="D">Because the mutated gene absorbs the radiation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The clone having the mutated gene will hence not appear on the photographic film, because the probe will not have complementarity with the mutated gene.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the underlying principle of ELISA (Enzyme Linked Immuno-sorbent Assay)?</text>
            <option id="A">Amplification of nucleic acids</option>
            <option id="B">Antigen-antibody interaction</option>
            <option id="C">DNA hybridization</option>
            <option id="D">Gel electrophoresis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>ELISA is based on the principle of antigen-antibody interaction. Infection by pathogen can be detected by the presence of antigens (proteins, glycoproteins, etc.) or by detecting the antibodies synthesised against the pathogen.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If testing vaccines on transgenic mice is found to be successful and reliable, they could replace the use of which animal in vaccine testing?</text>
            <option id="A">Pigs</option>
            <option id="B">Cows</option>
            <option id="C">Monkeys</option>
            <option id="D">Dogs</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Transgenic mice are being used to test the safety of the polio vaccine. If successful and found to be reliable, they could replace the use of monkeys to test the safety of batches of the vaccine.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Transgenic animals are made that carry genes which make them more sensitive to toxic substances than non-transgenic animals. What is the purpose of this?</text>
            <option id="A">To study the disease mechanism of the toxin</option>
            <option id="B">For chemical safety (toxicity) testing</option>
            <option id="C">To produce antidotes against the toxins</option>
            <option id="D">To selectively breed these animals</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Chemical safety testing: This is known as toxicity/safety testing. ... Transgenic animals are made that carry genes which make them more sensitive to toxic substances than non-transgenic animals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the advantage of using transgenic animals for toxicity testing?</text>
            <option id="A">They never die from the toxins</option>
            <option id="B">It allows us to obtain results in less time</option>
            <option id="C">It eliminates the need for human trials</option>
            <option id="D">They do not feel pain</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>They are then exposed to the toxic substances and the effects studied. Toxicity testing in such animals will allow us to obtain results in less time.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The manipulation of living organisms by the human race requires regulation. Which Indian organization makes decisions regarding the validity of GM research and the safety of introducing GM-organisms for public services?</text>
            <option id="A">Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR)</option>
            <option id="B">Genetic Engineering Appraisal Committee (GEAC)</option>
            <option id="C">Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR)</option>
            <option id="D">Ministry of Environment and Forests (MoEF)</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Therefore, the Indian Government has set up organisations such as GEAC (Genetic Engineering Appraisal Committee), which will make decisions regarding the validity of GM research and the safety of introducing GM-organisms for public services.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>In 1983, Eli Lilly, an American company, prepared two DNA sequences corresponding to A and B chains of human insulin. How were they produced to form human insulin (Humulin)?</text>
            <option id="A">They were introduced in plasmids of Agrobacterium tumefaciens and chains were combined using restriction enzymes.</option>
            <option id="B">They were introduced in plasmids of E. coli to produce insulin chains, extracted separately, and combined by creating disulfide bonds.</option>
            <option id="C">They were inserted into retroviruses and grown in human cell cultures.</option>
            <option id="D">They were grown directly in a bioreactor without a host organism.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Eli Lilly prepared two DNA sequences corresponding to A and B, chains of human insulin and introduced them in plasmids of E. coli to produce insulin chains. Chains A and B were produced separately, extracted and combined by creating disulfide bonds to form human insulin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following approaches is used to cure ADA deficiency by modifying the patient's cells?</text>
            <option id="A">Administering ADA enzyme via continuous IV infusion.</option>
            <option id="B">Extracting lymphocytes, introducing a functional ADA cDNA using a retroviral vector, and returning them to the patient.</option>
            <option id="C">Using RNA interference to silence the defective ADA gene.</option>
            <option id="D">Injecting Agrobacterium tumefaciens carrying the ADA gene directly into the bone marrow.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In gene therapy for ADA deficiency, lymphocytes from the blood of the patient are grown in a culture outside the body. A functional ADA cDNA (using a retroviral vector) is then introduced into these lymphocytes, which are subsequently returned to the patient.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Nematode resistance in tobacco plants has been introduced using Agrobacterium vectors to express nematode-specific genes. Which RNAi-based mechanism is responsible for this resistance?</text>
            <option id="A">The host plant produces a single-stranded RNA that degrades the nematode's DNA.</option>
            <option id="B">The introduced DNA produces both sense and anti-sense RNA in the host, forming dsRNA that silences the specific mRNA of the nematode.</option>
            <option id="C">The nematode produces dsRNA that acts as a toxin against its own cells upon entering the plant roots.</option>
            <option id="D">The plant produces a toxic protein similar to Bt toxin that is lethal to the nematode.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Using Agrobacterium vectors, nematode-specific genes were introduced into the host plant. The introduction of DNA was such that it produced both sense and anti-sense RNA in the host cells. These two RNAs being complementary formed a dsRNA that initiated RNAi and silenced the specific mRNA of the nematode.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Transgenic animals that produce useful biological products can be created by the introduction of a portion of DNA which codes for a particular product. For which human disease has the protein alpha-1-antitrypsin been produced transgenically?</text>
            <option id="A">Cystic fibrosis</option>
            <option id="B">Phenylketonuria (PKU)</option>
            <option id="C">Emphysema</option>
            <option id="D">Alzheimer's disease</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Alpha-1-antitrypsin is a protein produced transgenically to treat emphysema. Similar attempts are being made for treatment of phenylketonuria (PKU) and cystic fibrosis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following statements about the ethical issues of biotechnology is INCORRECT?</text>
            <option id="A">The Indian Government has set up GEAC to make decisions regarding the validity of GM research.</option>
            <option id="B">Biopiracy refers to the use of bio-resources by multinational companies without proper authorization from the countries concerned.</option>
            <option id="C">A patent granted in the USA for Basmati rice allowed an American company to claim a monopoly on a variety derived from Indian farmers' varieties.</option>
            <option id="D">All transgenic organisms are entirely predictable in their behavior when introduced into wild ecosystems.</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The modification/usage of living organisms for public services (as food and medicine sources, for example) has also created problems with patents granted for the same. The behavior of transgenic organisms when introduced into wild ecosystems is completely unpredictable, making statement D incorrect.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The genetically modified brinjal in India has been developed for:</text>
            <option id="A">Enhancing shelf life</option>
            <option id="B">Insect-resistance</option>
            <option id="C">Drought-resistance</option>
            <option id="D">Enhancing mineral content</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Bt brinjal was developed in India to provide resistance against lepidopteran insects (like fruit and shoot borer), similar to how Bt cotton works.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following bodies in India makes decisions regarding the validity of GM research and the safety of introducing GM-organisms for public services?</text>
            <option id="A">Genetic Engineering Approval Committee (GEAC)</option>
            <option id="B">Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR)</option>
            <option id="C">Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR)</option>
            <option id="D">Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR)</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The Indian Government has set up organizations such as GEAC (Genetic Engineering Approval Committee), which makes decisions regarding the validity of GM research and the safety of introducing GM-organisms for public services.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following animals are most widely used for testing the safety of vaccines before they are used on humans?</text>
            <option id="A">Rabbits</option>
            <option id="B">Transgenic mice</option>
            <option id="C">Monkeys</option>
            <option id="D">Guinea pigs</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Transgenic mice are being developed for use in testing the safety of vaccines before they are used on humans. Transgenic mice are being used to test the safety of the polio vaccine. If successful and found to be reliable, they could replace the use of monkeys.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which gene in Bacillus thuringiensis codes for the Bt toxin?</text>
            <option id="A">lacZ gene</option>
            <option id="B">cry gene</option>
            <option id="C">ampR gene</option>
            <option id="D">tetR gene</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Bt toxin is coded by a gene named cry. There are a number of them, for example, the proteins encoded by the genes cryIAc and cryIIAb control the cotton bollworms, that of cryIAb controls corn borer.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>To which class of enzymes does the enzyme ADA (Adenosine deaminase), missing in ADA deficiency, belong?</text>
            <option id="A">Hydrolases</option>
            <option id="B">Transferases</option>
            <option id="C">Isomerases</option>
            <option id="D">Ligases</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Adenosine deaminase (ADA) is a hydrolase enzyme involved in purine metabolism. It is crucial for the immune system to function properly.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Why does the Bt toxin not kill the Bacillus thuringiensis bacterium itself?</text>
            <option id="A">The bacterium possesses an antitoxin.</option>
            <option id="B">The toxin exists as an inactive protoxin within the bacterium.</option>
            <option id="C">The bacterium has a highly resistant cell wall.</option>
            <option id="D">The toxin only targets eukaryotic ribosomes.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Actually, the Bt toxin protein exist as inactive protoxins but once an insect ingest the inactive toxin, it is converted into an active form of toxin due to the alkaline pH of the gut which solubilise the crystals. Hence it does not kill the bacterium.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The nematode Meloidegyne incognitia infects the roots of which important plant, causing a great reduction in yield?</text>
            <option id="A">Cotton</option>
            <option id="B">Tobacco</option>
            <option id="C">Tomato</option>
            <option id="D">Potato</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A nematode Meloidegyne incognitia infects the roots of tobacco plants and causes a great reduction in yield. A novel strategy was adopted to prevent this infection which was based on the process of RNA interference (RNAi).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>To study the complex factors involved in growth such as insulin-like growth factor, transgenic animals are designed with extra genes from other species. What is the primary purpose of such studies?</text>
            <option id="A">To produce cheaper meat</option>
            <option id="B">To study normal physiology and development</option>
            <option id="C">To increase the lifespan of the animals</option>
            <option id="D">To develop new pet breeds</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Transgenic animals can be specifically designed to allow the study of how genes are regulated, and how they affect the normal functions of the body and its development, e.g., study of complex factors involved in growth such as insulin-like growth factor.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>ELISA (Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent Assay) is a diagnostic test based on the principle of:</text>
            <option id="A">DNA-DNA hybridization</option>
            <option id="B">Antigen-antibody interaction</option>
            <option id="C">RNA sequencing</option>
            <option id="D">Protein denaturation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>ELISA is based on the principle of antigen-antibody interaction. Infection by pathogen can be detected by the presence of antigens (proteins, glycoproteins, etc.) or by detecting the antibodies synthesised against the pathogen.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The transgenic cow 'Rosie' produced human protein-enriched milk. Which human protein was present in her milk?</text>
            <option id="A">Human alpha-lactalbumin</option>
            <option id="B">Alpha-1-antitrypsin</option>
            <option id="C">Insulin</option>
            <option id="D">Interferon</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In 1997, the first transgenic cow, Rosie, produced human protein-enriched milk (2.4 grams per litre). The milk contained the human alpha-lactalbumin and was nutritionally a more balanced product for human babies than natural cow-milk.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The use of bio-resources by multinational companies and other organisations without proper authorisation from the countries and people concerned without compensatory payment is termed as:</text>
            <option id="A">Bioremediation</option>
            <option id="B">Biopiracy</option>
            <option id="C">Biofortification</option>
            <option id="D">Biomagnification</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Biopiracy is the term used to refer to the use of bio-resources by multinational companies and other organisations without proper authorisation from the countries and people concerned without compensatory payment.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which genes from Bacillus thuringiensis control the cotton bollworms?</text>
            <option id="A">cryIAc and cryIIAb</option>
            <option id="B">cryIAb</option>
            <option id="C">cryIIAc</option>
            <option id="D">cryIAa</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The proteins encoded by the genes cryIAc and cryIIAb control the cotton bollworms, that of cryIAb controls corn borer.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A nematode Meloidogyne incognita infects the roots of which plant, causing a great reduction in yield?</text>
            <option id="A">Cotton</option>
            <option id="B">Tobacco</option>
            <option id="C">Corn</option>
            <option id="D">Tomato</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A nematode Meloidogyne incognita infects the roots of tobacco plants and causes a great reduction in yield. A novel strategy was adopted to prevent this infection which was based on the process of RNA interference (RNAi).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>RNA interference (RNAi) takes place in all eukaryotic organisms as a method of:</text>
            <option id="A">Cellular defense</option>
            <option id="B">Energy production</option>
            <option id="C">DNA replication</option>
            <option id="D">Protein synthesis</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>RNAi takes place in all eukaryotic organisms as a method of cellular defense. This method involves silencing of a specific mRNA due to a complementary dsRNA molecule that binds to and prevents translation of the mRNA (silencing).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In 1983, which American company successfully prepared two DNA sequences corresponding to A and B chains of human insulin and introduced them in plasmids of E. coli?</text>
            <option id="A">Biocon</option>
            <option id="B">Eli Lilly</option>
            <option id="C">Pfizer</option>
            <option id="D">Genentech</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In 1983, Eli Lilly an American company prepared two DNA sequences corresponding to A and B, chains of human insulin and introduced them in plasmids of E. coli to produce insulin chains.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following techniques is used for early diagnosis of diseases, long before the symptoms appear?</text>
            <option id="A">Urine analysis</option>
            <option id="B">Serum analysis</option>
            <option id="C">Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR)</option>
            <option id="D">X-ray imaging</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Using conventional methods of diagnosis (serum and urine analysis, etc.) early detection is not possible. Recombinant DNA technology, Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) and Enzyme Linked Immuno-sorbent Assay (ELISA) are some of the techniques that serve the purpose of early diagnosis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>ELISA is based on the principle of:</text>
            <option id="A">Antigen-antibody interaction</option>
            <option id="B">DNA amplification</option>
            <option id="C">RNA interference</option>
            <option id="D">Autoradiography</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>ELISA is based on the principle of antigen-antibody interaction. Infection by pathogen can be detected by the presence of antigens (proteins, glycoproteins, etc.) or by detecting the antibodies synthesised against the pathogen.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The proteins encoded by the genes cryIAc and cryIIAb control the cotton bollworms, whereas that of cryIAb controls:</text>
            <option id="A">Corn borer</option>
            <option id="B">Armyworm</option>
            <option id="C">Mosquitoes</option>
            <option id="D">Beetles</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The toxin is coded by a gene named cry. There are a number of them, for example, the proteins encoded by the genes cryIAc and cryIIAb control the cotton bollworms, that of cryIAb controls corn borer.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In RNA interference (RNAi), the source of the complementary RNA could be from an infection by viruses having RNA genomes or mobile genetic elements called:</text>
            <option id="A">Plasmids</option>
            <option id="B">Transposons</option>
            <option id="C">Bacteriophages</option>
            <option id="D">Prions</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The source of this complementary RNA could be from an infection by viruses having RNA genomes or mobile genetic elements (transposons) that replicate via an RNA intermediate.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Using Agrobacterium vectors, nematode-specific genes were introduced into the host plant. The introduction of DNA was such that it produced:</text>
            <option id="A">Only sense RNA</option>
            <option id="B">Only antisense RNA</option>
            <option id="C">Both sense and antisense RNA in the host cells</option>
            <option id="D">A double-stranded DNA molecule</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Using Agrobacterium vectors, nematode-specific genes were introduced into the host plant. The introduction of DNA was such that it produced both sense and anti-sense RNA in the host cells. These two RNA's being complementary to each other formed a double stranded (dsRNA) that initiated RNAi.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which cellular defense mechanism takes place in all eukaryotic organisms and was used to prevent nematode infection in tobacco plants?</text>
            <option id="A">Phagocytosis</option>
            <option id="B">Apoptosis</option>
            <option id="C">RNA interference (RNAi)</option>
            <option id="D">Antibody production</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>A novel strategy was adopted to prevent this infection which was based on the process of RNA interference (RNAi). RNAi takes place in all eukaryotic organisms as a method of cellular defense.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>RNA interference (RNAi) involves the silencing of a specific mRNA due to a complementary molecule that binds to and prevents translation of the mRNA. This complementary molecule is:</text>
            <option id="A">Single-stranded RNA</option>
            <option id="B">Double-stranded RNA (dsRNA)</option>
            <option id="C">Single-stranded DNA</option>
            <option id="D">Double-stranded DNA</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>This method involves silencing of a specific mRNA due to a complementary dsRNA molecule that binds to and prevents translation of the mRNA (silencing).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When using Agrobacterium vectors to introduce nematode-specific genes into tobacco plants for RNAi, what forms the double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) that initiates RNAi?</text>
            <option id="A">Only the sense RNA produced in the host</option>
            <option id="B">The complementary sense and anti-sense RNA produced in the host cells</option>
            <option id="C">The mRNA of the nematode itself</option>
            <option id="D">Viral RNA introduced intentionally</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Using Agrobacterium vectors, nematode-specific genes were introduced into the host plant. The introduction of DNA was such that it produced both sense and anti-sense RNA in the host cells. These two RNA's being complementary to each other formed a double stranded (dsRNA) that initiated RNAi.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In some children, ADA deficiency can be cured by bone marrow transplantation or by enzyme replacement therapy. What is the main problem with these approaches?</text>
            <option id="A">They are too expensive</option>
            <option id="B">They are not completely curative</option>
            <option id="C">They cause severe allergic reactions</option>
            <option id="D">They require constant hospitalization</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In some children ADA deficiency can be cured by bone marrow transplantation; in others it can be treated by enzyme replacement therapy, in which functional ADA is given to the patient by injection. But the problem with both of these approaches that they are not completely curative.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In gene therapy for ADA deficiency, lymphocytes from the blood of the patient are grown in a culture outside the body. What is then introduced into these lymphocytes?</text>
            <option id="A">A functional ADA cDNA (using a retroviral vector)</option>
            <option id="B">Antibodies against the disease</option>
            <option id="C">Stem cells from a donor</option>
            <option id="D">The active ADA enzyme itself</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>As a first step towards gene therapy, lymphocytes from the blood of the patient are grown in a culture outside the body. A functional ADA cDNA (using a retroviral vector) is then introduced into these lymphocytes, which are subsequently returned to the patient.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Why do patients receiving gene therapy for ADA deficiency require periodic infusions of genetically engineered lymphocytes?</text>
            <option id="A">Because the vector replicates too slowly</option>
            <option id="B">Because the introduced gene is eventually expelled by the cells</option>
            <option id="C">Because the cells are not immortal and eventually die</option>
            <option id="D">Because the ADA enzyme breaks down rapidly in the blood</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>However, as these cells are not immortal, the patient requires periodic infusion of such genetically engineered lymphocytes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Animals that have had their DNA manipulated to possess and express an extra (foreign) gene are known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Cloned animals</option>
            <option id="B">Transgenic animals</option>
            <option id="C">Mutated animals</option>
            <option id="D">Hybrid animals</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Animals that have had their DNA manipulated to possess and express an extra (foreign) gene are known as transgenic animals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>While transgenic rats, rabbits, pigs, sheep, and cows have been produced, which animal constitutes over 95 per cent of all existing transgenic animals?</text>
            <option id="A">Pigs</option>
            <option id="B">Cows</option>
            <option id="C">Mice</option>
            <option id="D">Sheep</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Transgenic rats, rabbits, pigs, sheep, cows and fish have been produced, although over 95 per cent of all existing transgenic animals are mice.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>One of the reasons for producing transgenic animals is for the "Study of disease". Transgenic models exist for many human diseases. Which of the following is NOT explicitly mentioned as a disease for which transgenic models exist?</text>
            <option id="A">Cancer</option>
            <option id="B">Cystic fibrosis</option>
            <option id="C">Alzheimer's disease</option>
            <option id="D">Tuberculosis</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Today transgenic models exist for many human diseases such as cancer, cystic fibrosis, rheumatoid arthritis and Alzheimer's.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The use of bio-resources by multinational companies and other organisations without proper authorisation from the countries and people concerned without compensatory payment is termed as:</text>
            <option id="A">Biotechnology</option>
            <option id="B">Bioethics</option>
            <option id="C">Biopiracy</option>
            <option id="D">Biopatent</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Biopiracy is the term used to refer to the use of bio-resources by multinational companies and other organisations without proper authorisation from the countries and people concerned without compensatory payment.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which country is estimated to have over 200,000 varieties of rice alone?</text>
            <option id="A">China</option>
            <option id="B">Japan</option>
            <option id="C">India</option>
            <option id="D">USA</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>There are an estimated 200,000 varieties of rice in India alone. The diversity of rice in India is one of the richest in the world.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In 1997, an American company got patent rights on Basmati rice through the US Patent and Trademark Office. How did they 'create' this "new" variety?</text>
            <option id="A">By genetically modifying it to produce more vitamin A</option>
            <option id="B">By crossing Indian Basmati with semi-dwarf varieties and claiming it as an invention</option>
            <option id="C">By discovering it growing wildly in the US</option>
            <option id="D">By developing a synthetic version in the lab</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In 1997, an American company got patent rights on Basmati rice... This 'new' variety of Basmati had actually been derived from Indian farmer's varieties. Indian Basmati was crossed with semi-dwarf varieties and claimed as an invention or a novelty.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>