<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="338" name="Environmental Issues">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>The Kyoto Protocol was endorsed at:</text>
            <option id="A">CoP-3</option>
            <option id="B">CoP-4</option>
            <option id="C">CoP-5</option>
            <option id="D">CoP-6</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The Kyoto Protocol was endorsed at the Third Conference of Parties (CoP-3) in Kyoto, Japan, in 1997. It is an international treaty aimed at reducing greenhouse gas emissions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is the most significant contributor to global warming?</text>
            <option id="A">CFCs</option>
            <option id="B">Methane</option>
            <option id="C">Nitrous oxide</option>
            <option id="D">Carbon dioxide</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Carbon dioxide (CO2) is the major greenhouse gas contributing to global warming, responsible for about 60% of the greenhouse effect. It is followed by methane (20%), CFCs (14%), and N2O (6%).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Biomagnification of DDT in an aquatic food chain starting from water (0.003 ppb) can reach up to what concentration in fish-eating birds?</text>
            <option id="A">2 ppm</option>
            <option id="B">5 ppm</option>
            <option id="C">25 ppm</option>
            <option id="D">50 ppm</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Biomagnification refers to the increase in concentration of a toxicant at successive trophic levels. For DDT, it starts at 0.003 ppb in water and can magnify up to 25 ppm in fish-eating birds, disrupting their calcium metabolism.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is responsible for ozone depletion in the stratosphere?</text>
            <option id="A">Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)</option>
            <option id="B">Carbon dioxide</option>
            <option id="C">Methane</option>
            <option id="D">Sulfur dioxide</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs) are primarily responsible for ozone depletion in the stratosphere. They release active chlorine atoms which degrade ozone releasing molecular oxygen.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of nutrient enrichment of water bodies, leading to algal blooms and oxygen depletion, is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Biomagnification</option>
            <option id="B">Eutrophication</option>
            <option id="C">Stratification</option>
            <option id="D">Biological oxygen demand</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Eutrophication is the natural aging of a lake by nutrient enrichment of its water. Accelerated eutrophication occurs due to human activities like adding fertilizers and sewage.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In India, the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act came into force in the year:</text>
            <option id="A">1974</option>
            <option id="B">1981</option>
            <option id="C">1986</option>
            <option id="D">1992</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In India, the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act came into force in 1981, but was amended in 1987 to include noise as an air pollutant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The thickness of the ozone layer is measured in which units?</text>
            <option id="A">Decibels (dB)</option>
            <option id="B">Dobson units (DU)</option>
            <option id="C">Parts per million (ppm)</option>
            <option id="D">Centimeters (cm)</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The thickness of the ozone in a column of air from the ground to the top of the atmosphere is measured in terms of Dobson units (DU).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following gases is the most abundant greenhouse gas in the Earth's atmosphere?</text>
            <option id="A">Methane</option>
            <option id="B">Nitrous oxide</option>
            <option id="C">Carbon dioxide</option>
            <option id="D">Chlorofluorocarbons</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Carbon dioxide (CO2) is the most abundant greenhouse gas, contributing about 60% to the total global warming effect.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What does CNG stand for?</text>
            <option id="A">Common Natural Gas</option>
            <option id="B">Compressed Natural Gas</option>
            <option id="C">Converted Natural Gas</option>
            <option id="D">Combustible Natural Gas</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>CNG stands for Compressed Natural Gas. It is considered a better fuel than petrol or diesel because it burns most efficiently, leaving very little unburnt.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB), particulate size of what diameter (in micrometres) is responsible for causing the greatest harm to human health?</text>
            <option id="A">5.0 or less</option>
            <option id="B">10.0 or less</option>
            <option id="C">2.5 or less</option>
            <option id="D">1.0 or less</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>According to Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB), particulate size 2.5 micrometers or less in diameter (PM 2.5) are responsible for causing the greatest harm to human health. These fine particulates can be breathed deep into the lungs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which device is the most widely used to remove particulate matter from the exhaust of a thermal power plant?</text>
            <option id="A">Scrubber</option>
            <option id="B">Catalytic converter</option>
            <option id="C">Electrostatic precipitator</option>
            <option id="D">Incinerator</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>There are several ways of removing particulate matter; the most widely used of which is the electrostatic precipitator, which can remove over 99 per cent particulate matter present in the exhaust from a thermal power plant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A scrubber in the exhaust of a chemical plant primarily removes gases like:</text>
            <option id="A">Sulphur dioxide</option>
            <option id="B">Carbon monoxide</option>
            <option id="C">Nitrous oxide</option>
            <option id="D">Ozone</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>A scrubber can remove gases like sulphur dioxide. In a scrubber, the exhaust is passed through a spray of water or lime.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following acts as an indicator of water pollution by organic matter?</text>
            <option id="A">Presence of large number of fish</option>
            <option id="B">High Biochemical Oxygen Demand (BOD)</option>
            <option id="C">Abundance of clean-water diatoms</option>
            <option id="D">High Dissolved Oxygen (DO)</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>High Biochemical Oxygen Demand (BOD) is a strong indicator of water pollution by organic matter, as it shows high bacterial activity consuming oxygen to break down the waste.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the effect of discharging sewage into a river on its Dissolved Oxygen (DO) levels?</text>
            <option id="A">DO levels increase</option>
            <option id="B">DO levels sharply decline</option>
            <option id="C">DO levels remain unaffected</option>
            <option id="D">DO levels fluctuate randomly</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Micro-organisms involved in biodegradation of organic matter in the receiving water body consume a lot of oxygen, and as a result there is a sharp decline in dissolved oxygen downstream from the point of sewage discharge.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The accumulation of which heavy metal causes Minamata disease?</text>
            <option id="A">Lead</option>
            <option id="B">Cadmium</option>
            <option id="C">Mercury</option>
            <option id="D">Arsenic</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Minamata disease is a neurological syndrome caused by severe mercury poisoning, historically linked to the consumption of fish from Minamata Bay, Japan, heavily polluted with methylmercury.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB), particulate size of what diameter (in micrometres) is responsible for causing the greatest harm to human health?</text>
            <option id="A">5.0 or less</option>
            <option id="B">2.5 or less</option>
            <option id="C">10.0 or less</option>
            <option id="D">7.5 or less</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>According to Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB), particulate size 2.5 micrometers or less in diameter (PM 2.5) are responsible for causing the greatest harm to human health.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Catalytic converters, having expensive metals namely platinum-palladium and rhodium as the catalysts, are fitted into automobiles for reducing emission of poisonous gases. As the exhaust passes through the catalytic converter, unburnt hydrocarbons are converted into:</text>
            <option id="A">Carbon monoxide and water</option>
            <option id="B">Carbon dioxide and water</option>
            <option id="C">Nitric oxide and oxygen</option>
            <option id="D">Ozone and water</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>As the exhaust passes through the catalytic converter, unburnt hydrocarbons are converted into carbon dioxide and water, and carbon monoxide and nitric oxide are changed to carbon dioxide and nitrogen gas, respectively.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Motor vehicles equipped with catalytic converters should use unleaded petrol because lead in the petrol:</text>
            <option id="A">Increases the consumption of fuel</option>
            <option id="B">Inactivates the catalyst</option>
            <option id="C">Corrodes the engine</option>
            <option id="D">Causes loud knocking</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Motor vehicles equipped with catalytic converter should use unleaded petrol because lead in the petrol inactivates the catalyst (platinum-palladium and rhodium).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The term "Solid waste" refers to:</text>
            <option id="A">Only industrial waste</option>
            <option id="B">Only agricultural waste</option>
            <option id="C">Everything that goes out in trash</option>
            <option id="D">Liquid waste that solidifies</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Solid wastes refer to everything that goes out in trash. Municipal solid wastes are wastes from homes, offices, stores, schools, hospitals, etc., that are collected and disposed by the municipality.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a major disadvantage of sanitary landfills?</text>
            <option id="A">They completely eliminate waste</option>
            <option id="B">There is a danger of seepage of chemicals polluting underground water resources</option>
            <option id="C">They are too expensive to construct</option>
            <option id="D">They do not accept municipal waste</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Sanitary landfills were adopted as the substitute for open-burning dumps. However, landfills are not much of a solution since the amount of garbage generation specially in the metros has increased so much that these sites are getting filled too. Also there is danger of seepage of chemicals, etc., from these landfills polluting the underground water resources.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Waste that can be degraded by natural processes is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Biodegradable</option>
            <option id="B">Recyclable</option>
            <option id="C">Non-biodegradable</option>
            <option id="D">E-waste</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>All waste that we generate can be categorised into three types – (a) bio-degradable, (b) recyclable and (c) the non-biodegradable.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is pollution according to the Environmental (Protection) Act?</text>
            <option id="A">Only the release of toxic chemicals into water</option>
            <option id="B">Any undesirable change in physical, chemical or biological characteristics of air, land, water or soil</option>
            <option id="C">The increase in global temperatures due to greenhouse gases</option>
            <option id="D">The accumulation of solid wastes in landfills</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Pollution is any undesirable change in physical, chemical or biological characteristics of air, land, water or soil. Agents that bring about such an undesirable change are called as pollutants.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In order to control environmental pollution, the Government of India passed the Environment (Protection) Act in the year:</text>
            <option id="A">1974</option>
            <option id="B">1981</option>
            <option id="C">1986</option>
            <option id="D">1992</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In order to control environmental pollution, the Government of India has passed the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 to protect and improve the quality of our environment (air, water and soil).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a major cause of air pollution?</text>
            <option id="A">Smokestacks of thermal power plants and smelters</option>
            <option id="B">Use of natural gas in homes</option>
            <option id="C">Solar panels</option>
            <option id="D">Wind turbines</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Smokestacks of thermal power plants, smelters and other industries release particulate and gaseous air pollutants together with harmless gases, such as nitrogen, oxygen, etc. These pollutants must be separated/filtered out before releasing the harmless gases into the atmosphere.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In India, the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act came into force in the year:</text>
            <option id="A">1974</option>
            <option id="B">1981</option>
            <option id="C">1987</option>
            <option id="D">1992</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In India, the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act came into force in 1981, but was amended in 1987 to include noise as an air pollutant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In which year was the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act amended to include noise as an air pollutant?</text>
            <option id="A">1981</option>
            <option id="B">1987</option>
            <option id="C">1990</option>
            <option id="D">1995</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In India, the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act came into force in 1981, but was amended in 1987 to include noise as an air pollutant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Noise is defined as:</text>
            <option id="A">Any sound produced by nature</option>
            <option id="B">Undesired high level of sound</option>
            <option id="C">Sound that can only be heard by animals</option>
            <option id="D">Sound measuring below 50 dB</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Noise is undesired high level of sound. We have got used to associating loud sounds with pleasure and entertainment not realising that noise causes psychological and physiological disorders in humans.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Simultaneously with switching to CNG, what other steps did the Delhi government take to reduce vehicular pollution?</text>
            <option id="A">Phasing out old vehicles</option>
            <option id="B">Use of unleaded petrol</option>
            <option id="C">Use of low-sulphur petrol and diesel</option>
            <option id="D">All of the above</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Simultaneously parallel steps taken in Delhi for reducing vehicular pollution include phasing out of old vehicles, use of unleaded petrol, use of low-sulphur petrol and diesel, use of catalytic converters in vehicles, as well as application of stringent pollution-level norms for vehicles.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What was the primary goal of the new auto fuel policy laid out by the Government of India?</text>
            <option id="A">To increase fuel efficiency to 50 km/l</option>
            <option id="B">To steadily reduce the sulphur and aromatic content in petrol and diesel fuels</option>
            <option id="C">To replace all petrol vehicles with electric vehicles</option>
            <option id="D">To ban the use of diesel completely</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Government of India through a new auto fuel policy has laid out a roadmap to cut down vehicular pollution in Indian cities. More stringent norms for fuels means steadily reducing the sulphur and aromatic content in petrol and diesel fuels.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Euro III norms, sulphur in diesel is to be controlled at:</text>
            <option id="A">50 parts per million (ppm)</option>
            <option id="B">150 parts per million (ppm)</option>
            <option id="C">350 parts per million (ppm)</option>
            <option id="D">500 parts per million (ppm)</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Euro III norms, for example, stipulate that sulphur be controlled at 350 parts-per-million (ppm) in diesel and 150 ppm in petrol.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following heavy metals is NOT typically associated with wastewater from industries like petroleum, paper manufacturing, and chemical manufacturing?</text>
            <option id="A">Mercury</option>
            <option id="B">Cadmium</option>
            <option id="C">Calcium</option>
            <option id="D">Lead</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Unlike domestic sewage, waste water from industries like petroleum, paper manufacturing, metal extraction and processing, chemical manufacturing, etc., often contain toxic substances, notably, heavy metals (defined as elements with density > 5 g/cm3 such as mercury, cadmium, copper, lead, etc.) and a variety of organic compounds.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Biomagnification is the process where the concentration of a toxicant increases at successive trophic levels. Why does this happen?</text>
            <option id="A">Because organisms at higher trophic levels live longer</option>
            <option id="B">Because a toxic substance accumulated by an organism cannot be metabolised or excreted</option>
            <option id="C">Because the toxicant multiplies within the organism</option>
            <option id="D">Because higher trophic levels consume water directly</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A few toxic substances, often present in industrial waste waters, can undergo biological magnification (Biomagnification) in the aquatic food chain. Biomagnification refers to increase in concentration of the toxicant at successive trophic levels. This happens because a toxic substance accumulated by an organism cannot be metabolised or excreted, and is thus passed on to the next higher trophic level.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Biomagnification is well-known for which of the following substances?</text>
            <option id="A">Nitrates and Phosphates</option>
            <option id="B">Mercury and DDT</option>
            <option id="C">Calcium and Magnesium</option>
            <option id="D">Carbon dioxide and Methane</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>This phenomenon is well-known for mercury and DDT.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Heated (thermal) wastewaters flowing out of electricity-generating units constitute another important category of pollutants. What is the effect of thermal wastewater on aquatic life?</text>
            <option id="A">It eliminates or reduces the number of organisms sensitive to high temperatures</option>
            <option id="B">It has no effect on aquatic life</option>
            <option id="C">It increases the dissolved oxygen content of the water</option>
            <option id="D">It causes the water to freeze faster in winter</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Heated (thermal) wastewaters flowing out of electricity-generating units – e.g., thermal power plants – constitute another important category of pollutants. Thermal wastewater eliminates or reduces the number of organisms sensitive to high temperature, and may enhance the growth of plants and fish in extremely cold areas but, only after causing damage to the indigenous flora and fauna.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the town of Arcata, California, a collaborative effort created an integrated wastewater treatment process. What was the role of the marshes in the second stage of this process?</text>
            <option id="A">To generate electricity</option>
            <option id="B">To act as a sanctuary for humans</option>
            <option id="C">To neutralize, absorb, and assimilate heavy metals and other pollutants</option>
            <option id="D">To chemically disinfect the water with chlorine</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The townspeople of Arcata, situated along the northern coast of California, collaborated with biologists from the Humboldt State University... The biologists developed a series of six connected marshes over 60 hectares of marshland. Appropriate plants, algae, fungi and bacteria were seeded into this area, which neutralise, absorb and assimilate the pollutants. Hence, as the water flows through the marshes, it gets purified naturally.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A citizens group in Arcata responsible for the upkeep and safeguarding of the integrated wastewater treatment project is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Save the Marshes Society</option>
            <option id="B">Friends of the Arcata Marsh (FOAM)</option>
            <option id="C">California Water Protectors</option>
            <option id="D">Arcata Environmental Group</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A citizens group called Friends of the Arcata Marsh (FOAM) are responsible for the upkeep and safeguarding of this wonderful project.</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>An electrostatic precipitator is used to control which type of pollution?</text>
            <option id="A">Water pollution</option>
            <option id="B">Noise pollution</option>
            <option id="C">Particulate air pollution</option>
            <option id="D">Soil pollution</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Electrostatic precipitators are highly efficient devices used in thermal power plants and industries to remove over 99% of particulate matter present in the exhaust by electrically charging the particles.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>High Biochemical Oxygen Demand (BOD) in a water body indicates that:</text>
            <option id="A">The water is highly pure</option>
            <option id="B">The water has high dissolved oxygen</option>
            <option id="C">The water is highly polluted with organic matter</option>
            <option id="D">The water is deficient in microorganisms</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>BOD is the amount of oxygen required by bacteria to decompose organic matter in a sample of water. High BOD indicates that the water is heavily polluted with organic matter, leading to a sharp decline in dissolved oxygen.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Ozone depletion in the stratosphere is primarily caused by:</text>
            <option id="A">Carbon dioxide</option>
            <option id="B">Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)</option>
            <option id="C">Sulfur dioxide</option>
            <option id="D">Nitrogen oxides</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs) widely used as refrigerants move to the stratosphere where UV rays act on them to release active chlorine atoms. These chlorine atoms catalyze the degradation of ozone.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of nutrient enrichment of water bodies leading to algal blooms is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Biomagnification</option>
            <option id="B">Eutrophication</option>
            <option id="C">Stratification</option>
            <option id="D">Salinization</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Eutrophication is the natural aging of a lake by nutrient enrichment (primarily nitrogen and phosphorus) of its water. Human activities can accelerate this process, known as cultural or accelerated eutrophication, causing massive algal blooms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the effect of an electrostatic precipitator installed in the exhaust of a thermal power plant?</text>
            <option id="A">It removes toxic gases like sulfur dioxide.</option>
            <option id="B">It removes particulate matter.</option>
            <option id="C">It reduces the temperature of the exhaust gas.</option>
            <option id="D">It converts carbon monoxide to carbon dioxide.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>An electrostatic precipitator can remove over 99 per cent particulate matter present in the exhaust from a thermal power plant. It is not effective for gases like sulfur dioxide, for which a scrubber is used.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The phenomenon where the concentration of toxic substances increases at successive trophic levels is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Bioremediation</option>
            <option id="B">Biomagnification</option>
            <option id="C">Bioaccumulation</option>
            <option id="D">Eutrophication</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Biomagnification refers to the increase in concentration of the toxicant at successive trophic levels. This happens because a toxic substance accumulated by an organism cannot be metabolised or excreted.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following conventions is associated with the reduction of greenhouse gas emissions?</text>
            <option id="A">Montreal Protocol</option>
            <option id="B">Kyoto Protocol</option>
            <option id="C">Earth Summit (Rio de Janeiro)</option>
            <option id="D">World Summit (Johannesburg)</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Kyoto Protocol is an international agreement linked to the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, which commits its Parties by setting internationally binding emission reduction targets for greenhouse gases.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Polyblend, a fine powder of recycled modified plastic, has proved to be a good material for:</text>
            <option id="A">Making plastic bags</option>
            <option id="B">Constructing roads</option>
            <option id="C">Fertilizer</option>
            <option id="D">Water purification</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Polyblend, developed by Ahmed Khan, is a fine powder of recycled modified plastic. This mixture is mixed with the bitumen that is used to lay roads, enhancing the bitumen's water repellant properties.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Joint Forest Management (JFM) concept was introduced by the Government of India in the year:</text>
            <option id="A">1974</option>
            <option id="B">1980</option>
            <option id="C">1986</option>
            <option id="D">1992</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Realising the significance of participation by local communities, the Government of India in 1980s has introduced the concept of Joint Forest Management (JFM) so as to work closely with the local communities for protecting and managing forests.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a major cause of deforestation in the tropics?</text>
            <option id="A">Slash and burn agriculture (Jhum cultivation)</option>
            <option id="B">Reforestation programs</option>
            <option id="C">Establishment of national parks</option>
            <option id="D">Urbanization in polar regions</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Slash and burn agriculture, commonly called Jhum cultivation in the north-eastern states of India, has contributed significantly to deforestation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The "Bishnoi" community of Rajasthan is famously associated with:</text>
            <option id="A">Protecting wildlife and forests</option>
            <option id="B">Promoting nuclear energy</option>
            <option id="C">Developing polyblend</option>
            <option id="D">Inventing catalytic converters</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In 1731, Amrita Devi Bishnoi and others from the Bishnoi community hugged trees to protect them from being cut down by the king's men, demonstrating extraordinary courage and dedication to protecting nature.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which disease is caused by the chronic consumption of water highly contaminated with cadmium?</text>
            <option id="A">Minamata disease</option>
            <option id="B">Itai-itai disease</option>
            <option id="C">Black foot disease</option>
            <option id="D">Blue baby syndrome</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Itai-itai disease is caused by chronic cadmium poisoning. (Minamata is caused by mercury, Black foot by arsenic, Blue baby by nitrates).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Catalytic converters fitted into automobiles for reducing emission of poisonous gases contain expensive metals as catalysts. Which of the following are these metals?</text>
            <option id="A">Iron and copper</option>
            <option id="B">Platinum, palladium and rhodium</option>
            <option id="C">Silver and gold</option>
            <option id="D">Lead and zinc</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Catalytic converters, having expensive metals namely platinum-palladium and rhodium as the catalysts, are fitted into automobiles for reducing emission of poisonous gases.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Motor vehicles equipped with catalytic converters should use unleaded petrol because lead in the petrol:</text>
            <option id="A">Increases carbon monoxide emission</option>
            <option id="B">Reduces the mileage of the vehicle</option>
            <option id="C">Inactivates the catalyst</option>
            <option id="D">Causes knocking in the engine</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Motor vehicles equipped with catalytic converter should use unleaded petrol because lead in the petrol inactivates the catalyst.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act came into force in India in 1981, but was amended in 1987 to include which of the following as an air pollutant?</text>
            <option id="A">Ozone</option>
            <option id="B">Noise</option>
            <option id="C">Chlorofluorocarbons</option>
            <option id="D">Methane</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In India, the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act came into force in 1981, but was amended in 1987 to include noise as an air pollutant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Biochemical Oxygen Demand (BOD) is a measure of:</text>
            <option id="A">The amount of dissolved oxygen present in water</option>
            <option id="B">The oxygen required by bacteria to degrade organic matter in a water sample</option>
            <option id="C">The rate of photosynthesis by aquatic plants</option>
            <option id="D">The toxicity of heavy metals in water</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>It is possible to estimate the amount of biodegradable organic matter in sewage water by measuring Biochemical Oxygen Demand (BOD). Micro-organisms involved in biodegradation of organic matter consume a lot of oxygen.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following statements about Biomagnification is correct?</text>
            <option id="A">It is the decrease of toxicant concentration at successive trophic levels.</option>
            <option id="B">It happens because toxic substances can be easily metabolised.</option>
            <option id="C">It refers to the increase in concentration of toxicant at successive trophic levels.</option>
            <option id="D">It only affects aquatic primary producers.</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Biomagnification refers to increase in concentration of the toxicant at successive trophic levels. This happens because a toxic substance accumulated by an organism cannot be metabolised or excreted.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>High concentration of DDT in birds causes a decline in their population because it disturbs the metabolism of:</text>
            <option id="A">Phosphorus</option>
            <option id="B">Nitrogen</option>
            <option id="C">Calcium</option>
            <option id="D">Potassium</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>High concentrations of DDT disturb calcium metabolism in birds, which causes thinning of eggshell and their premature breaking, eventually causing decline in bird populations.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The natural aging of a lake by biological enrichment of its water is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Biomagnification</option>
            <option id="B">Eutrophication</option>
            <option id="C">Stratification</option>
            <option id="D">Nitrification</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Eutrophication is the natural aging of a lake by nutrient enrichment of its water. In a young lake the water is cold and clear, supporting little life. With time, streams draining into the lake introduce nutrients such as nitrogen and phosphorus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered an environmentally friendly alternative to traditional sanitary landfills for disposing of solid waste?</text>
            <option id="A">Open burning</option>
            <option id="B">Dumping in oceans</option>
            <option id="C">Incineration at low temperatures</option>
            <option id="D">Recovery, recycling, and composting</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Recovery, recycling, and composting of biodegradable materials are environmentally sound ways of managing solid waste, reducing the burden on landfills.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In India, the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act came into force in 1981, but was amended in 1987 to include which of the following as an air pollutant?</text>
            <option id="A">Ozone</option>
            <option id="B">Noise</option>
            <option id="C">Radioactive waste</option>
            <option id="D">Heavy metals</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In India, the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act came into force in 1981, but was amended in 1987 to include noise as an air pollutant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A brief exposure to extremely high sound level, 150 dB or more generated by take-off of a jet plane or rocket, may damage:</text>
            <option id="A">Ear drums</option>
            <option id="B">Vocal cords</option>
            <option id="C">Retina</option>
            <option id="D">Olfactory receptors</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>A brief exposure to extremely high sound level, 150 dB or more generated by take-off of a jet plane or rocket, may damage ear drums thus permanently impairing hearing ability.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Government of India has passed the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act in which year to safeguard our water resources?</text>
            <option id="A">1974</option>
            <option id="B">1981</option>
            <option id="C">1986</option>
            <option id="D">1992</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Realising the importance of maintaining the cleanliness of the water bodies, the Government of India has passed the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 to safeguard our water resources.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Presence of large amounts of nutrients in waters also causes excessive growth of planktonic (free-floating) algae, called an algal bloom. What does an algal bloom do?</text>
            <option id="A">Improves the water quality</option>
            <option id="B">Increases fish populations</option>
            <option id="C">Imparts a distinct color to the water bodies and deteriorates the water quality</option>
            <option id="D">Increases the dissolved oxygen level</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Algal bloom imparts a distinct colour to the water bodies. Algal blooms cause deterioration of the water quality and fish mortality. Some bloom-forming algae are extremely toxic to human beings and animals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Irreparable computers and other electronic goods are known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Biomedical waste</option>
            <option id="B">E-wastes</option>
            <option id="C">Municipal solid waste</option>
            <option id="D">Industrial waste</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Irreparable computers and other electronic goods are known as electronic wastes (e-wastes). E-wastes are buried in landfills or incinerated.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the only environmentally sound solution for the treatment of e-wastes?</text>
            <option id="A">Incineration</option>
            <option id="B">Burying in landfills</option>
            <option id="C">Dumping in oceans</option>
            <option id="D">Recycling</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Recycling is the only solution for the treatment of e-waste, provided it is carried out in an environment-friendly manner.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Polyblend is a fine powder of recycled modified plastic. When mixed with bitumen, it is used to lay:</text>
            <option id="A">Building foundations</option>
            <option id="B">Roads</option>
            <option id="C">Railway tracks</option>
            <option id="D">Airport runways</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A fine powder of recycled modified plastic, called polyblend, has been developed. This mixture is mixed with the bitumen that is used to lay roads.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A polyblend and bitumen mixture increases the water repelling properties of roads, which enhances the road's:</text>
            <option id="A">Color</option>
            <option id="B">Smoothness</option>
            <option id="C">Life</option>
            <option id="D">Friction</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Polyblend and bitumen, when used to lay roads, enhanced the bitumen's water repellant properties, and helped to increase road life by a factor of three.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which device is most widely used to remove particulate matter from the exhaust of thermal power plants?</text>
            <option id="A">Catalytic converter</option>
            <option id="B">Electrostatic precipitator</option>
            <option id="C">Scrubber</option>
            <option id="D">Incinerator</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>There are several ways of removing particulate matter; the most widely used of which is the electrostatic precipitator, which can remove over 99 per cent particulate matter present in the exhaust from a thermal power plant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In an electrostatic precipitator, electrode wires are maintained at several thousand volts to produce a corona that releases:</text>
            <option id="A">Positively charged ions</option>
            <option id="B">Electrons</option>
            <option id="C">Neutrons</option>
            <option id="D">Protons</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>It has electrode wires that are maintained at several thousand volts, which produce a corona that releases electrons. These electrons attach to dust particles giving them a net negative charge.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A scrubber can remove gaseous pollutants such as:</text>
            <option id="A">Sulphur dioxide</option>
            <option id="B">Carbon monoxide</option>
            <option id="C">Nitrogen</option>
            <option id="D">Methane</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>A scrubber can remove gases like sulphur dioxide. In a scrubber, the exhaust is passed through a spray of water or lime.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB), particulate size less than what value is responsible for causing the greatest harm to human health?</text>
            <option id="A">2.5 micrometers (PM 2.5)</option>
            <option id="B">5.0 micrometers</option>
            <option id="C">10 micrometers</option>
            <option id="D">50 micrometers</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>According to Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB), particulate size 2.5 micrometers or less in diameter (PM 2.5) are responsible for causing the greatest harm to human health.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A brief exposure to extremely high sound level, 150 dB or more generated by take-off of a jet plane or rocket, may damage:</text>
            <option id="A">The optic nerve</option>
            <option id="B">Ear drums, thus permanently impairing hearing ability</option>
            <option id="C">The vocal cords</option>
            <option id="D">The sense of smell</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A brief exposure to extremely high sound level, 150 dB or more generated by take-off of a jet plane or rocket, may damage ear drums thus permanently impairing hearing ability.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Even chronic exposure to a relatively lower noise level of cities may permanently damage:</text>
            <option id="A">Vision</option>
            <option id="B">Hearing abilities</option>
            <option id="C">Bone density</option>
            <option id="D">Digestive system</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Even chronic exposure to a relatively lower noise level of cities may permanently damage hearing abilities of humans.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a typical effect of noise pollution on humans?</text>
            <option id="A">Sleeplessness</option>
            <option id="B">Increased heart beat</option>
            <option id="C">Altered breathing pattern</option>
            <option id="D">Decreased blood pressure</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Noise also causes sleeplessness, increased heart beat, altered breathing pattern, thus considerably stressing humans.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>By the 1990s, which city ranked fourth among the 41 most polluted cities of the world regarding air pollution?</text>
            <option id="A">Mumbai</option>
            <option id="B">Delhi</option>
            <option id="C">Kolkata</option>
            <option id="D">Chennai</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Delhi leads the country in its levels of air-pollution – it has more cars than the states of Gujarat and West Bengal put together. In the 1990s, Delhi ranked fourth among the 41 most polluted cities of the world.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Euro III norms, aromatic hydrocarbons are to be contained at what percentage of the concerned fuel?</text>
            <option id="A">20 per cent</option>
            <option id="B">35 per cent</option>
            <option id="C">42 per cent</option>
            <option id="D">50 per cent</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Aromatic hydrocarbons are to be contained at 42 per cent of the concerned fuel.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the ultimate goal of the roadmap regarding sulphur in fuels?</text>
            <option id="A">To increase it to 100 ppm</option>
            <option id="B">To reduce it to 50 ppm in petrol and diesel</option>
            <option id="C">To eliminate it completely</option>
            <option id="D">To maintain it at 350 ppm</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The goal, according to the roadmap, is to reduce sulphur to 50 ppm in petrol and diesel and bring down the level to 35 per cent.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>As a result of efforts like switching to CNG and enforcing stricter fuel norms, the air quality of Delhi has significantly improved. A substantial fall in CO and SO2 levels has been found in Delhi between which years?</text>
            <option id="A">1990 and 1995</option>
            <option id="B">1997 and 2005</option>
            <option id="C">2005 and 2010</option>
            <option id="D">2010 and 2015</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Thanks to the efforts made, the air quality of Delhi has significantly improved. According to an estimate, a substantial fall in CO and SO2 level has been found in Delhi between 1997 and 2005.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>We often find that water bodies, like ponds or lakes, turn green and start giving off an unpleasant smell. This is due to the process of:</text>
            <option id="A">Biomagnification</option>
            <option id="B">Eutrophication</option>
            <option id="C">Salinization</option>
            <option id="D">Sedimentation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>You may have seen ponds or lakes that look green and give off a bad smell... The presence of large amounts of nutrients in waters also causes excessive growth of planktonic (free-floating) algae, called an algal bloom [which is a part of eutrophication].</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In an aquatic food chain, if water has a DDT concentration of 0.003 ppb, what can the concentration reach in fish-eating birds due to biomagnification?</text>
            <option id="A">0.04 ppm</option>
            <option id="B">0.5 ppm</option>
            <option id="C">2 ppm</option>
            <option id="D">25 ppm</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Figure 16.5 shows biomagnification of DDT in an aquatic food chain. In this manner, the concentration of DDT is increased at successive trophic levels; say if it starts at 0.003 ppb (ppb = parts per billion) in water, it can ultimately reach 25 ppm (ppm = parts per million) in fish-eating birds, through biomagnification.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is a major physiological consequence of high concentrations of DDT in birds?</text>
            <option id="A">It causes blindness</option>
            <option id="B">It disturbs calcium metabolism, causing thinning of eggshells and premature breaking</option>
            <option id="C">It prevents them from flying</option>
            <option id="D">It causes their feathers to fall out</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>High concentrations of DDT disturb calcium metabolism in birds, which causes thinning of eggshell and their premature breaking, eventually causing decline in bird populations.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Eutrophication is the natural aging of a lake. What is this aging primarily caused by?</text>
            <option id="A">Evaporation of water</option>
            <option id="B">Biological enrichment of its water with nutrients like nitrogen and phosphorus</option>
            <option id="C">Accumulation of heavy metals</option>
            <option id="D">Decreased sunlight penetration</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Eutrophication is the natural aging of a lake by nutrient enrichment of its water. In a young lake the water is cold and clear, supporting little life. With time, streams draining into the lake introduce nutrients such as nitrogen and phosphorus, which encourage the growth of aquatic organisms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When a lake undergoes eutrophication over thousands of years, what eventually happens to the lake?</text>
            <option id="A">It becomes a deeper and colder lake</option>
            <option id="B">It turns into a fast-flowing river</option>
            <option id="C">It fills in with debris and becomes land</option>
            <option id="D">It becomes a saltwater sea</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Over the centuries, as silt and organic debris pile up, the lake grows shallower and warmer... Eventually, the lake gives way to large masses of floating plants (bog), finally converting into land.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Ecological sanitation (EcoSan) is a sustainable system for handling human excreta. What is the primary method used in EcoSan?</text>
            <option id="A">Flushing with large amounts of water</option>
            <option id="B">Chemical treatment in large tanks</option>
            <option id="C">Dry composting toilets</option>
            <option id="D">Incineration of waste</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Ecological sanitation is a sustainable system for handling human excreta, using dry composting toilets. This is a practical, hygienic, efficient and cost-effective solution to human waste disposal.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>With EcoSan toilets, what is human excreta eventually recycled into?</text>
            <option id="A">Drinking water</option>
            <option id="B">Building materials</option>
            <option id="C">A resource (as natural fertiliser)</option>
            <option id="D">Biogas only</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The key point to note here is that with this composting method, human excreta can be recycled into a resource (as natural fertiliser), which reduces the need for chemical fertilisers. There are working 'EcoSan' toilets in many areas of Kerala and Sri Lanka.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Solid wastes refer to everything that goes out in trash. Municipal solid wastes are collected and disposed of by the municipality. Historically, what was the primary method of disposing of these wastes?</text>
            <option id="A">Recycling</option>
            <option id="B">Burning to reduce volume</option>
            <option id="C">Dumping in the ocean</option>
            <option id="D">Composting</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Solid wastes refer to everything that goes out in trash. Municipal solid wastes are wastes from homes, offices, stores, schools, hospitals, etc., that are collected and disposed by the municipality. The municipal solid wastes generally comprise paper, food wastes, plastics, glass, metals, rubber, leather, textile, etc. Burning reduces the volume of the wastes, although it is generally not burnt to completion and open dumps often serve as the breeding ground for rats and flies.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What was adopted as a substitute for open-burning dumps for solid waste disposal?</text>
            <option id="A">Sanitary landfills</option>
            <option id="B">Incinerators</option>
            <option id="C">Recycling plants</option>
            <option id="D">Space disposal</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Sanitary landfills were adopted as the substitute for open-burning dumps. In a sanitary landfill, wastes are dumped in a depression or trench after compaction, and covered with dirt everyday.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>According to the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB), which particulate size is responsible for causing the greatest harm to human health?</text>
            <option id="A">5.0 micrometers or less</option>
            <option id="B">10 micrometers or less</option>
            <option id="C">2.5 micrometers or less</option>
            <option id="D">1.0 micrometers or less</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>According to CPCB, particulate size 2.5 micrometers or less in diameter (PM 2.5) are responsible for causing the greatest harm to human health because they can be breathed deep into the lungs and cause severe respiratory problems.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following treaties was signed in 1987 to control the emission of ozone-depleting substances?</text>
            <option id="A">Kyoto Protocol</option>
            <option id="B">Montreal Protocol</option>
            <option id="C">Earth Summit</option>
            <option id="D">World Summit</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Recognizing the deleterious affects of ozone depletion, an international treaty, known as the Montreal Protocol, was signed at Montreal (Canada) in 1987 (effective in 1989) to control the emission of ozone depleting substances.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The 'Joint Forest Management' (JFM) concept was introduced by the Government of India in the 1980s. What is its main objective?</text>
            <option id="A">To completely privatize all forest land in India.</option>
            <option id="B">To involve local communities closely in protecting and managing forests.</option>
            <option id="C">To ban all human entry into dense forest regions.</option>
            <option id="D">To introduce exotic plant species to increase forest yield.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Realizing the significance of participation by local communities, the Government of India in 1980s introduced the concept of Joint Forest Management (JFM) to work closely with the local communities for protecting and managing forests.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A high Biological Oxygen Demand (BOD) in a water body indicates that:</text>
            <option id="A">The water is pure and highly oxygenated.</option>
            <option id="B">The water is highly polluted with organic matter.</option>
            <option id="C">There is an excess of inorganic nutrients like nitrates.</option>
            <option id="D">The number of heterotrophic bacteria is very low.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>High BOD indicates that a large amount of oxygen is required by bacteria and other microorganisms to decompose the organic matter present in the water, meaning the water is highly polluted with organic matter.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Catalytic converters are fitted into automobiles to reduce emission of poisonous gases. Which of the following metals is NOT used as a catalyst in these converters?</text>
            <option id="A">Platinum</option>
            <option id="B">Palladium</option>
            <option id="C">Rhodium</option>
            <option id="D">Iron</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Catalytic converters have expensive metals namely platinum-palladium and rhodium as the catalysts, which are fitted into automobiles for reducing emission of poisonous gases.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The 'Ozone hole' refers to:</text>
            <option id="A">A literal hole in the stratosphere where no ozone exists.</option>
            <option id="B">An area of the stratosphere with elevated ozone concentrations.</option>
            <option id="C">A thinning of the ozone layer, particularly over the Antarctic region.</option>
            <option id="D">A gap in the tropospheric ozone layer.</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The term 'ozone hole' does not mean a literal hole, but rather refers to a severe depletion or thinning of the ozone layer, which is particularly marked over the Antarctic region.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Integrated organic farming is a cyclical, zero-waste procedure. Who among the following is famously associated with creating the Haryana Kisan Welfare Club to promote this practice?</text>
            <option id="A">Ahmed Khan</option>
            <option id="B">Ramesh Chandra Dagar</option>
            <option id="C">Amrita Devi</option>
            <option id="D">Sunderlal Bahuguna</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Ramesh Chandra Dagar, a farmer in Sonipat, Haryana, includes bee-keeping, dairy management, water harvesting, composting and agriculture in a chain of processes, which support each other and allow an extremely economical and sustainable venture.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>UV-B radiation from the sun is known to cause all of the following EXCEPT:</text>
            <option id="A">Snow-blindness</option>
            <option id="B">Cataract</option>
            <option id="C">Mutation in DNA</option>
            <option id="D">Enhanced rate of photosynthesis in phytoplankton</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>UV-B damages DNA and mutation may occur. It causes aging of skin, damage to skin cells and various types of skin cancers. In human eye, cornea absorbs UV-B radiation, and a high dose of UV-B causes inflammation of cornea, called snow-blindness, cataract, etc. It damages phytoplankton; it does not enhance photosynthesis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB), what size of particulate matter is responsible for causing the greatest harm to human health?</text>
            <option id="A">5.0 micrometers or more in diameter</option>
            <option id="B">2.5 micrometers or less in diameter</option>
            <option id="C">Between 2.5 and 5.0 micrometers in diameter</option>
            <option id="D">10 micrometers in diameter</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>According to Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB), particulate size 2.5 micrometers or less in diameter (PM 2.5) are responsible for causing the greatest harm to human health. These fine particulates can be breathed deep into the lungs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Algal bloom in a water body is primarily caused by:</text>
            <option id="A">Presence of large amounts of dissolved oxygen</option>
            <option id="B">Presence of large amounts of nutrients (nitrogen and phosphorus)</option>
            <option id="C">Decreased temperature of the water</option>
            <option id="D">High salinity of the water</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Presence of large amounts of nutrients in waters also causes excessive growth of planktonic (free-floating) algae, called an algal bloom which imparts a distinct colour to the water bodies. Algal blooms cause deterioration of the water quality and fish mortality.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following plants is known as the "Terror of Bengal" due to its highly invasive nature and tendency to choke water bodies?</text>
            <option id="A">Lantana camara</option>
            <option id="B">Parthenium hysterophorus</option>
            <option id="C">Eichhornia crassipes (Water hyacinth)</option>
            <option id="D">Prosopis juliflora</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The world's most problematic aquatic weed, Eichhornia crassipes (Water hyacinth) is also called 'Terror of Bengal'. They grow abundantly in eutrophic water bodies, and lead to an imbalance in the ecosystem dynamics of the water body.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Biomagnification refers to increase in concentration of the toxicant at successive trophic levels. This happens because the toxic substance:</text>
            <option id="A">Is rapidly metabolised by the organism</option>
            <option id="B">Is rapidly excreted by the organism</option>
            <option id="C">Cannot be metabolised or excreted, and is thus passed on to the next higher trophic level</option>
            <option id="D">Is converted into a non-toxic form</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Biomagnification refers to increase in concentration of the toxicant at successive trophic levels. This happens because a toxic substance accumulated by an organism cannot be metabolised or excreted, and is thus passed on to the next higher trophic level.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The term "polyblend" is associated with the successful recycling of which material?</text>
            <option id="A">Electronic waste (e-waste)</option>
            <option id="B">Plastic waste</option>
            <option id="C">Agricultural waste</option>
            <option id="D">Radioactive waste</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Polyblend is a fine powder of recycled modified plastic, developed by Ahmed Khan in Bangalore. This mixture is mixed with the bitumen that is used to lay roads.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a major contributor to the 'Greenhouse Effect'?</text>
            <option id="A">Oxygen</option>
            <option id="B">Nitrogen</option>
            <option id="C">Carbon dioxide</option>
            <option id="D">Argon</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Carbon dioxide is the major contributor to the greenhouse effect (about 60%), followed by methane (20%), CFCs (14%) and N2O (6%).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The "Ozone hole" over Antarctica is most prominent during which season?</text>
            <option id="A">Late summer</option>
            <option id="B">Early spring (Late August - Early October)</option>
            <option id="C">Mid-winter</option>
            <option id="D">Late autumn</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The depletion of the ozone layer is particularly marked over the Antarctic region. This has resulted in formation of a large area of thinned ozone layer, commonly called as the ozone hole, which develops each year between late August and early October (early spring in Antarctica).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>High doses of UV-B causes inflammation of the cornea in the human eye. This condition is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Cataract</option>
            <option id="B">Snow-blindness</option>
            <option id="C">Glaucoma</option>
            <option id="D">Myopia</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In human eye, cornea absorbs UV-B radiation, and a high dose of UV-B causes inflammation of cornea, called snow-blindness, cataract, etc. Such exposure may permanently damage the cornea.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Recognising the deleterious affects of ozone depletion, an international treaty was signed at Montreal (Canada) in 1987 to control the emission of ozone depleting substances. What is this protocol called?</text>
            <option id="A">Kyoto Protocol</option>
            <option id="B">Earth Summit</option>
            <option id="C">Montreal Protocol</option>
            <option id="D">World Summit on Sustainable Development</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Recognising the deleterious affects of ozone depletion, an international treaty, known as the Montreal Protocol, was signed at Montreal (Canada) in 1987 (effective in 1989) to control the emission of ozone depleting substances.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Government of India has recently instituted which award for individuals or communities from rural areas that have shown extraordinary courage and dedication in protecting wildlife?</text>
            <option id="A">Padma Shri Award</option>
            <option id="B">Indira Gandhi Paryavaran Puraskar</option>
            <option id="C">Amrita Devi Bishnoi Wildlife Protection Award</option>
            <option id="D">Rajiv Gandhi Wildlife Conservation Award</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The Government of India has recently instituted the Amrita Devi Bishnoi Wildlife Protection Award for individuals or communities from rural areas that have shown extraordinary courage and dedication in protecting wildlife.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The use of chemical fertilizers to meet the increasing demands of agricultural production has resulted in:</text>
            <option id="A">Decreased soil fertility</option>
            <option id="B">Eutrophication of aquatic ecosystems</option>
            <option id="C">Increased ozone depletion</option>
            <option id="D">Both A and B</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In the wake of the green revolution, use of inorganic fertilisers and pesticides has increased manifold for enhancing crop production. Pesticides, herbicides, fungicides, etc., are being increasingly used. These incidentally, are also toxic to non-target organisms, that are important components of the soil ecosystem. Artificial fertilisers cause eutrophication in aquatic ecosystems.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Ramesh Chandra Dagar created the Haryana Kisan Welfare Club to promote:</text>
            <option id="A">Use of synthetic fertilizers</option>
            <option id="B">Integrated organic farming</option>
            <option id="C">Deforestation for agriculture</option>
            <option id="D">Use of genetically modified crops</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Ramesh Chandra Dagar, a farmer in Sonipat, Haryana, is doing just this. He includes bee-keeping, dairy management, water harvesting, composting and agriculture in a chain of processes, which support each other and allow an extremely economical and sustainable venture. To spread information and help on the practice of integrated organic farming, Dagar has created the Haryana Kisan Welfare Club.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The most problematic greenhouse gas, contributing to about 60% of total global warming, is:</text>
            <option id="A">Methane</option>
            <option id="B">Carbon dioxide</option>
            <option id="C">Nitrous oxide</option>
            <option id="D">CFCs</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Carbon dioxide (CO2) is the most abundant greenhouse gas, contributing to 60% of total global warming, followed by methane (20%), CFCs (14%) and N2O (6%).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What effect does the inhalation of PM 2.5 particles have on humans?</text>
            <option id="A">It improves lung capacity</option>
            <option id="B">It has no significant effect</option>
            <option id="C">It can cause respiratory symptoms, irritation, inflammations and damage to the lungs and premature deaths</option>
            <option id="D">It only affects the nasal passage</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>These fine particulates can be breathed deep into the lungs and can cause breathing and respiratory symptoms, irritation, inflammations and damage to the lungs and premature deaths.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Automobiles are a major cause for atmospheric pollution at least in the metro cities. Proper maintenance of automobiles along with use of lead-free petrol or diesel can reduce the pollutants they emit. Catalytic converters are fitted into automobiles for reducing emission of poisonous gases. These converters have expensive metals as catalysts, which are:</text>
            <option id="A">Iron, copper, and zinc</option>
            <option id="B">Platinum-palladium and rhodium</option>
            <option id="C">Gold, silver, and platinum</option>
            <option id="D">Aluminum, magnesium, and titanium</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Catalytic converters, having expensive metals namely platinum-palladium and rhodium as the catalysts, are fitted into automobiles for reducing emission of poisonous gases.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>As the exhaust passes through the catalytic converter, unburnt hydrocarbons are converted into carbon dioxide and water, and carbon monoxide and nitric oxide are changed to:</text>
            <option id="A">Carbon dioxide and nitrogen gas</option>
            <option id="B">Methane and ammonia</option>
            <option id="C">Ozone and sulphur dioxide</option>
            <option id="D">Lead and arsenic</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>As the exhaust passes through the catalytic converter, unburnt hydrocarbons are converted into carbon dioxide and water, and carbon monoxide and nitric oxide are changed to carbon dioxide and nitrogen gas, respectively.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>To combat air pollution in Delhi, the Supreme Court ordered all buses to switch from diesel to which fuel by the end of 2002?</text>
            <option id="A">Petrol</option>
            <option id="B">Unleaded petrol</option>
            <option id="C">Compressed Natural Gas (CNG)</option>
            <option id="D">Electricity</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>All the buses of Delhi were converted to run on CNG by the end of 2002. You may ask the question as to why CNG is better than diesel. The answer is that CNG burns most efficiently, unlike petrol or diesel.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Why is Compressed Natural Gas (CNG) considered better than diesel or petrol for automobiles?</text>
            <option id="A">It is more expensive</option>
            <option id="B">It burns most efficiently and very little of it is left unburnt</option>
            <option id="C">It can be easily siphoned off by thieves</option>
            <option id="D">It is adulterated frequently</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The answer is that CNG burns most efficiently, unlike petrol or diesel, in the automobiles and very little of it is left unburnt. Moreover, CNG is cheaper than petrol or diesel, cannot be siphoned off by thieves and adulterated like petrol or diesel.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the main problem with switching to CNG as an automobile fuel?</text>
            <option id="A">It is highly toxic</option>
            <option id="B">It is more expensive than petrol</option>
            <option id="C">The difficulty of laying down pipelines to deliver CNG through distribution points/pumps</option>
            <option id="D">It cannot be used in buses</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The main problem with switching over to CNG is the difficulty of laying down pipelines to deliver CNG through distribution points/ pumps and ensuring uninterrupted supply.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act was passed by the Government of India in which year to safeguard water resources?</text>
            <option id="A">1974</option>
            <option id="B">1981</option>
            <option id="C">1986</option>
            <option id="D">1990</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Realising the importance of maintaining the cleanliness of the water bodies, the Government of India has passed the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 to safeguard our water resources.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What percentage of impurities makes domestic sewage unfit for human use?</text>
            <option id="A">A mere 0.1 per cent</option>
            <option id="B">Around 1 per cent</option>
            <option id="C">About 5 per cent</option>
            <option id="D">Over 10 per cent</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>A mere 0.1 per cent impurities make domestic sewage unfit for human use.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of dissolved materials present in domestic sewage?</text>
            <option id="A">Sand and silt</option>
            <option id="B">Fecal matter and bacteria</option>
            <option id="C">Nutrients like nitrate, ammonia, phosphate, sodium, calcium</option>
            <option id="D">Paper fibers and cloth</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Domestic sewage primarily contains biodegradable organic matter, which readily decomposes... Dissolved materials include nutrients (nitrate, ammonia, phosphate, sodium, calcium).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When the natural aging process of a lake is accelerated by human activities like effluents from industries and homes, it is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Biomagnification</option>
            <option id="B">Cultural or Accelerated Eutrophication</option>
            <option id="C">Sedimentation</option>
            <option id="D">Salinization</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>However, pollutants from man's activities like effluents from the industries and homes can radically accelerate the aging process. This phenomenon has been called Cultural or Accelerated Eutrophication.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which two nutrients are the prime contaminants responsible for cultural eutrophication?</text>
            <option id="A">Calcium and Magnesium</option>
            <option id="B">Nitrates and Phosphates</option>
            <option id="C">Iron and Zinc</option>
            <option id="D">Sodium and Potassium</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The prime contaminants are nitrates and phosphates, which act as plant nutrients.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is a consequence of the overstimulation of algal growth due to nitrates and phosphates in a lake?</text>
            <option id="A">Increased oxygen levels in the water</option>
            <option id="B">Scum formation, unpleasant odors, and depletion of dissolved oxygen</option>
            <option id="C">Increased transparency of the water</option>
            <option id="D">Enhanced growth of all fish species</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>They overstimulate the growth of algae, causing unsightly scum and unpleasant odours, and robbing the water of dissolved oxygen vital to other aquatic life. At the same time, other pollutants flowing into a lake may poison whole populations of fish, whose decomposing remains further deplete the water's dissolved oxygen content.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Sanitary landfills are not a perfect solution for solid waste because there is a danger of chemicals seeping and polluting:</text>
            <option id="A">The atmosphere</option>
            <option id="B">The underground water resources</option>
            <option id="C">The ozone layer</option>
            <option id="D">Nearby forests only</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Landfills are also not really much of a solution since the amount of garbage generation specially in the metros has increased so much that these sites are getting filled too. Also there is danger of seepage of chemicals, etc., from these landfills polluting the underground water resources.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>All waste that we generate can be categorized into three types. Which of the following is NOT one of those types?</text>
            <option id="A">Bio-degradable</option>
            <option id="B">Recyclable</option>
            <option id="C">Non-biodegradable</option>
            <option id="D">Extraterrestrial</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>A solution to all this can only be in human beings becoming more sensitive to these environment issues. All waste that we generate can be categorised into three types – (a) bio-degradable, (b) recyclable and (c) the non-biodegradable.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>For waste disposal, the Kabadiwallahs and rag-pickers do a great job of separating which type of materials?</text>
            <option id="A">Bio-degradable materials</option>
            <option id="B">Materials for recycling</option>
            <option id="C">Toxic chemicals</option>
            <option id="D">Medical waste</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>It is important that all garbage generated is sorted. What can be reused or recycled should be separated out; our kabadiwallahs and rag-pickers do a great job of separation of materials for recycling.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>