<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="329" name="Evolution">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>Who proposed the theory of chemical evolution that life came from pre-existing non-living organic molecules?</text>
            <option id="A">Louis Pasteur</option>
            <option id="B">Oparin and Haldane</option>
            <option id="C">Stanley Miller</option>
            <option id="D">Charles Darwin</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Oparin of Russia and Haldane of England proposed that the first form of life could have come from pre-existing non-living organic molecules (e.g., RNA, protein, etc.) and that formation of life was preceded by chemical evolution.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Analogous structures are a result of:</text>
            <option id="A">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Divergent evolution</option>
            <option id="C">Shared ancestry</option>
            <option id="D">Genetic drift</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Analogous structures are anatomically different structures evolving for the same function due to living in similar habitats. This is a result of convergent evolution (e.g., wings of butterfly and birds).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The phrase "Survival of the fittest" was coined by:</text>
            <option id="A">Charles Darwin</option>
            <option id="B">Jean-Baptiste Lamarck</option>
            <option id="C">Herbert Spencer</option>
            <option id="D">Hugo de Vries</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Though heavily associated with Charles Darwin's theory of natural selection, the exact phrase "survival of the fittest" was first coined by Herbert Spencer after reading Darwin's On the Origin of Species.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Charles Darwin, evolution is a gradual process that occurs primarily through:</text>
            <option id="A">Mutation</option>
            <option id="B">Natural selection</option>
            <option id="C">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="D">Use and disuse of organs</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>According to Darwin, fitness is the end result of the ability to adapt and get selected by nature. He called it natural selection and implied it as a mechanism of evolution.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The presence of gill slits in the embryos of all vertebrates supports the theory of:</text>
            <option id="A">Biogenesis</option>
            <option id="B">Recapitulation</option>
            <option id="C">Special creation</option>
            <option id="D">Spontaneous generation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Ernst Haeckel proposed the biogenetic law (recapitulation theory), which states that 'ontogeny recapitulates phylogeny'. The presence of gill slits in embryos of all vertebrates supports this embryological evidence for evolution.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered the closest ancestor to modern humans?</text>
            <option id="A">Australopithecus</option>
            <option id="B">Homo habilis</option>
            <option id="C">Homo erectus</option>
            <option id="D">Homo neanderthalensis</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Homo neanderthalensis (Neanderthal man) is considered the closest extinct human relative to modern humans (Homo sapiens), having lived near east and central Asia between 1,00,000-40,000 years back.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following homologous structures indicates a common ancestry among vertebrates?</text>
            <option id="A">Wings of butterfly and wings of bird</option>
            <option id="B">Flippers of penguin and flippers of dolphin</option>
            <option id="C">Forelimbs of whales, bats, cheetahs, and humans</option>
            <option id="D">Eyes of octopus and eyes of mammals</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Homology indicates common ancestry. Whales, bats, cheetah and human (all mammals) share similarities in the pattern of bones of forelimbs. Though these forelimbs perform different functions, they have similar anatomical structure.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The theory of spontaneous generation stated that:</text>
            <option id="A">Life originated from pre-existing life.</option>
            <option id="B">Life originated from decaying and rotting matter like straw, mud, etc.</option>
            <option id="C">Life was created by a supernatural power.</option>
            <option id="D">Life came from outer space in the form of spores.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>For a long time it was also believed that life came out of decaying and rotting matter like straw, mud, etc. This was the theory of spontaneous generation. Louis Pasteur carefully conducted experiments to disprove this theory.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who among the following scientists finally dismissed the theory of spontaneous generation using a swan-necked flask experiment?</text>
            <option id="A">Stanley Miller</option>
            <option id="B">Oparin and Haldane</option>
            <option id="C">Louis Pasteur</option>
            <option id="D">Charles Darwin</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Louis Pasteur by careful experimentation demonstrated that life comes only from pre-existing life. He showed that in pre-sterilised swan-necked flasks, life did not come from killed yeast while in another flask open to air, new living organisms arose.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to the Big Bang theory, how long ago did the origin of the universe occur?</text>
            <option id="A">20 billion years ago</option>
            <option id="B">4.5 billion years ago</option>
            <option id="C">10 billion years ago</option>
            <option id="D">15 billion years ago</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The Big Bang theory attempts to explain to us the origin of universe. It talks of a singular huge explosion unimaginable in physical terms. The universe is very old - almost 20 billion years old.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The earth is supposed to have been formed about:</text>
            <option id="A">20 billion years back</option>
            <option id="B">4.5 billion years back</option>
            <option id="C">3.0 billion years back</option>
            <option id="D">500 million years back</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In the solar system of the milky way galaxy, earth was supposed to have been formed about 4.5 billion years back. There was no atmosphere on early earth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The theory of 'Panspermia' or 'Cosmozoic theory' suggests that:</text>
            <option id="A">Life arose from non-living matter through chemical evolution.</option>
            <option id="B">Life came from outerspace in the form of spores.</option>
            <option id="C">Life was created by a supernatural power.</option>
            <option id="D">Life arose spontaneously from decaying organic matter.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some scientists believe that life came from outerspace. Early Greek thinkers thought units of life called spores were transferred to different planets including earth. 'Panspermia' is still a favourite idea for some astronomers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Charles Darwin, what is the mechanism of evolution?</text>
            <option id="A">Inheritance of acquired characters</option>
            <option id="B">Natural selection</option>
            <option id="C">Mutation</option>
            <option id="D">Genetic drift</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Charles Darwin concluded that existing living forms share similarities to varying degrees not only among themselves but also with life forms that existed millions of years ago. He proposed that evolution occurs through a process called natural selection.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The fitness, according to Darwin, refers ultimately and only to:</text>
            <option id="A">Physical strength</option>
            <option id="B">Reproductive fitness</option>
            <option id="C">Ability to find food</option>
            <option id="D">Lifespan</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Darwinian fitness refers ultimately and only to reproductive fitness. Hence, those who are better fit in an environment, leave more progeny than others.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Alfred Wallace, a naturalist who worked in the Malay Archipelago, came to similar conclusions as Darwin. What did he observe?</text>
            <option id="A">That all organisms are exactly the same everywhere</option>
            <option id="B">That new species arise from pre-existing species over time</option>
            <option id="C">That the earth is only a few thousand years old</option>
            <option id="D">That acquired traits are inherited</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Alfred Wallace, a naturalist who worked in Malay Archipelago had also come to similar conclusions around the same time. In due course of time, apparently new types of organisms are recognisable. All the existing life forms share similarities and share common ancestors.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Hardy-Weinberg principle, the sum total of all the allelic frequencies is:</text>
            <option id="A">0</option>
            <option id="B">0.5</option>
            <option id="C">1</option>
            <option id="D">Infinity</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>This principle says that allele frequencies in a population are stable and is constant from generation to generation. The gene pool remains a constant. This is called genetic equilibrium. Sum total of all the allelic frequencies is 1.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In a Hardy-Weinberg equation, p² + 2pq + q² = 1. What does 2pq represent?</text>
            <option id="A">Frequency of homozygous dominant individuals</option>
            <option id="B">Frequency of heterozygous individuals</option>
            <option id="C">Frequency of homozygous recessive individuals</option>
            <option id="D">Frequency of the dominant allele</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Individual frequencies, for example, can be named p, q, etc. In a diploid, p and q represent the frequency of allele A and allele a. The frequency of AA individuals in a population is simply p². Similarly of aa is q², of Aa 2pq. Hence, p² + 2pq + q² = 1.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following factors does NOT affect Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium?</text>
            <option id="A">Gene migration or gene flow</option>
            <option id="B">Random mating</option>
            <option id="C">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="D">Mutation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Five factors are known to affect Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. These are gene migration or gene flow, genetic drift, mutation, genetic recombination and natural selection. Random mating is a condition required for maintaining the equilibrium.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who demonstrated that life comes only from pre-existing life by showing that in pre-sterilised flasks, life did not come from killed yeast, but did in flasks open to air?</text>
            <option id="A">Charles Darwin</option>
            <option id="B">Louis Pasteur</option>
            <option id="C">Alexander Oparin</option>
            <option id="D">Stanley Miller</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Louis Pasteur by careful experimentation demonstrated that life comes only from pre-existing life. He showed that in pre-sterilised flasks, life did not come from killed yeast while in another flask open to air, new living organisms arose from 'killed yeast'.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first cellular form of life did not possibly originate till about how many million years ago?</text>
            <option id="A">500 mya</option>
            <option id="B">1000 mya</option>
            <option id="C">2000 mya</option>
            <option id="D">3000 mya</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The first cellular form of life did not possibly originate till about 2000 million years ago. These were probably single-cells. All life forms were in water environment only.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following refers to the study of fossils to understand evolution?</text>
            <option id="A">Embryology</option>
            <option id="B">Paleontology</option>
            <option id="C">Morphology</option>
            <option id="D">Biogeography</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Fossils are remains of hard parts of life-forms found in rocks. The study of fossils in different sedimentary layers indicates the geological period in which they existed. This paleontology evidence is one of the most direct proofs of evolution.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to the Big Bang theory, how old is the universe?</text>
            <option id="A">4.5 billion years</option>
            <option id="B">10 billion years</option>
            <option id="C">20 billion years</option>
            <option id="D">100 billion years</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The universe is very old – almost 20 billion years old. Huge clusters of galaxies comprise the universe.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which theory attempts to explain the singular huge explosion that unimaginable in physical terms, which created the universe?</text>
            <option id="A">Steady State Theory</option>
            <option id="B">Big Bang Theory</option>
            <option id="C">Nebular Hypothesis</option>
            <option id="D">Panspermia Theory</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Big Bang theory attempts to explain to us the origin of universe. It talks of a singular huge explosion unimaginable in physical terms. The universe expanded and hence, the temperature came down.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the solar system of the Milky Way galaxy, earth was supposed to have been formed about:</text>
            <option id="A">20 billion years back</option>
            <option id="B">4.5 billion years back</option>
            <option id="C">4.0 billion years back</option>
            <option id="D">3.5 billion years back</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In the solar system of the milky way galaxy, earth was supposed to have been formed about 4.5 billion years back.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who is the British naturalist who worked in the Malay Archipelago and came to conclusions similar to Darwin's around the same time?</text>
            <option id="A">Alfred Wallace</option>
            <option id="B">Thomas Malthus</option>
            <option id="C">Jean Baptiste Lamarck</option>
            <option id="D">Hugo de Vries</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Alfred Wallace, a naturalist who worked in Malay Archipelago had also come to similar conclusions around the same time.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Darwin, what is the 'fitness' of an organism ultimately measured by?</text>
            <option id="A">Its physical strength</option>
            <option id="B">Its reproductive fitness</option>
            <option id="C">Its lifespan</option>
            <option id="D">Its ability to find food</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Fitness, according to Darwin, refers ultimately and only to reproductive fitness. Hence, those who are better fit in an environment, leave more progeny than others.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What determines whether an organism will survive more efficiently in a changing environment, according to Darwinian theory?</text>
            <option id="A">Its conscious effort to adapt</option>
            <option id="B">Inherited characteristics (variation)</option>
            <option id="C">Acquired characteristics during its lifetime</option>
            <option id="D">The size of its population</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>There has been gradual evolution of life forms. Any population has built in variation in characteristics. Those characteristics which enable some to survive better in natural conditions (climate, food, physical factors, etc.) would outbreed others that are less-endowed to survive under such natural conditions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Darwin, what is the mechanism by which evolution occurs?</text>
            <option id="A">Use and disuse of organs</option>
            <option id="B">Inheritance of acquired characters</option>
            <option id="C">Natural selection</option>
            <option id="D">Mutation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Darwin concluded that existing living forms share similarities to varying degrees... This process of evolution of different species in a given geographical area starting from a point and literally radiating to other areas of geography (habitats) is called adaptive radiation. Natural selection is the mechanism proposed by Darwin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who proposed the theory of evolution based on the 'use and disuse' of organs?</text>
            <option id="A">Charles Darwin</option>
            <option id="B">Alfred Wallace</option>
            <option id="C">Jean Baptiste Lamarck</option>
            <option id="D">Thomas Malthus</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>French naturalist Lamarck had said that evolution of life forms had occurred but driven by use and disuse of organs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the classic example Lamarck used to explain his theory of use and disuse of organs?</text>
            <option id="A">The long neck of giraffes</option>
            <option id="B">The beak shapes of Darwin's finches</option>
            <option id="C">Industrial melanism in peppered moths</option>
            <option id="D">Antibiotic resistance in bacteria</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>French naturalist Lamarck had said that evolution of life forms had occurred but driven by use and disuse of organs. He gave the examples of Giraffes who in an attempt to forage leaves on tall trees had to adapt by elongation of their necks.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Hardy-Weinberg principle, allele frequencies in a population are stable and is constant from generation to generation. This is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="B">Genetic equilibrium</option>
            <option id="C">Natural selection</option>
            <option id="D">Mutation rate</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>This principle says that allele frequencies in a population are stable and is constant from generation to generation. The gene pool... remains a constant. This is called genetic equilibrium.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the Hardy-Weinberg equation (p² + 2pq + q² = 1), what does p² represent?</text>
            <option id="A">Frequency of heterozygous individuals</option>
            <option id="B">Frequency of homozygous recessive individuals</option>
            <option id="C">Frequency of homozygous dominant individuals</option>
            <option id="D">Frequency of mutations</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The frequency of AA individuals in a population is simply p². This is simply stated in another ways, i.e., the probability that an allele A with a frequency of p appear on both the chromosomes of a diploid individual is simply the product of the probabilities, i.e., p².</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the Hardy-Weinberg equation, what does 2pq represent?</text>
            <option id="A">Frequency of the dominant allele</option>
            <option id="B">Frequency of homozygous individuals</option>
            <option id="C">Frequency of heterozygous individuals</option>
            <option id="D">Frequency of the recessive allele</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Similarly of aa is q², of Aa 2pq. Hence, p² + 2pq + q² = 1.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>About 2000 million years ago, the first cellular forms of life appeared on earth. Some of these cells had the ability to release O2. The reaction could have been similar to the light reaction in:</text>
            <option id="A">Respiration</option>
            <option id="B">Photosynthesis</option>
            <option id="C">Chemosynthesis</option>
            <option id="D">Fermentation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>About 2000 million years ago (mya) the first cellular forms of life appeared on earth... Some of these cells had the ability to release O2. The reaction could have been similar to the light reaction in photosynthesis where water is split with the help of solar energy captured and channelised by appropriate light harvesting pigments.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>By the time of 500 million years ago (mya), which of the following organisms were formed and became active?</text>
            <option id="A">Invertebrates</option>
            <option id="B">Jawless fish</option>
            <option id="C">Reptiles</option>
            <option id="D">Mammals</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Slowly single-celled organisms became multi-cellular forms. By the time of 500 mya, invertebrates were formed and active.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Jawless fish probably evolved around how many million years ago?</text>
            <option id="A">500 mya</option>
            <option id="B">350 mya</option>
            <option id="C">320 mya</option>
            <option id="D">200 mya</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Jawless fish probably evolved around 350 mya.</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following provides evidence for divergent evolution?</text>
            <option id="A">Flippers of penguins and dolphins</option>
            <option id="B">Eye of the octopus and mammals</option>
            <option id="C">Forelimbs of whales, bats, cheetah, and humans</option>
            <option id="D">Sweet potato and potato</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Forelimbs of whales, bats, cheetah, and humans share similarities in the pattern of bones (humerus, radius, ulna, carpals, metacarpals, phalanges) but perform different functions. This represents homologous organs, which indicate divergent evolution from a common ancestor.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Industrial melanism as observed in peppered moth (Biston betularia) in England is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Artificial selection</option>
            <option id="B">Directional natural selection</option>
            <option id="C">Stabilizing natural selection</option>
            <option id="D">Disruptive natural selection</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Industrial melanism is an excellent example of directional natural selection, where the environment changed (pollution darkened the tree trunks), shifting the survival advantage from the light-colored moths to the dark-colored (melanic) moths.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the Hardy-Weinberg equation, p² + 2pq + q² = 1, the term '2pq' represents:</text>
            <option id="A">The frequency of the dominant allele</option>
            <option id="B">The frequency of homozygous recessive individuals</option>
            <option id="C">The frequency of heterozygous individuals</option>
            <option id="D">The frequency of homozygous dominant individuals</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In the Hardy-Weinberg equation, p represents the dominant allele frequency, q is the recessive allele frequency. Therefore, p² is homozygous dominant, q² is homozygous recessive, and 2pq represents the frequency of heterozygous individuals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The brain capacity of Homo habilis was approximately:</text>
            <option id="A">400 - 500 cc</option>
            <option id="B">650 - 800 cc</option>
            <option id="C">900 cc</option>
            <option id="D">1400 cc</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Homo habilis was the first human-like hominid. They probably did not eat meat, and their brain capacities were between 650-800 cc. Homo erectus had a larger brain capacity around 900 cc.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Industrial melanism as observed in peppered moth (Biston betularia) in England is an excellent example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="B">Directional natural selection</option>
            <option id="C">Disruptive natural selection</option>
            <option id="D">Stabilizing natural selection</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Industrial melanism is a classic example of directional natural selection, where the environment changed (due to industrial smoke), shifting the advantage from the light-colored moths to the dark-colored (melanic) moths.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process by which organisms with different evolutionary history evolve similar phenotypic adaptations in response to a common environmental challenge is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Divergent evolution</option>
            <option id="C">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <option id="D">Co-evolution</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Convergent evolution is the process whereby organisms not closely related independently evolve similar traits as a result of having to adapt to similar environments or ecological niches (e.g., wings of butterfly and bird).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the Hardy-Weinberg equation (p^2 + 2pq + q^2 = 1), what does the term '2pq' represent?</text>
            <option id="A">The frequency of the dominant allele</option>
            <option id="B">The frequency of homozygous dominant individuals</option>
            <option id="C">The frequency of heterozygous individuals</option>
            <option id="D">The frequency of homozygous recessive individuals</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In the Hardy-Weinberg equation, p^2 represents the frequency of homozygous dominant individuals, q^2 represents homozygous recessive individuals, and 2pq represents the frequency of heterozygous individuals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first cellular form of life could not possibly have originated before:</text>
            <option id="A">4.5 billion years ago</option>
            <option id="B">3 billion years ago</option>
            <option id="C">2 billion years ago</option>
            <option id="D">2000 million years ago</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The first non-cellular forms of life could have originated 3 billion years back. The first cellular form of life did not possibly originate till about 2000 million years ago.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Fossils are generally found in which type of rocks?</text>
            <option id="A">Igneous rocks</option>
            <option id="B">Sedimentary rocks</option>
            <option id="C">Metamorphic rocks</option>
            <option id="D">Volcanic rocks</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Fossils are remains of hard parts of life-forms found in rocks. Rocks form sediments and a cross-section of earth's crust indicates the arrangement of sediments one over the other during the long history of earth. Fossils are found in sedimentary rocks.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following islands was visited by Charles Darwin during his voyage on the H.M.S. Beagle?</text>
            <option id="A">Madagascar</option>
            <option id="B">Galapagos Islands</option>
            <option id="C">Greenland</option>
            <option id="D">Sri Lanka</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>During his journey, Darwin went to Galapagos Islands. There he observed an amazing diversity of creatures, including the famous small black birds later called Darwin's Finches.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The evolution of different species in a given geographical area starting from a point and literally radiating to other areas of geography is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <option id="C">Saltation</option>
            <option id="D">Genetic drift</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>This process of evolution of different species in a given geographical area starting from a point and literally radiating to other areas of geography (habitats) is called adaptive radiation. Darwin's finches represent one of the best examples of this phenomenon.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Australian marsupials and placental mammals showing corresponding forms (e.g., Tasmanian wolf and placental wolf) is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Divergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="C">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <option id="D">Mutation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When more than one adaptive radiation appeared to have occurred in an isolated geographical area (representing different habitats), one can call this convergent evolution. Placental mammals in Australia also exhibit adaptive radiation in evolving into varieties of such placental mammals each of which appears to be 'similar' to a corresponding marsupial.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who experimentally dismissed the theory of spontaneous generation once and for all by using swan-necked flasks?</text>
            <option id="A">Charles Darwin</option>
            <option id="B">Alexander Oparin</option>
            <option id="C">Louis Pasteur</option>
            <option id="D">Stanley Miller</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Louis Pasteur by careful experimentation demonstrated that life comes only from pre-existing life. He showed that in pre-sterilised flasks, life did not come from killed yeast while in another flask open to air, new living organisms arose from 'killed yeast'.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Oparin of Russia and Haldane of England proposed that the first form of life could have come from pre-existing:</text>
            <option id="A">Living organisms</option>
            <option id="B">Non-living organic molecules</option>
            <option id="C">Inorganic gases</option>
            <option id="D">Spores from space</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Oparin of Russia and Haldane of England proposed that the first form of life could have come from pre-existing non-living organic molecules (e.g. RNA, protein, etc.) and that formation of life was preceded by chemical evolution.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In his 1953 experiment simulating primitive Earth conditions, S.L. Miller observed the formation of which organic molecules?</text>
            <option id="A">Nucleic acids</option>
            <option id="B">Proteins</option>
            <option id="C">Amino acids</option>
            <option id="D">Lipids</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In 1953, S.L. Miller, an American scientist created similar conditions in a laboratory scale. He created electric discharge in a closed flask containing CH4, H2, NH3 and water vapour at 800 degree C. He observed formation of amino acids.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first non-cellular forms of life could have originated ________ years ago.</text>
            <option id="A">2 billion</option>
            <option id="B">3 billion</option>
            <option id="C">4 billion</option>
            <option id="D">4.5 billion</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The first non-cellular forms of life could have originated 3 billion years back. They would have been giant molecules (RNA, Protein, Polysaccharides, etc.).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Fossils are the remains of hard parts of life-forms found in rocks. The study of fossils to understand evolution is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Embryology</option>
            <option id="B">Paleontology</option>
            <option id="C">Biogeography</option>
            <option id="D">Molecular biology</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Fossils are remains of hard parts of life-forms found in rocks. A study of fossils in different sedimentary layers indicates the geological period in which they existed. The study showed that life-forms varied over time and certain life forms are restricted to certain geological time spans. Hence, new forms of life have arisen at different times in the history of earth. All this is called paleontological evidence.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The presence of gills in the embryos of all vertebrates, including humans, which later disappear in adults, is an example of evidence for evolution from:</text>
            <option id="A">Paleontology</option>
            <option id="B">Embryology</option>
            <option id="C">Biogeography</option>
            <option id="D">Anatomy</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Embryological support for evolution was also proposed by Ernst Haeckel based upon the observation of certain features during embryonic stage common to all vertebrates that are absent in adult. For example, the embryos of all vertebrates including human develop a row of vestigial gill slit just behind the head but it is a functional organ only in fish and not found in any other adult vertebrates.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who carefully performed experiments and disapproved the embryological support for evolution proposed by Ernst Haeckel, noting that embryos never pass through the adult stages of other animals?</text>
            <option id="A">Karl Ernst von Baer</option>
            <option id="B">Charles Darwin</option>
            <option id="C">Hugo de Vries</option>
            <option id="D">Jean Baptiste Lamarck</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>However, this proposal was disapproved on careful study performed by Karl Ernst von Baer. He noted that embryos never pass through the adult stages of other animals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The development of dark-coloured (melanic) moths in England in response to industrial pollution is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Directional selection</option>
            <option id="B">Disruptive selection</option>
            <option id="C">Stabilising selection</option>
            <option id="D">Artificial selection</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Industrial melanism as observed in peppered moth proves that in a mixed population, those that can better-adapt, survive and increase in population size. Remember that no variant is completely wiped out. This represents directional selection as the environment shifts the peak of the trait distribution in one direction.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When a small group of individuals is isolated from the rest of the population, they may carry only a small sample of the genetic variation of the parent population. If they establish a new population, this effect is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Bottleneck effect</option>
            <option id="B">Founder effect</option>
            <option id="C">Gene flow</option>
            <option id="D">Directional selection</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Sometimes the change in allele frequency is so different in the new sample of population that they become a different species. The original drifted population becomes founders and the effect is called founder effect.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In natural selection, if more individuals acquire a mean character value, leading to a narrower and taller peak in the trait distribution, this type of selection is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Directional selection</option>
            <option id="B">Disruptive selection</option>
            <option id="C">Stabilising selection</option>
            <option id="D">Artificial selection</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Natural selection can lead to stabilisation (in which more individuals acquire mean character value), directional change (more individuals acquire value other than the mean character value) or disruption (more individuals acquire peripheral character value at both ends of the distribution curve).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>About how many million years ago (mya) did the first non-cellular forms of life originate?</text>
            <option id="A">500 mya</option>
            <option id="B">2000 mya</option>
            <option id="C">3000 mya</option>
            <option id="D">4500 mya</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The first non-cellular forms of life could have originated 3 billion years back (3000 mya). They would have been giant molecules (RNA, Protein, Polysaccharides, etc.).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which extinct reptiles went back into water to evolve into fish-like reptiles (e.g., Ichthyosaurs) probably around 200 mya?</text>
            <option id="A">Dinosaurs</option>
            <option id="B">Pelycosaurs</option>
            <option id="C">Therapsids</option>
            <option id="D">Some land reptiles</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Some of these land reptiles went back into water to evolve into fish like reptiles probably 200 mya (e.g. Ichthyosaurs). The land reptiles were, of course, the dinosaurs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Homology is based on:</text>
            <option id="A">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Divergent evolution</option>
            <option id="C">Parallel evolution</option>
            <option id="D">Co-evolution</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Homology indicates common ancestry. Homology is based on divergent evolution whereas analogy refers to a situation exactly opposite. These structures developed along different directions due to adaptions to different needs. This is divergent evolution and these structures are homologous.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Sweet potato (root modification) and potato (stem modification) are examples of:</text>
            <option id="A">Homologous structures</option>
            <option id="B">Analogous structures</option>
            <option id="C">Vestigial structures</option>
            <option id="D">Atavism</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Sweet potato (root modification) and potato (stem modification) is another example for analogy. Analogous structures are a result of convergent evolution - different structures evolving for the same function.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which evolutionary principle does the similarity in proteins and genes among diverse organisms support?</text>
            <option id="A">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Common ancestry</option>
            <option id="C">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="D">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Similarities in proteins and genes performing a given function among diverse organisms give clues to common ancestry. These biochemical similarities point to the same shared ancestry as structural similarities among diverse organisms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What type of evolution does the development of the camera eye of the octopus and of mammals illustrate?</text>
            <option id="A">Divergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="C">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <option id="D">Saltation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The eye of the octopus and of mammals are analogous structures. They are not anatomically similar structures though they perform similar functions. This is convergent evolution.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What was the composition of the early Earth's atmosphere?</text>
            <option id="A">Oxygen, nitrogen, and carbon dioxide</option>
            <option id="B">Water vapour, methane, carbon dioxide, and ammonia</option>
            <option id="C">Oxygen, ozone, and argon</option>
            <option id="D">Helium, hydrogen, and oxygen</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>There was no atmosphere on early earth. Water vapour, methane, carbon dioxide and ammonia released from molten mass covered the surface.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The UV rays from the sun broke up water on early Earth into Hydrogen and Oxygen. What happened to these gases?</text>
            <option id="A">Both gases escaped into space</option>
            <option id="B">Both gases remained in the atmosphere</option>
            <option id="C">The lighter H2 escaped, while oxygen combined with ammonia and methane to form water, CO2 and others</option>
            <option id="D">Oxygen escaped, and hydrogen combined with other elements</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The UV rays from the sun broke up water into Hydrogen and Oxygen and the lighter H2 escaped. Oxygen combined with ammonia and methane to form water, CO2 and others.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The theory that life came from outerspace in the form of spores is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Spontaneous generation</option>
            <option id="B">Panspermia</option>
            <option id="C">Chemical evolution</option>
            <option id="D">Biogenesis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some scientists believe that it came from outside. Early Greek thinkers thought units of life called spores were transferred to different planets including earth. 'Panspermia' is still a favourite idea for some astronomers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Louis Pasteur carefully demonstrated that life comes only from pre-existing life, thus disproving the theory of:</text>
            <option id="A">Chemical evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Spontaneous generation</option>
            <option id="C">Biogenesis</option>
            <option id="D">Special creation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Louis Pasteur by careful experimentation demonstrated that life comes only from pre-existing life. He showed that in pre-sterilised flasks, life did not come from killed yeast while in another flask open to air, new living organisms arose from 'killed yeast'. Spontaneous generation theory was dismissed once and for all.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following lines of evidence provides the most direct, observable record of the history of life on Earth?</text>
            <option id="A">Embryological evidence</option>
            <option id="B">Homologous structures</option>
            <option id="C">Paleontological evidence (Fossils)</option>
            <option id="D">Biogeography</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Fossils are remains of hard parts of life-forms found in rocks. The study of fossils in different sedimentary layers indicates the geological period in which they existed. This paleontology evidence is one of the most direct proofs of evolution.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which German scientist proposed the embryological support for evolution, stating that embryos pass through adult stages of their ancestors?</text>
            <option id="A">Karl Ernst von Baer</option>
            <option id="B">Ernst Haeckel</option>
            <option id="C">Charles Darwin</option>
            <option id="D">Hugo de Vries</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Embryological support for evolution was also proposed by Ernst Haeckel based upon the observation of certain features during embryonic stage common to all vertebrates that are absent in adult.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who carefully studied embryos and disproved Ernst Haeckel's proposal that embryos pass through adult ancestral stages?</text>
            <option id="A">Charles Darwin</option>
            <option id="B">Karl Ernst von Baer</option>
            <option id="C">Alfred Wallace</option>
            <option id="D">Thomas Malthus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>However, this proposal [Haeckel's] was disapproved on careful study performed by Karl Ernst von Baer. He noted that embryos never pass through the adult stages of other animals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The forelimbs of whales, bats, cheetahs, and humans share similarities in the pattern of bones. This indicates:</text>
            <option id="A">Analogy</option>
            <option id="B">Homology</option>
            <option id="C">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="D">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>For example, whales, bats, Cheetah and human (all mammals) share similarities in the pattern of bones of forelimbs. Though these forelimbs perform different functions in these animals, they have similar anatomical structure. Hence, in these animals, the same structure developed along different directions due to adaptations to different needs. This is divergent evolution and these structures are homologous. Homology indicates common ancestry.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What do we call the process of evolution of different species in a given geographical area starting from a point and radiating to other habitats?</text>
            <option id="A">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <option id="C">Parallel evolution</option>
            <option id="D">Coevolution</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>This process of evolution of different species in a given geographical area starting from a point and literally radiating to other areas of geography (habitats) is called adaptive radiation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Darwin's finches found on the Galapagos Islands are one of the best examples of:</text>
            <option id="A">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <option id="B">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="C">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="D">Mutation</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Darwin's finches represent one of the best examples of this phenomenon [adaptive radiation].</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which other group of animals in Australia exhibits adaptive radiation similar to Darwin's finches, having evolved from an ancestral stock within the Australian island continent?</text>
            <option id="A">Placental mammals</option>
            <option id="B">Marsupials</option>
            <option id="C">Monotremes</option>
            <option id="D">Reptiles</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Another example is Australian marsupials. A number of marsupials, each different from the other evolved from an ancestral stock, but all within the Australian island continent.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When more than one adaptive radiation occurs in an isolated geographical area representing different habitats, resulting in unrelated groups developing similar adaptations, what is this called?</text>
            <option id="A">Divergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="C">Sympatric speciation</option>
            <option id="D">Directional selection</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When more than one adaptive radiation appeared to have occurred in an isolated geographical area (representing different habitats), one can call this convergent evolution.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following factors does NOT affect Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium?</text>
            <option id="A">Gene migration</option>
            <option id="B">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="C">Random mating</option>
            <option id="D">Natural selection</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Five factors are known to affect Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. These are gene migration or gene flow, genetic drift, mutation, genetic recombination and natural selection. (Random mating maintains equilibrium).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When a section of a population migrates to another place, gene frequencies change in both the original and new populations. If this migration occurs multiple times, it is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="B">Founder effect</option>
            <option id="C">Gene flow</option>
            <option id="D">Mutation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>When migration of a section of population to another place and population occurs, gene frequencies change in the original as well as in the new population... If this gene migration, happens multiple times, it would be a gene flow.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If a change in gene frequency occurs completely by chance rather than through migration or selection, it is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Gene flow</option>
            <option id="B">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="C">Recombination</option>
            <option id="D">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>If the same change occurs by chance, it is called genetic drift.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Sometimes the change in allele frequency due to genetic drift is so drastically different in the new sample of population that they become a different species. The original drifted population becomes founders and the effect is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Bottleneck effect</option>
            <option id="B">Founder effect</option>
            <option id="C">Gene flow effect</option>
            <option id="D">Directional effect</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Sometimes the change in allele frequency is so different in the new sample of population that they become a different species. The original drifted population becomes founders and the effect is called founder effect.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Sea weeds and few plants existed probably around how many million years ago?</text>
            <option id="A">500 mya</option>
            <option id="B">350 mya</option>
            <option id="C">320 mya</option>
            <option id="D">65 mya</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Sea weeds and few plants existed probably around 320 mya.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which organisms were the first to invade land?</text>
            <option id="A">Insects</option>
            <option id="B">Amphibians</option>
            <option id="C">Plants</option>
            <option id="D">Reptiles</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>We are told that the first organisms that invaded land were plants. They were widespread on land when animals invaded land.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Fish with stout and strong fins could move on land and go back to water. This occurred about 350 mya. In 1938, a fish of this type, thought to be extinct, was caught in South Africa. What was it called?</text>
            <option id="A">Lungfish</option>
            <option id="B">Coelacanth</option>
            <option id="C">Shark</option>
            <option id="D">Ray</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Fish with stout and strong fins could move on land and go back to water. This was about 350 mya. In 1938, a fish caught in South Africa happened to be a Coelacanth which was thought to be extinct.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Coelacanths, also known as lobefins, evolved into which group of animals that lived both on land and in water?</text>
            <option id="A">Reptiles</option>
            <option id="B">Mammals</option>
            <option id="C">Amphibians</option>
            <option id="D">Birds</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>These animals called lobefins evolved into the first amphibians that lived on both land and water.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>According to Hugo de Vries, the mechanism of evolution is:</text>
            <option id="A">Continuous minor variations</option>
            <option id="B">Inheritance of acquired characters</option>
            <option id="C">Saltation (single step large mutation)</option>
            <option id="D">Natural selection</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Hugo de Vries, based on his work on evening primrose, proposed that mutations are random and directionless and cause evolution. He believed mutation caused speciation and called it saltation (single step large mutation), unlike Darwin who believed evolution was gradual.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the Miller-Urey experiment, the gases circulated in the closed flask were:</text>
            <option id="A">CH4, NH3, H2, and H2O vapor at 800°C</option>
            <option id="B">CO2, NH3, H2, and H2O vapor at 800°C</option>
            <option id="C">CH4, NO2, H2, and H2O vapor at 500°C</option>
            <option id="D">CH4, NH3, O2, and H2O vapor at 800°C</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>S.L. Miller created electric discharge in a closed flask containing CH4 (methane), H2 (hydrogen), NH3 (ammonia), and water vapor at 800°C to simulate primitive Earth conditions. Notably, oxygen (O2) was absent as primitive Earth had a reducing atmosphere.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The phenomenon where a small portion of a population breaks away and forms a new population in a new geographic area, exhibiting a different allelic frequency from the original population, is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Gene migration</option>
            <option id="B">Genetic recombination</option>
            <option id="C">Founder effect</option>
            <option id="D">Directional selection</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>When a small group of individuals breaks off from a larger population to establish a colony, the new colony may have different allele frequencies than the original population. This specific type of genetic drift is called the Founder effect.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Hugo de Vries, the mechanism of evolution is:</text>
            <option id="A">Multiple step mutations</option>
            <option id="B">Saltation</option>
            <option id="C">Phenotypic variations</option>
            <option id="D">Use and disuse of organs</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Hugo de Vries believed that it is mutation which causes evolution and not the minor variations (heritable) that Darwin talked about. He called this saltation (single step large mutation).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following factors is NOT considered to affect Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium?</text>
            <option id="A">Gene migration</option>
            <option id="B">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="C">Random mating</option>
            <option id="D">Mutation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium relies on the assumption of random mating. Factors that affect (disrupt) the equilibrium include gene migration, genetic drift, mutation, genetic recombination, and natural selection.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The 'Founder Effect' is a special case of:</text>
            <option id="A">Natural selection</option>
            <option id="B">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="C">Mutation</option>
            <option id="D">Gene flow</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When a small group of individuals breaks off from a larger population to establish a colony, the new colony may have a different allele frequency than the original population. This is a type of genetic drift known as the founder effect.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following hominids had a brain capacity of about 900 cc and probably ate meat?</text>
            <option id="A">Australopithecus</option>
            <option id="B">Homo habilis</option>
            <option id="C">Homo erectus</option>
            <option id="D">Neanderthal man</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Fossils discovered in Java in 1891 revealed the next stage, i.e., Homo erectus about 1.5 mya. Homo erectus had a large brain around 900 cc. Homo erectus probably ate meat.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Agriculture came around how many years ago?</text>
            <option id="A">1,00,000 years ago</option>
            <option id="B">40,000 years ago</option>
            <option id="C">10,000 years ago</option>
            <option id="D">1,000 years ago</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>During ice age between 75,000-10,000 years ago modern Homo sapiens arose. Agriculture came around 10,000 years back and human settlements started.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which extinct lobe-finned fish was discovered in South Africa in 1938 and is thought to have evolved into the first amphibians?</text>
            <option id="A">Ichthyosaur</option>
            <option id="B">Coelacanth</option>
            <option id="C">Lungfish</option>
            <option id="D">Pteranodon</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In 1938, a fish caught in South Africa happened to be a Coelacanth which was thought to be extinct. These animals, called lobefins, evolved into the first amphibians that lived on both land and water.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The concept of 'use and disuse of organs' as a mechanism for evolution was proposed by:</text>
            <option id="A">Charles Darwin</option>
            <option id="B">Alfred Wallace</option>
            <option id="C">Jean Baptiste Lamarck</option>
            <option id="D">Hugo de Vries</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>French naturalist Lamarck had said that evolution of life forms had occurred but driven by use and disuse of organs. He gave the examples of Giraffes who in an attempt to forage leaves on tall trees had to adapt by elongation of their necks.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following describes 'homologous organs'?</text>
            <option id="A">Organs with different structure but similar function.</option>
            <option id="B">Organs with similar structure but different functions.</option>
            <option id="C">Organs present only in embryos.</option>
            <option id="D">Vestigial organs with no function.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Homology indicates common ancestry. Homologous organs have the same basic structural plan but perform different functions. For example, forelimbs of whales, bats, Cheetah and human share similarities in the pattern of bones but perform different functions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Sweet potato (a root modification) and potato (a stem modification) storing food is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Homology</option>
            <option id="B">Analogy</option>
            <option id="C">Atavism</option>
            <option id="D">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Analogy refers to a situation exactly opposite to homology. Analogous structures are a result of convergent evolution - different structures evolving for the same function. Sweet potato (root modification) and potato (stem modification) is an example of analogy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The evolution of different species in a given geographical area starting from a point and literally radiating to other areas of geography (habitats) is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <option id="C">Parallel evolution</option>
            <option id="D">Coevolution</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>This process of evolution of different species in a given geographical area starting from a point and literally radiating to other areas of geography (habitats) is called adaptive radiation. Darwin's finches represent one of the best examples of this phenomenon.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Australian marsupials, each different from the other (like kangaroo, Tasmanian wolf), evolved from an ancestral stock, but all within the Australian island continent. This is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Adaptive radiation</option>
            <option id="C">Mutation</option>
            <option id="D">Genetic drift</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Another example is Australian marsupials. A number of marsupials, each different from the other evolved from an ancestral stock, but all within the Australian island continent. This is also adaptive radiation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who proposed the mutation theory of evolution, stating that mutations are random, directionless, and cause speciation (saltation)?</text>
            <option id="A">Charles Darwin</option>
            <option id="B">Hugo de Vries</option>
            <option id="C">Thomas Malthus</option>
            <option id="D">Jean Baptiste Lamarck</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In the first decade of twentieth century, Hugo deVries based on his work on evening primrose brought forth the idea of mutations - large difference arising suddenly in a population. He believed that it is mutation which causes evolution and not the minor variations (heritable) that Darwin talked about.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The biggest dinosaur, which was about 20 feet in height and had huge fearsome dagger-like teeth, was:</text>
            <option id="A">Brachiosaurus</option>
            <option id="B">Triceratops</option>
            <option id="C">Tyrannosaurus rex</option>
            <option id="D">Stegosaurus</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The biggest of them, i.e., Tyrannosaurus rex, was about 20 feet in height and had huge fearsome dagger like teeth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following hominids had a brain capacity between 650-800 cc and probably did not eat meat?</text>
            <option id="A">Homo habilis</option>
            <option id="B">Homo erectus</option>
            <option id="C">Homo sapiens</option>
            <option id="D">Australopithecus</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>This creature was called the first human-like being the hominid and was called Homo habilis. The brain capacities were between 650-800cc. They probably did not eat meat.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which hominid species lived in near east and central Asia between 1,00,000-40,000 years back, used hides to protect their body and buried their dead?</text>
            <option id="A">Homo erectus</option>
            <option id="B">Neanderthal man</option>
            <option id="C">Homo habilis</option>
            <option id="D">Australopithecus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Neanderthal man with a brain size of 1400cc lived in near east and central Asia between 1,00,000-40,000 years back. They used hides to protect their body and buried their dead.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When did jawless fish probably evolve?</text>
            <option id="A">500 mya</option>
            <option id="B">350 mya</option>
            <option id="C">320 mya</option>
            <option id="D">200 mya</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>By the time of 500 mya, invertebrates were formed and active. Jawless fish probably evolved around 350 mya. Sea weeds and few plants existed probably around 320 mya.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which ancient lobefins (stout and strong-finned fishes) could move on land and go back to water, evolving into the first amphibians?</text>
            <option id="A">Coelacanth</option>
            <option id="B">Ichthyosaurs</option>
            <option id="C">Pelycosaurs</option>
            <option id="D">Therapsids</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In 1938, a fish caught in South Africa happened to be a Coelacanth which was thought to be extinct. These animals called lobefins evolved into the first amphibians that lived on both land and water.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which reptiles dominated the earth for millions of years but went extinct abruptly about 65 million years ago?</text>
            <option id="A">Turtles</option>
            <option id="B">Crocodiles</option>
            <option id="C">Dinosaurs</option>
            <option id="D">Synapsids</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Some of them, the land reptiles, were of course, the dinosaurs. The biggest of them, i.e., Tyrannosaurus rex, was about 20 feet in height. About 65 mya, the dinosaurs suddenly disappeared from the earth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Oparin of Russia and Haldane of England proposed that the first form of life could have come from pre-existing non-living organic molecules. This theory is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Biogenesis</option>
            <option id="B">Chemical evolution</option>
            <option id="C">Spontaneous generation</option>
            <option id="D">Panspermia</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Oparin of Russia and Haldane of England proposed that the first form of life could have come from pre-existing non-living organic molecules (e.g. RNA, protein, etc.) and that formation of life was preceded by chemical evolution, i.e., formation of diverse organic molecules from inorganic constituents.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In 1953, S.L. Miller created an electric discharge in a closed flask containing CH4, H2, NH3, and water vapour at 800°C. What did he observe the formation of?</text>
            <option id="A">Nucleic acids</option>
            <option id="B">Proteins</option>
            <option id="C">Amino acids</option>
            <option id="D">Lipids</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In 1953, S.L. Miller, an American scientist created similar conditions in a laboratory scale. He created electric discharge in a closed flask containing CH4, H2, NH3 and water vapour at 8000C. He observed formation of amino acids.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first non-cellular forms of life could have originated about how many years ago?</text>
            <option id="A">4 billion years</option>
            <option id="B">3 billion years</option>
            <option id="C">2 billion years</option>
            <option id="D">1 billion years</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>We have no idea about how the first self replicating metabolic capsule of life arose. The first non-cellular forms of life could have originated 3 billion years back. They would have been giant molecules (RNA, Protein, Polysaccharides, etc.).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Homologous structures are a result of which evolutionary process?</text>
            <option id="A">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Divergent evolution</option>
            <option id="C">Parallel evolution</option>
            <option id="D">Coevolution</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Hence, in these animals, the same structure developed along different directions due to adaptations to different needs. This is divergent evolution and these structures are homologous.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In plants, the thorn of Bougainvillea and the tendril of Cucurbita represent:</text>
            <option id="A">Analogous structures</option>
            <option id="B">Homologous structures</option>
            <option id="C">Vestigial structures</option>
            <option id="D">Atavism</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Homology indicates common ancestry. Other examples are vertebrate hearts or brains. In plants also, the thorn and tendrils of Bougainvillea and Cucurbita represent homology.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following pairs are considered analogous structures?</text>
            <option id="A">Forelimbs of man and cheetah</option>
            <option id="B">Thorn of Bougainvillea and tendril of Cucurbita</option>
            <option id="C">Wings of a butterfly and wings of a bird</option>
            <option id="D">Vertebrate hearts</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Wings of butterfly and of birds look alike. They are not anatomically similar structures though they perform similar functions. Hence, analogous structures are a result of convergent evolution.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In Australia, placental mammals also exhibit adaptive radiation and have evolved into varieties that appear similar to corresponding marsupials. This similarity between a placental mammal (like a Placental wolf) and a marsupial (like a Tasmanian wolf) is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Divergent evolution</option>
            <option id="B">Convergent evolution</option>
            <option id="C">Homology</option>
            <option id="D">Coevolution</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Placental mammals in Australia also exhibit adaptive radiation in evolving into varieties of such placental mammals each of which appears to be 'similar' to a corresponding marsupial (e.g., Placental wolf and Tasmanian wolf-marsupial). This is convergent evolution.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to Darwin, what are the two key concepts of his Theory of Evolution?</text>
            <option id="A">Branching descent and natural selection</option>
            <option id="B">Use and disuse, and inheritance of acquired traits</option>
            <option id="C">Mutation and genetic drift</option>
            <option id="D">Gene flow and Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Branching descent and natural selection are the two key concepts of Darwinian Theory of Evolution.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What did Thomas Malthus write an essay on, which greatly influenced Darwin's ideas about natural selection?</text>
            <option id="A">Genetics</option>
            <option id="B">Populations</option>
            <option id="C">Geology</option>
            <option id="D">Embryology</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The work of Thomas Malthus on populations influenced Darwin. Natural selection is based on certain observations which are factual.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Natural selection can lead to different outcomes. Which type of selection occurs when more individuals acquire the mean character value, making the peak higher and narrower?</text>
            <option id="A">Directional selection</option>
            <option id="B">Stabilising selection</option>
            <option id="C">Disruptive selection</option>
            <option id="D">Artificial selection</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Natural selection can lead to stabilisation (in which more individuals acquire mean character value), directional change... or disruption...</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If natural selection leads to more individuals acquiring values other than the mean character value (shifting the peak in one direction), it is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Stabilising selection</option>
            <option id="B">Directional selection</option>
            <option id="C">Disruptive selection</option>
            <option id="D">Convergent selection</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Natural selection can lead to... directional change (more individuals acquire value other than the mean character value)...</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What type of natural selection occurs when more individuals acquire peripheral character values at both ends of the distribution curve, forming two peaks?</text>
            <option id="A">Stabilising selection</option>
            <option id="B">Directional selection</option>
            <option id="C">Disruptive selection</option>
            <option id="D">Random selection</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Natural selection can lead to... disruption (more individuals acquire peripheral character value at both ends of the distribution curve).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first amphibians were the ancestors of modern-day:</text>
            <option id="A">Snakes and lizards</option>
            <option id="B">Frogs and salamanders</option>
            <option id="C">Crocodiles and turtles</option>
            <option id="D">Dinosaurs</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>These animals called lobefins evolved into the first amphibians that lived on both land and water. There are no specimens of these left with us. However, these were ancestors of modern day frogs and salamanders.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Amphibians evolved into reptiles. What is a key characteristic of reptilian eggs compared to amphibian eggs?</text>
            <option id="A">They are laid in water</option>
            <option id="B">They are soft and jelly-like</option>
            <option id="C">They have thick shells and do not dry up in the sun</option>
            <option id="D">They do not need to be fertilized</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The amphibians evolved into reptiles. They lay thick-shelled eggs which do not dry up in sun unlike those of amphibians.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Giant ferns (pteridophytes) were present during the evolution of reptiles, but they all fell to form what deposits slowly over time?</text>
            <option id="A">Limestone</option>
            <option id="B">Coal</option>
            <option id="C">Petroleum</option>
            <option id="D">Iron ore</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Giant ferns (pteridophytes) were present but they all fell to form coal deposits slowly.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>