<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="330" name="Human Health and Disease">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following diseases is caused by a protozoan?</text>
            <option id="A">Typhoid</option>
            <option id="B">Malaria</option>
            <option id="C">Pneumonia</option>
            <option id="D">Ringworm</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Malaria is caused by Plasmodium, a tiny protozoan. Typhoid and pneumonia are bacterial diseases, while ringworm is caused by fungi.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The yellowish fluid 'colostrum' secreted by mother during the initial days of lactation has abundant antibodies to protect the infant. Which antibody is most abundant in it?</text>
            <option id="A">IgA</option>
            <option id="B">IgM</option>
            <option id="C">IgG</option>
            <option id="D">IgE</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Colostrum is rich in IgA antibodies, providing natural passive immunity to the infant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Widal test is used for the diagnosis of:</text>
            <option id="A">Malaria</option>
            <option id="B">Cholera</option>
            <option id="C">Typhoid</option>
            <option id="D">Tuberculosis</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Typhoid fever, caused by the bacterium Salmonella typhi, can be confirmed by the Widal test.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following diseases is transmitted by the bite of an infected female Culex mosquito?</text>
            <option id="A">Malaria</option>
            <option id="B">Dengue</option>
            <option id="C">Filariasis</option>
            <option id="D">Chikungunya</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Wuchereria (W. bancrofti and W. malayi), the filarial worms cause a slowly developing chronic inflammation of the organs in which they live for many years, usually the lymphatic vessels of the lower limbs and the disease is called elephantiasis or filariasis. The pathogens are transmitted to a healthy person through the bite by the female mosquito vectors (Culex).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The immune response that primarily involves the production of antibodies in the blood is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Cell-mediated immunity</option>
            <option id="B">Humoral immune response</option>
            <option id="C">Innate immunity</option>
            <option id="D">Passive immunity</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Antibodies are found in the blood, so the response is also called as humoral immune response. This is one of the two types of our acquired immune response - antibody mediated.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which lymphoid organ is quite large at the time of birth but keeps reducing in size with age, becoming very small by puberty?</text>
            <option id="A">Spleen</option>
            <option id="B">Thymus</option>
            <option id="C">Bone marrow</option>
            <option id="D">Tonsils</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The thymus is quite large at the time of birth but keeps reducing in size with age and by the time puberty is attained it reduces to a very small size.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following acts as a physiological barrier to the entry of microorganisms in the human body?</text>
            <option id="A">Skin</option>
            <option id="B">Epithelium of urogenital tract</option>
            <option id="C">Tears from eyes</option>
            <option id="D">Monocytes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Acid in the stomach, saliva in the mouth, tears from eyes all prevent microbial growth and constitute physiological barriers. Skin and epithelium are physical barriers, while monocytes are cellular barriers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The use of vaccines and immunisation programmes have enabled us to completely eradicate which of the following deadly diseases?</text>
            <option id="A">Polio</option>
            <option id="B">Smallpox</option>
            <option id="C">Tetanus</option>
            <option id="D">Diphtheria</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The use of vaccines and immunisation programmes have enabled us to completely eradicate a deadly disease like smallpox.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an infectious disease?</text>
            <option id="A">Cancer</option>
            <option id="B">Allergy</option>
            <option id="C">Rheumatoid arthritis</option>
            <option id="D">Common cold</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Diseases which are easily transmitted from one person to another, are called infectious diseases. Common cold is a highly infectious viral disease.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following diseases is caused by a protozoan pathogen?</text>
            <option id="A">Typhoid</option>
            <option id="B">Pneumonia</option>
            <option id="C">Malaria</option>
            <option id="D">Ringworm</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Some of the human diseases are caused by protozoans too. You might have heard about malaria, a disease man has been fighting since many years. Plasmodium, a tiny protozoan is responsible for this disease.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The most fatal form of malaria, malignant malaria, is caused by which species of Plasmodium?</text>
            <option id="A">Plasmodium vivax</option>
            <option id="B">Plasmodium malariae</option>
            <option id="C">Plasmodium falciparum</option>
            <option id="D">Plasmodium ovale</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Of the different species of Plasmodium (P. vivax, P. malariae and P. falciparum), malignant malaria caused by Plasmodium falciparum is the most serious one and can even be fatal.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Entamoeba histolytica is a protozoan parasite in the large intestine of human which causes:</text>
            <option id="A">Amoebiasis</option>
            <option id="B">Ascariasis</option>
            <option id="C">Filariasis</option>
            <option id="D">Dengue</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Entamoeba histolytica is a protozoan parasite in the large intestine of human which causes amoebiasis (amoebic dysentery). Symptoms include constipation, abdominal pain and cramps, stools with excess mucous and blood clots.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following diseases is caused by a protozoan?</text>
            <option id="A">Typhoid</option>
            <option id="B">Pneumonia</option>
            <option id="C">Malaria</option>
            <option id="D">Common cold</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Some of the human diseases are caused by protozoans too. You might have heard about malaria, a disease man has been fighting since many years. Plasmodium, a tiny protozoan is responsible for this disease.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Entamoeba histolytica is a protozoan parasite in the large intestine of humans which causes:</text>
            <option id="A">Amoebiasis (amoebic dysentery)</option>
            <option id="B">Ascariasis</option>
            <option id="C">Filariasis</option>
            <option id="D">Ringworm</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Entamoeba histolytica is a protozoan parasite in the large intestine of human which causes amoebiasis (amoebic dysentery). Symptoms of this disease include constipation, abdominal pain and cramps, stools with excess mucous and blood clots.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Ascaris, the common round worm, is an intestinal parasite that causes ascariasis. Which of the following is NOT a symptom of this disease?</text>
            <option id="A">Internal bleeding</option>
            <option id="B">Muscular pain</option>
            <option id="C">Fever</option>
            <option id="D">Elephantiasis</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Ascaris, the common round worm and Wuchereria, the filarial worm, are some of the helminths which are known to be pathogenic to man. Ascaris, an intestinal parasite causes ascariasis. Symptoms of these disease include internal bleeding, muscular pain, fever, anemia and blockage of the intestinal passage. Elephantiasis is caused by Wuchereria.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cancer-causing viruses are known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Retroviruses</option>
            <option id="B">Oncogenic viruses</option>
            <option id="C">Bacteriophages</option>
            <option id="D">Adenoviruses</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Cancer causing viruses called oncogenic viruses have genes called viral oncogenes. Furthermore, several genes called cellular oncogenes (c-onc) or proto oncogenes have been identified in normal cells which, when activated under certain conditions, could lead to oncogenic transformation of the cells.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The use of drugs like opioids, cannabinoids, and coca alkaloids is common among drug abusers. Opioids bind to specific opioid receptors present in our:</text>
            <option id="A">Central nervous system and gastrointestinal tract</option>
            <option id="B">Respiratory system and cardiovascular system</option>
            <option id="C">Liver and kidneys</option>
            <option id="D">Muscular and skeletal systems</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Opioids are the drugs, which bind to specific opioid receptors present in our central nervous system and gastrointestinal tract. Heroin, commonly called smack is chemically diacetylmorphine which is a white, odourless, bitter crystalline compound.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cannabinoids are known for their effects on which system of the body?</text>
            <option id="A">Respiratory system</option>
            <option id="B">Cardiovascular system</option>
            <option id="C">Digestive system</option>
            <option id="D">Excretory system</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Cannabinoids are a group of chemicals, which interact with cannabinoid receptors present principally in the brain. They are known for their effects on cardiovascular system of the body.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following barriers under innate immunity includes the acid in the stomach and saliva in the mouth?</text>
            <option id="A">Physical barriers</option>
            <option id="B">Physiological barriers</option>
            <option id="C">Cellular barriers</option>
            <option id="D">Cytokine barriers</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Physiological barriers: Acid in the stomach, saliva in the mouth, tears from eyes–all prevent microbial growth. Physical barriers include the skin and mucus coatings.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Interferons are proteins secreted by virus-infected cells to protect non-infected cells from further viral infection. They are an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Physical barriers</option>
            <option id="B">Physiological barriers</option>
            <option id="C">Cellular barriers</option>
            <option id="D">Cytokine barriers</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Cytokine barriers: Virus-infected cells secrete proteins called interferons which protect non-infected cells from further viral infection.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Each antibody molecule has four peptide chains: two small called light chains and two longer called heavy chains. How is this represented?</text>
            <option id="A">H2L2</option>
            <option id="B">H4L4</option>
            <option id="C">HL2</option>
            <option id="D">H2L</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Each antibody molecule has four peptide chains, two small called light chains and two longer called heavy chains. Hence, an antibody is represented as H2L2. Different types of antibodies are produced in our body. IgA, IgM, IgE, IgG are some of them.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which scientist disproved the 'good humor' hypothesis of health using thermometers to demonstrate normal body temperature in persons with blackbile?</text>
            <option id="A">Hippocrates</option>
            <option id="B">William Harvey</option>
            <option id="C">Louis Pasteur</option>
            <option id="D">Robert Koch</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The discovery of blood circulation by William Harvey using experimental method and the demonstration of normal body temperature in persons with blackbile using thermometer disproved the 'good humor' hypothesis of health.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Health is affected by genetic disorders, infections, and:</text>
            <option id="A">Climate only</option>
            <option id="B">Life style</option>
            <option id="C">Only hereditary factors</option>
            <option id="D">Age</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Health, for a long time, was considered as a state of body and mind where there was a balance of certain 'humors'. In later years, biology stated that mind influences, through neural system and endocrine system, our immune system and that our immune system maintains our health. Health is affected by - (i) genetic disorders, (ii) infections, and (iii) life style.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When the functioning of one or more organs or systems of the body is adversely affected, characterised by various signs and symptoms, we say that we have a:</text>
            <option id="A">Disorder</option>
            <option id="B">Disease</option>
            <option id="C">Syndrome</option>
            <option id="D">Infection</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When the functioning of one or more organs or systems of the body is adversely affected, characterised by various signs and symptoms, we say that we are not healthy, i.e., we have a disease.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is the causative agent of Pneumonia in humans?</text>
            <option id="A">Streptococcus pneumoniae and Haemophilus influenzae</option>
            <option id="B">Salmonella typhi</option>
            <option id="C">Plasmodium vivax</option>
            <option id="D">Rhinoviruses</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Bacteria like Streptococcus pneumoniae and Haemophilus influenzae are responsible for the disease pneumonia in humans.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Pneumonia affects which part of the respiratory system?</text>
            <option id="A">The upper respiratory tract</option>
            <option id="B">The trachea</option>
            <option id="C">The alveoli (air-filled sacs) of the lungs</option>
            <option id="D">The diaphragm</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Bacteria like Streptococcus pneumoniae and Haemophilus influenzae are responsible for the disease pneumonia in humans which infects the alveoli (air filled sacs) of the lungs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What happens to the alveoli during a severe pneumonia infection?</text>
            <option id="A">They completely collapse</option>
            <option id="B">They expand and burst</option>
            <option id="C">They get filled with fluid leading to severe problems in respiration</option>
            <option id="D">They become calcified</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>As a result of the infection, the alveoli get filled with fluid leading to severe problems in respiration.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Plasmodium parasite requires two hosts to complete its life cycle. Who are these two hosts?</text>
            <option id="A">Human and tsetse fly</option>
            <option id="B">Human and mosquitoes</option>
            <option id="C">Human and sand fly</option>
            <option id="D">Human and tick</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The malarial parasite requires two hosts – human and mosquitoes – to complete its life cycle.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which insect acts as the vector for transmitting Plasmodium to humans?</text>
            <option id="A">Male Anopheles mosquito</option>
            <option id="B">Female Anopheles mosquito</option>
            <option id="C">Culex mosquito</option>
            <option id="D">Aedes mosquito</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The female Anopheles mosquito is the vector (transmitting agent) too.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Once Plasmodium sporozoites enter the human body, where do they initially multiply?</text>
            <option id="A">In the red blood cells</option>
            <option id="B">In the brain cells</option>
            <option id="C">Within the liver cells</option>
            <option id="D">In the white blood cells</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The parasites initially multiply within the liver cells and then attack the red blood cells (RBCs) resulting in their rupture.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following diseases is caused by roundworms (Ascaris) in humans?</text>
            <option id="A">Elephantiasis</option>
            <option id="B">Amoebiasis</option>
            <option id="C">Ascariasis</option>
            <option id="D">Ringworm</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Ascaris, the common round worm and Wuchereria, the filarial worm, are some of the helminths which are known to be pathogenic to man. Ascaris, an intestinal parasite causes ascariasis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What are the typical symptoms of Ascariasis?</text>
            <option id="A">High fever, weakness, stomach pain, constipation</option>
            <option id="B">Internal bleeding, muscular pain, fever, anemia, and blockage of the intestinal passage</option>
            <option id="C">Dry, scaly lesions on various parts of the body</option>
            <option id="D">Chronic inflammation of the lymphatic vessels</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Symptoms of these disease [ascariasis] include internal bleeding, muscular pain, fever, anemia and blockage of the intestinal passage.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How does a healthy person usually get infected with Ascaris?</text>
            <option id="A">Through the bite of a mosquito</option>
            <option id="B">Through contaminated water, vegetables, and fruits containing eggs of the parasite</option>
            <option id="C">Through sexual contact</option>
            <option id="D">Through inhaling droplet nuclei</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The eggs of the parasite are excreted along with the faeces of infected persons which contaminate soil, water, plants, etc. A healthy person acquires this infection through contaminated water, vegetables, fruits, etc.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which vector is responsible for transmitting the deadly disease Malaria?</text>
            <option id="A">Culex mosquito</option>
            <option id="B">Aedes mosquito</option>
            <option id="C">Anopheles mosquito</option>
            <option id="D">Housefly</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Female Anopheles mosquito is the vector for Malaria.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which vector is responsible for transmitting diseases like Dengue and Chikungunya?</text>
            <option id="A">Anopheles mosquito</option>
            <option id="B">Culex mosquito</option>
            <option id="C">Aedes mosquito</option>
            <option id="D">Tsetse fly</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Such precautions [against mosquitoes] have become all the more important especially in the light of recent widespread incidences of the vector-borne (Aedes mosquitoes) diseases like dengue and chikungunya in many parts of India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The ability of the host to fight the disease-causing organisms, conferred by the immune system, is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Allergy</option>
            <option id="B">Autoimmunity</option>
            <option id="C">Immunity</option>
            <option id="D">Vaccination</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Everyday we are exposed to large number of infectious agents. However, only a few of these exposures result in disease. Why? This is due to the fact that the body is able to defend itself from most of these foreign agents. This overall ability of the host to fight the disease-causing organisms, conferred by the immune system is called immunity.</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following acts as a physiological barrier to the entry of microorganisms in the human body?</text>
            <option id="A">Skin</option>
            <option id="B">Epithelium of the urogenital tract</option>
            <option id="C">Tears from eyes</option>
            <option id="D">Monocytes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Tears from eyes, saliva in the mouth, and acid in the stomach are physiological barriers. Skin and epithelium are physical barriers, while monocytes are cellular barriers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>HIV that causes AIDS first starts destroying:</text>
            <option id="A">Helper T-lymphocytes</option>
            <option id="B">B-lymphocytes</option>
            <option id="C">Leucocytes</option>
            <option id="D">Thrombocytes</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>After entering the body, HIV enters macrophages and then Helper T-lymphocytes (TH), where it replicates and produces progeny viruses, progressively decreasing the number of helper T cells.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the life cycle of Plasmodium, sexual stages (gametocytes) develop in:</text>
            <option id="A">Human liver cells</option>
            <option id="B">Human red blood cells (RBCs)</option>
            <option id="C">Gut of mosquito</option>
            <option id="D">Salivary glands of mosquito</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The sexual stages (gametocytes) of Plasmodium develop in the human red blood cells. These are then taken up by the female Anopheles mosquito during a blood meal.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an autoimmune disease?</text>
            <option id="A">Asthma</option>
            <option id="B">Rheumatoid arthritis</option>
            <option id="C">Cirrhosis</option>
            <option id="D">AIDS</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Rheumatoid arthritis is an autoimmune disease where the body's immune system attacks self-cells, resulting in damage to the joints.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The excessive response of the immune system to certain antigens present in the environment is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Autoimmunity</option>
            <option id="B">Immunodeficiency</option>
            <option id="C">Allergy</option>
            <option id="D">Inflammation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The exaggerated response of the immune system to certain antigens present in the environment is called allergy. The substances to which such an immune response is produced are called allergens.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Morphine, a very effective sedative and painkiller, is extracted from the latex of which plant?</text>
            <option id="A">Cannabis sativa</option>
            <option id="B">Erythroxylum coca</option>
            <option id="C">Papaver somniferum</option>
            <option id="D">Atropa belladonna</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Opioids are the drugs, which bind to specific opioid receptors present in our central nervous system and gastrointestinal tract. Heroin, commonly called smack is chemically diacetylmorphine which is a white, odourless, bitter crystalline compound. This is obtained by acetylation of morphine, which is extracted from the latex of poppy plant Papaver somniferum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which test is widely used for the detection of AIDS?</text>
            <option id="A">Widal test</option>
            <option id="B">ELISA test</option>
            <option id="C">Biopsy</option>
            <option id="D">MRI</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A widely used diagnostic test for AIDS is enzyme linked immuno-sorbent assay (ELISA).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The property of normal cells to inhibit uncontrolled growth and division upon touching other cells is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Metastasis</option>
            <option id="B">Contact inhibition</option>
            <option id="C">Apoptosis</option>
            <option id="D">Transformation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Normal cells show a property called contact inhibition by virtue of which contact with other cells inhibits their uncontrolled growth. Cancer cells appears to have lost this property.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The pathogen Microsporum is responsible for which of the following diseases in humans?</text>
            <option id="A">Ringworm</option>
            <option id="B">Amoebiasis</option>
            <option id="C">Ascariasis</option>
            <option id="D">Filariasis</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Many fungi belonging to the genera Microsporum, Trichophyton and Epidermophyton are responsible for ringworms which is one of the most common infectious diseases in man.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Colostrum, the yellowish fluid secreted by the mother during the initial days of lactation, provides which type of immunity to the infant?</text>
            <option id="A">Active immunity</option>
            <option id="B">Passive immunity</option>
            <option id="C">Autoimmunity</option>
            <option id="D">Cell-mediated immunity</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When ready-made antibodies are directly given to protect the body against foreign agents, it is called passive immunity. Colostrum contains abundant antibodies (IgA) to protect the infant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following cells acts as an 'HIV factory' in the human body?</text>
            <option id="A">Macrophage</option>
            <option id="B">B-lymphocyte</option>
            <option id="C">T-helper cell</option>
            <option id="D">Erythrocyte</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>After getting into the body of the person, the HIV enters into macrophages where RNA genome of the virus replicates to form viral DNA. The macrophages continue to produce virus and in this way acts like an HIV factory.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cancer-causing genes are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Operons</option>
            <option id="B">Oncogenes</option>
            <option id="C">Mutagens</option>
            <option id="D">Carcinogens</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Several genes called cellular oncogenes (c-onc) or proto-oncogenes have been identified in normal cells which, when activated under certain conditions, could lead to oncogenic transformation of the cells.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Wuchereria (W. bancrofti and W. malayi) cause a slowly developing chronic inflammation of the organs in which they live for many years, usually the lymphatic vessels of the lower limbs. What is the common name for this disease?</text>
            <option id="A">Ascariasis</option>
            <option id="B">Elephantiasis</option>
            <option id="C">Amoebiasis</option>
            <option id="D">Ringworm</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Wuchereria, the filarial worms cause a slowly developing chronic inflammation of the organs in which they live for many years, usually the lymphatic vessels of the lower limbs and the disease is called elephantiasis or filariasis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which vector transmits the filarial worms to healthy individuals?</text>
            <option id="A">Anopheles mosquito</option>
            <option id="B">Culex mosquito</option>
            <option id="C">Aedes mosquito</option>
            <option id="D">Housefly</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The pathogens (Wuchereria) are transmitted to a healthy person through the bite by the female mosquito vectors (such as Culex mosquito).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The overall ability of the host to fight the disease-causing organisms, conferred by the immune system, is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Pathogenicity</option>
            <option id="B">Immunity</option>
            <option id="C">Allergy</option>
            <option id="D">Autoimmunity</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Everyday we are exposed to large number of infectious agents. However, only a few of these exposures result in disease. The overall ability of the host to fight the disease-causing organisms, conferred by the immune system is called immunity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which type of immunity is non-specific and is present at the time of birth?</text>
            <option id="A">Active immunity</option>
            <option id="B">Passive immunity</option>
            <option id="C">Innate immunity</option>
            <option id="D">Acquired immunity</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Innate immunity is non-specific type of defense, that is present at the time of birth. This is accomplished by providing different types of barriers to the entry of the foreign agents into our body.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The yellowish fluid colostrum secreted by mother during the initial days of lactation has abundant antibodies to protect the infant. Which antibody is predominant in colostrum?</text>
            <option id="A">IgA</option>
            <option id="B">IgM</option>
            <option id="C">IgE</option>
            <option id="D">IgG</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The yellowish fluid colostrum secreted by mother during the initial days of lactation has abundant antibodies (IgA) to protect the infant. This is an example of passive immunity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When a host is exposed to antigens, which may be in the form of living or dead microbes or other proteins, antibodies are produced in the host body. This type of immunity is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Passive immunity</option>
            <option id="B">Active immunity</option>
            <option id="C">Innate immunity</option>
            <option id="D">Autoimmunity</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When a host is exposed to antigens, which may be in the form of living or dead microbes or other proteins, antibodies are produced in the host body. This type of immunity is called active immunity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The exaggerated response of the immune system to certain antigens present in the environment is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Autoimmunity</option>
            <option id="B">Allergy</option>
            <option id="C">Immunodeficiency</option>
            <option id="D">Vaccination</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The exaggerated response of the immune system to certain antigens present in the environment is called allergy. The substances to which such an immune response is produced are called allergens.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In some cases, the body's immune system mistakenly attacks self-cells, resulting in damage to the body. This condition is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Allergy</option>
            <option id="B">Passive immunity</option>
            <option id="C">Auto-immune disease</option>
            <option id="D">Acquired immunodeficiency</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Sometimes, due to genetic and other unknown reasons, the body attacks self-cells. This results in damage to the body and is called auto-immune disease. Rheumatoid arthritis which affects many people in our society is an auto-immune disease.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cocaine, obtained from the coca plant Erythroxylum coca, interferes with the transport of which neurotransmitter?</text>
            <option id="A">Acetylcholine</option>
            <option id="B">Dopamine</option>
            <option id="C">Serotonin</option>
            <option id="D">GABA</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Coca alkaloid or cocaine is obtained from coca plant Erythroxylum coca, native to South America. It interferes with the transport of the neuro-transmitter dopamine. Cocaine, commonly called coke or crack is usually snorted.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which plant possesses hallucinogenic properties and is often associated with drug abuse?</text>
            <option id="A">Atropa belladona</option>
            <option id="B">Datura</option>
            <option id="C">Papaver somniferum</option>
            <option id="D">Both A and B</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>It has a potent stimulating action on central nervous system, producing a sense of euphoria and increased energy. Excessive dosage of cocaine causes hallucinations. Other well-known plants with hallucinogenic properties are Atropa belladona and Datura.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Tobacco has been used by human beings for more than 400 years. It contains a large number of chemical substances including nicotine, which is an alkaloid. What is the physiological effect of nicotine?</text>
            <option id="A">It depresses the central nervous system</option>
            <option id="B">It stimulates the adrenal gland to release adrenaline and nor-adrenaline</option>
            <option id="C">It decreases blood pressure and heart rate</option>
            <option id="D">It acts as a potent hallucinogen</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Tobacco contains a large number of chemical substances including nicotine, an alkaloid. Nicotine stimulates adrenal gland to release adrenaline and nor-adrenaline into blood circulation, both of which raise blood pressure and increase heart rate.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cirrhosis of the liver is typically associated with the chronic use of:</text>
            <option id="A">Tobacco</option>
            <option id="B">Cocaine</option>
            <option id="C">Alcohol</option>
            <option id="D">Cannabis</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The chronic use of drugs and alcohol damages nervous system and liver (cirrhosis). The use of drugs and alcohol during pregnancy is also known to adversely affect the foetus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The type of immune response primarily mediated by T-lymphocytes, which is responsible for the graft rejection in organ transplantation, is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Humoral immune response</option>
            <option id="B">Cell-mediated immune response (CMI)</option>
            <option id="C">Innate immune response</option>
            <option id="D">Allergic response</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The T-lymphocytes mediate CMI (Cell-mediated immunity). Very often, when some human organs like heart, eye, liver, kidney fail to function satisfactorily, transplantation is the only remedy. Tissue matching, blood group matching are essential before undertaking any graft/transplant and even after this the patient has to take immuno-suppresants all his/her life. The body is able to differentiate 'self' and 'nonself' and the cell-mediated immune response is responsible for the graft rejection.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When ready-made antibodies are directly given to protect the body against foreign agents, it is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Active immunity</option>
            <option id="B">Passive immunity</option>
            <option id="C">Innate immunity</option>
            <option id="D">Cell-mediated immunity</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When ready-made antibodies are directly given to protect the body against foreign agents, it is called passive immunity. For example, the yellowish fluid colostrum secreted by mother during the initial days of lactation has abundant antibodies (IgA).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In tetanus, patients are injected with preformed antibodies or antitoxins. This is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Active immunization</option>
            <option id="B">Passive immunization</option>
            <option id="C">Vaccination</option>
            <option id="D">Gene therapy</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>If a person is infected with some deadly microbes to which quick immune response is required as in tetanus, we need to directly inject the preformed antibodies, or antitoxin. This type of immunisation is called passive immunisation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which type of antibodies are produced in large quantities during allergic reactions?</text>
            <option id="A">IgG</option>
            <option id="B">IgM</option>
            <option id="C">IgE</option>
            <option id="D">IgA</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The exaggerated response of the immune system to certain antigens present in the environment is called allergy. The antibodies produced to these are of IgE type.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Diseases which are easily transmitted from one person to another are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Non-infectious diseases</option>
            <option id="B">Infectious diseases</option>
            <option id="C">Genetic disorders</option>
            <option id="D">Deficiency diseases</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Diseases can be broadly grouped into infectious and non-infectious. Diseases which are easily transmitted from one person to another, are called infectious diseases.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of an infectious disease that is fatal?</text>
            <option id="A">Cancer</option>
            <option id="B">AIDS</option>
            <option id="C">Diabetes</option>
            <option id="D">Hypertension</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Infectious diseases are very common and every one of us suffers from these at sometime or other. Some of the infectious diseases like AIDS are fatal.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Among non-infectious diseases, which is the major cause of death?</text>
            <option id="A">Cancer</option>
            <option id="B">Diabetes</option>
            <option id="C">Obesity</option>
            <option id="D">Arthritis</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Among non-infectious diseases, cancer is the major cause of death. Drug and alcohol abuse also affect our health adversely.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A wide range of organisms belonging to bacteria, viruses, fungi, protozoans, helminths, etc., could cause diseases in man. Such disease-causing organisms are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Vectors</option>
            <option id="B">Pathogens</option>
            <option id="C">Carriers</option>
            <option id="D">Parasites</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A wide range of organisms belonging to bacteria, viruses, fungi, protozoans, helminths, etc., could cause diseases in man. Such disease causing organisms are called pathogens.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following symptoms is characteristic of a severe case of pneumonia?</text>
            <option id="A">Persistent dry cough without fever</option>
            <option id="B">Lips and finger nails turning gray to bluish in color</option>
            <option id="C">Loss of taste and smell</option>
            <option id="D">Severe joint pain</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The symptoms of pneumonia include fever, chills, cough and headache. In severe cases, the lips and finger nails may turn gray to bluish in colour.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How is pneumonia primarily transmitted from an infected person to a healthy person?</text>
            <option id="A">Through mosquito bites</option>
            <option id="B">By inhaling droplets/aerosols released by an infected person</option>
            <option id="C">Through contaminated water</option>
            <option id="D">Through a blood transfusion</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A healthy person acquires the infection by inhaling the droplets/aerosols released by an infected person or even by sharing glasses and utensils with an infected person.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following group of pathogens causes one of the most infectious human ailments, the common cold?</text>
            <option id="A">Adenoviruses</option>
            <option id="B">Rhinoviruses</option>
            <option id="C">Coronaviruses</option>
            <option id="D">Retroviruses</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Many viruses also cause diseases in human beings. Rhinoviruses represent one such group of viruses which cause one of the most infectious human ailments – the common cold.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is a key difference between the infection caused by Rhinoviruses (common cold) and Pneumonia?</text>
            <option id="A">Common cold infects the lungs, while pneumonia infects the nose.</option>
            <option id="B">Common cold infects the nose and respiratory passage but not the lungs, whereas pneumonia infects the alveoli of the lungs.</option>
            <option id="C">Common cold is caused by bacteria, while pneumonia is caused by viruses.</option>
            <option id="D">There is no difference; they infect the exact same tissues.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>They infect the nose and respiratory passage but not the lungs. The common cold is characterised by nasal congestion and discharge, sore throat, hoarseness, cough, headache, tiredness, etc., which usually last for 3-7 days.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The rupture of RBCs during a malaria infection releases a toxic substance responsible for the chill and high fever recurring every 3 to 4 days. What is this substance called?</text>
            <option id="A">Histamine</option>
            <option id="B">Hemozoin</option>
            <option id="C">Interferon</option>
            <option id="D">Pyrogen</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The rupture of RBCs is associated with release of a toxic substance, hemozoin, which is responsible for the chill and high fever recurring every 3 to 4 days.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Where do the sexual stages (gametocytes) of the Plasmodium parasite develop?</text>
            <option id="A">In the human liver</option>
            <option id="B">In the red blood cells (RBCs) of the human</option>
            <option id="C">In the mosquito's gut</option>
            <option id="D">In the mosquito's salivary glands</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Sexual stages (gametocytes) develop in red blood cells.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When a female Anopheles mosquito bites an infected person, what forms of the Plasmodium parasite does it take up with the blood meal?</text>
            <option id="A">Sporozoites</option>
            <option id="B">Merozoites</option>
            <option id="C">Gametocytes</option>
            <option id="D">Zygotes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Female mosquito takes up gametocytes with blood meal. Fertilisation and development take place in the mosquito's gut.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Where does the fertilization and development of Plasmodium gametes take place?</text>
            <option id="A">In the human red blood cells</option>
            <option id="B">In the human liver cells</option>
            <option id="C">In the mosquito's gut (intestine)</option>
            <option id="D">In the mosquito's salivary glands</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Fertilisation and development take place in the mosquito's gut.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which worms cause slowly developing chronic inflammation of the organs in which they live for many years, usually the lymphatic vessels of the lower limbs?</text>
            <option id="A">Ascaris lumbricoides</option>
            <option id="B">Wuchereria bancrofti and Wuchereria malayi</option>
            <option id="C">Entamoeba histolytica</option>
            <option id="D">Microsporum and Trichophyton</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Wuchereria (W. bancrofti and W. malayi), the filarial worms cause a slowly developing chronic inflammation of the organs in which they live for many years, usually the lymphatic vessels of the lower limbs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the common name for the disease caused by Wuchereria, which often results in gross deformities of the lower limbs and genital organs?</text>
            <option id="A">Ascariasis</option>
            <option id="B">Elephantiasis or Filariasis</option>
            <option id="C">Ringworm</option>
            <option id="D">Amoebiasis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Wuchereria... cause a slowly developing chronic inflammation of the organs in which they live for many years, usually the lymphatic vessels of the lower limbs and the disease is called elephantiasis or filariasis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How are filarial worms transmitted to a healthy person?</text>
            <option id="A">By drinking contaminated water</option>
            <option id="B">Through the bite of female mosquito vectors</option>
            <option id="C">By eating undercooked meat</option>
            <option id="D">Through direct contact with infected skin</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The pathogens [filarial worms] are transmitted to a healthy person through the bite by the female mosquito vectors.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Ringworm, a common infectious disease in humans, is primarily caused by which type of organisms?</text>
            <option id="A">Bacteria</option>
            <option id="B">Viruses</option>
            <option id="C">Fungi</option>
            <option id="D">Helminths</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Many fungi belonging to the genera Microsporum, Trichophyton and Epidermophyton are responsible for ringworms which is one of the most common infectious diseases in man.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Immunity is broadly categorized into two types. What are they?</text>
            <option id="A">Active and Passive immunity</option>
            <option id="B">Innate and Acquired immunity</option>
            <option id="C">Cellular and Humoral immunity</option>
            <option id="D">Primary and Secondary immunity</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Immunity is of two types: (i) Innate immunity and (ii) Acquired immunity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which type of immunity is non-specific and is present at the time of birth?</text>
            <option id="A">Acquired immunity</option>
            <option id="B">Active immunity</option>
            <option id="C">Innate immunity</option>
            <option id="D">Passive immunity</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Innate immunity is non-specific type of defence, that is present at the time of birth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Innate immunity is accomplished by providing different types of barriers. How many types of barriers does innate immunity consist of?</text>
            <option id="A">Two</option>
            <option id="B">Three</option>
            <option id="C">Four</option>
            <option id="D">Five</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>This [innate immunity] is accomplished by providing different types of barriers to the entry of the foreign agents into our body. Innate immunity consist of four types of barriers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Skin is the main barrier that prevents the entry of micro-organisms. Which category of innate immunity barrier does skin belong to?</text>
            <option id="A">Physiological barrier</option>
            <option id="B">Cellular barrier</option>
            <option id="C">Physical barrier</option>
            <option id="D">Cytokine barrier</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Physical barriers: Skin on our body is the main barrier which prevents entry of the micro-organisms.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>Read the following statements about cancer cells:\nA. They show contact inhibition.\nB. They compete with normal cells for vital nutrients.\nC. They possess the property of metastasis.\nD. They undergo differentiation to form specialized tissues.\nHow many of the above statements are correct?</text>
            <option id="A">One</option>
            <option id="B">Two</option>
            <option id="C">Three</option>
            <option id="D">Four</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Statements B and C are correct. Cancer cells lose the property of contact inhibition (Statement A is wrong) and they do not undergo normal differentiation (Statement D is wrong).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cocaine is obtained from the plant Erythroxylum coca, native to South America. It exerts its action on the central nervous system by interfering with the transport of the neurotransmitter:</text>
            <option id="A">Acetylcholine</option>
            <option id="B">Serotonin</option>
            <option id="C">Dopamine</option>
            <option id="D">GABA</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Cocaine, commonly called coke or crack, has a potent stimulating action on the central nervous system by interfering with the transport of the neurotransmitter dopamine.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Match the diseases with their causative agents:\n1. Elephantiasis   a. Trichophyton\n2. Ringworm        b. Wuchereria\n3. Amoebiasis      c. Haemophilus influenzae\n4. Pneumonia       d. Entamoeba histolytica</text>
            <option id="A">1-b, 2-a, 3-d, 4-c</option>
            <option id="B">1-a, 2-b, 3-d, 4-c</option>
            <option id="C">1-b, 2-a, 3-c, 4-d</option>
            <option id="D">1-c, 2-a, 3-d, 4-b</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Elephantiasis is caused by filarial worms (Wuchereria), Ringworm by fungi (Trichophyton), Amoebiasis by protozoan (Entamoeba histolytica), and Pneumonia by bacteria (Haemophilus influenzae/Streptococcus pneumoniae).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following classes of antibodies is primarily responsible for allergic reactions?</text>
            <option id="A">IgG</option>
            <option id="B">IgM</option>
            <option id="C">IgE</option>
            <option id="D">IgA</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The exaggerated response of the immune system to certain antigens present in the environment is called allergy. The antibodies produced to these are of IgE type.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Identify the INCORRECT statement regarding innate immunity.</text>
            <option id="A">It is non-specific type of defense.</option>
            <option id="B">It is present at the time of birth.</option>
            <option id="C">It relies on the production of memory cells.</option>
            <option id="D">It consists of four types of barriers (physical, physiological, cellular, cytokine).</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Innate immunity is non-specific defense that is present at the time of birth. It does not rely on memory cells; memory is a characteristic feature of acquired (adaptive) immunity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The infective stage of Plasmodium that enters the human body through the bite of an infected female Anopheles mosquito is:</text>
            <option id="A">Trophozoite</option>
            <option id="B">Merozoite</option>
            <option id="C">Sporozoite</option>
            <option id="D">Gametocyte</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Plasmodium enters the human body as sporozoites (infectious form) through the bite of infected female Anopheles mosquito. The parasites initially multiply within the liver cells and then attack the red blood cells (RBCs).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a hallucinogenic plant?</text>
            <option id="A">Erythroxylum coca</option>
            <option id="B">Atropa belladonna</option>
            <option id="C">Datura</option>
            <option id="D">All of the above</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Cocaine (from Erythroxylum coca) has a potent stimulating action on CNS, producing a sense of euphoria and increased energy. Excessive dosage of cocaine causes hallucinations. Other well-known plants with hallucinogenic properties are Atropa belladonna and Datura.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When a person is infected with tetanus, the immediate treatment involves injecting:</text>
            <option id="A">Attenuated tetanus bacteria</option>
            <option id="B">Preformed antibodies or antitoxin</option>
            <option id="C">Broad-spectrum antibiotics</option>
            <option id="D">Tetanus toxoid vaccine</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>If a person is infected with some deadly microbes to which quick immune response is required as in tetanus, we need to directly inject the preformed antibodies, or antitoxin (a preparation containing antibodies to the toxin). This is passive immunisation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Malignant tumors show the property of metastasis, which means:</text>
            <option id="A">They remain confined to their original location.</option>
            <option id="B">They do not cause damage to surrounding tissues.</option>
            <option id="C">Cells sloughed from such tumors reach distant sites through blood and start a new tumor.</option>
            <option id="D">They undergo programmed cell death.</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Cells sloughed from malignant tumors reach distant sites through blood, and wherever they get lodged in the body, they start a new tumor there. This property called metastasis is the most feared property of malignant tumors.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Polymorpho-nuclear leukocytes (PMNL-neutrophils) and monocytes in the blood act as which type of barrier in innate immunity?</text>
            <option id="A">Physical barriers</option>
            <option id="B">Physiological barriers</option>
            <option id="C">Cellular barriers</option>
            <option id="D">Cytokine barriers</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Certain types of leukocytes (WBC) of our body like polymorpho-nuclear leukocytes (PMNL-neutrophils) and monocytes and natural killer (type of lymphocytes) in the blood as well as macrophages in tissues can phagocytose and destroy microbes. These are cellular barriers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Interferons are proteins secreted by virus-infected cells. They belong to which category of innate immunity barriers?</text>
            <option id="A">Physical barriers</option>
            <option id="B">Physiological barriers</option>
            <option id="C">Cellular barriers</option>
            <option id="D">Cytokine barriers</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Virus-infected cells secrete proteins called interferons which protect non-infected cells from further viral infection. These constitute cytokine barriers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Acquired immunity is pathogen specific and is characterized by memory. The primary immune response is elicited when our body encounters a pathogen for the first time. The subsequent encounter with the same pathogen elicits a highly intensified response called:</text>
            <option id="A">Anamnestic response</option>
            <option id="B">Allergic response</option>
            <option id="C">Autoimmune response</option>
            <option id="D">Inflammatory response</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Subsequent encounter with the same pathogen elicits a highly intensified secondary or anamnestic response. This is ascribed to the fact that our body appears to have memory of the first encounter.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following lymphoid organs is quite large at the time of birth but keeps reducing in size with age, and by the time puberty is attained, it reduces to a very small size?</text>
            <option id="A">Spleen</option>
            <option id="B">Thymus</option>
            <option id="C">Tonsils</option>
            <option id="D">Bone marrow</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The thymus is quite large at the time of birth but keeps reducing in size with age and by the time puberty is attained it reduces to a very small size. Both bone-marrow and thymus provide micro-environments for the development and maturation of T-lymphocytes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>HIV (Human Immunodeficiency Virus) belongs to a group of viruses called:</text>
            <option id="A">Adenoviruses</option>
            <option id="B">Retroviruses</option>
            <option id="C">Rhinoviruses</option>
            <option id="D">Papillomaviruses</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>AIDS is caused by the Human Immuno deficiency Virus (HIV), a member of a group of viruses called retrovirus, which have an envelope enclosing the RNA genome.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following techniques is widely used for the detection of cancers of the internal organs?</text>
            <option id="A">Radiography (use of X-rays)</option>
            <option id="B">CT (Computed Tomography)</option>
            <option id="C">MRI (Magnetic Resonance Imaging)</option>
            <option id="D">All of the above</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Techniques like radiography (use of X-rays), CT (computed tomography) and MRI (magnetic resonance imaging) are very useful to detect cancers of the internal organs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Widal test is used for the diagnosis of:</text>
            <option id="A">Malaria</option>
            <option id="B">Pneumonia</option>
            <option id="C">Typhoid</option>
            <option id="D">Cholera</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Typhoid fever could be confirmed by Widal test. A classic case in medicine, that of Mary Mallon nicknamed Typhoid Mary, is worth mentioning here. She was a cook by profession and was a typhoid carrier who continued to spread typhoid for several years through the food she prepared.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Plasmodium, the malarial parasite, enters the human body as:</text>
            <option id="A">Gametocytes</option>
            <option id="B">Merozoites</option>
            <option id="C">Sporozoites</option>
            <option id="D">Trophozoites</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Plasmodium enters the human body as sporozoites (infectious form) through the bite of infected female Anopheles mosquito. The parasites initially multiply within the liver cells and then attack the red blood cells (RBCs) resulting in their rupture.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following cells acts as an HIV factory in the human body?</text>
            <option id="A">B-lymphocytes</option>
            <option id="B">Erythrocytes</option>
            <option id="C">Macrophages</option>
            <option id="D">Platelets</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>After getting into the body of the person, the virus enters into macrophages where RNA genome of the virus replicates to form viral DNA with the help of the enzyme reverse transcriptase. The macrophages continue to produce virus and in this way acts like a HIV factory.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Allergy is due to the release of chemicals like histamine and serotonin from which cells?</text>
            <option id="A">Macrophages</option>
            <option id="B">Mast cells</option>
            <option id="C">T-lymphocytes</option>
            <option id="D">Erythrocytes</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Allergy is due to the release of chemicals like histamine and serotonin from the mast cells. For determining the cause of allergy, the patient is exposed to or injected with very small doses of possible allergens.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The primary lymphoid organs where immature lymphocytes differentiate into antigen-sensitive lymphocytes are:</text>
            <option id="A">Spleen and Lymph nodes</option>
            <option id="B">Bone marrow and Thymus</option>
            <option id="C">Tonsils and Peyer's patches</option>
            <option id="D">Appendix and MALT</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The primary lymphoid organs are bone marrow and thymus where immature lymphocytes differentiate into antigen-sensitive lymphocytes. After maturation the lymphocytes migrate to secondary lymphoid organs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which lymphoid tissue is located within the lining of the major tracts (respiratory, digestive, and urogenital) and constitutes about 50% of the lymphoid tissue in the human body?</text>
            <option id="A">Spleen</option>
            <option id="B">Thymus</option>
            <option id="C">MALT (Mucosa-Associated Lymphoid Tissue)</option>
            <option id="D">Lymph nodes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>There is lymphoid tissue also located within the lining of the major tracts (respiratory, digestive and urogenital tracts) called mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue (MALT). It constitutes about 50 per cent of the lymphoid tissue in human body.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Salmonella typhi is a pathogenic bacterium which causes:</text>
            <option id="A">Pneumonia</option>
            <option id="B">Typhoid</option>
            <option id="C">Cholera</option>
            <option id="D">Tetanus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Salmonella typhi is a pathogenic bacterium which causes typhoid fever in human beings.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How do Salmonella typhi bacteria generally enter the small intestine?</text>
            <option id="A">Through mosquito bites</option>
            <option id="B">Through contaminated food and water</option>
            <option id="C">Through inhalation of droplets</option>
            <option id="D">Through direct contact with an infected person</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>These pathogens generally enter the small intestine through food and water contaminated with them and migrate to other organs through blood.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a classic case in medicine related to the spread of typhoid?</text>
            <option id="A">Typhoid Mary (Mary Mallon)</option>
            <option id="B">Florence Nightingale</option>
            <option id="C">Edward Jenner</option>
            <option id="D">Louis Pasteur</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>A classic case in medicine, that of Mary Mallon nicknamed Typhoid Mary, is worth mentioning here. She was a cook by profession and was a typhoid carrier who continued to spread typhoid for several years through the food she prepared.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following diseases is caused by a protozoan and has been a major health problem for mankind for many years?</text>
            <option id="A">Typhoid</option>
            <option id="B">Pneumonia</option>
            <option id="C">Malaria</option>
            <option id="D">Common cold</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Some of the human diseases are caused by protozoans too. You might have heard about malaria, a disease man has been fighting since many years.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which species of Plasmodium causes the most serious and potentially fatal form of malaria, known as malignant malaria?</text>
            <option id="A">Plasmodium vivax</option>
            <option id="B">Plasmodium malariae</option>
            <option id="C">Plasmodium falciparum</option>
            <option id="D">Plasmodium ovale</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Plasmodium, a tiny protozoan is responsible for this disease. Different species of Plasmodium (P. vivax, P. malariae and P. falciparum) are responsible for different types of malaria. Of these, malignant malaria caused by Plasmodium falciparum is the most serious one and can even be fatal.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How does the Plasmodium parasite enter the human body?</text>
            <option id="A">As gametocytes through the bite of a male Anopheles mosquito</option>
            <option id="B">As sporozoites through the bite of infected female Anopheles mosquito</option>
            <option id="C">Through contaminated water containing cysts</option>
            <option id="D">By inhaling aerosols containing the parasite</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Let us take a glance at the life cycle of Plasmodium. Plasmodium enters the human body as sporozoites (infectious form) through the bite of infected female Anopheles mosquito.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>After development in the mosquito's gut, mature infective stages (sporozoites) escape and are stored in which organ of the mosquito?</text>
            <option id="A">The gut wall</option>
            <option id="B">The salivary glands</option>
            <option id="C">The proboscis</option>
            <option id="D">The hemocoel</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Mature infective stages (sporozoites) escape from gut and migrate to the mosquito salivary glands.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which protozoan parasite causes amoebiasis (amoebic dysentery) in humans?</text>
            <option id="A">Plasmodium falciparum</option>
            <option id="B">Entamoeba histolytica</option>
            <option id="C">Trypanosoma gambiense</option>
            <option id="D">Leishmania donovani</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Entamoeba histolytica is a protozoan parasite in the large intestine of human which causes amoebiasis (amoebic dysentery).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following insects acts as a mechanical carrier for transmitting the parasite that causes amoebiasis?</text>
            <option id="A">Mosquitoes</option>
            <option id="B">Houseflies</option>
            <option id="C">Tsetse flies</option>
            <option id="D">Sand flies</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Houseflies act as mechanical carriers and serve to transmit the parasite from faeces of infected person to food and food products, thereby contaminating them.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which genera of fungi are responsible for causing ringworm in humans?</text>
            <option id="A">Microsporum, Trichophyton, and Epidermophyton</option>
            <option id="B">Aspergillus, Penicillium, and Rhizopus</option>
            <option id="C">Saccharomyces, Candida, and Cryptococcus</option>
            <option id="D">Plasmodium, Entamoeba, and Trypanosoma</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Many fungi belonging to the genera Microsporum, Trichophyton and Epidermophyton are responsible for ringworms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What are the main symptoms of ringworm infection?</text>
            <option id="A">High fever and chills</option>
            <option id="B">Appearance of dry, scaly lesions on skin, nails, and scalp, accompanied by intense itching</option>
            <option id="C">Internal bleeding and anemia</option>
            <option id="D">Swelling of the lymphatic vessels</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Appearance of dry, scaly lesions on various parts of the body such as skin, nails and scalp are the main symptoms of the disease. These lesions are accompanied by intense itching.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What factors help ringworm fungi thrive in areas like the skin folds (e.g., groin or between toes)?</text>
            <option id="A">Cold and dry conditions</option>
            <option id="B">Heat and moisture</option>
            <option id="C">Exposure to UV light</option>
            <option id="D">High oxygen levels</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Heat and moisture help these fungi to grow, which makes them thrive in skin folds such as those in the groin or between the toes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The mucus coating of the epithelium lining the respiratory, gastrointestinal, and urogenital tracts helps in trapping microbes. This is an example of which barrier?</text>
            <option id="A">Physiological barrier</option>
            <option id="B">Physical barrier</option>
            <option id="C">Cellular barrier</option>
            <option id="D">Cytokine barrier</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Physical barriers: Skin on our body is the main barrier... Mucus coating of the epithelium lining the respiratory, gastrointestinal and urogenital tracts also help in trapping microbes entering our body.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Acid in the stomach, saliva in the mouth, and tears from eyes all prevent microbial growth. These are examples of which innate immunity barrier?</text>
            <option id="A">Physical barriers</option>
            <option id="B">Physiological barriers</option>
            <option id="C">Cellular barriers</option>
            <option id="D">Cytokine barriers</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Physiological barriers: Acid in the stomach, saliva in the mouth, tears from eyes–all prevent microbial growth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Certain types of leukocytes (WBCs) like PMNL-neutrophils, monocytes, and natural killer (NK) cells can phagocytose and destroy microbes. These constitute which barrier?</text>
            <option id="A">Physical barriers</option>
            <option id="B">Physiological barriers</option>
            <option id="C">Cellular barriers</option>
            <option id="D">Cytokine barriers</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Cellular barriers: Certain types of leukocytes (WBC) of our body like polymorpho-nuclear leukocytes (PMNL-neutrophils) and monocytes and natural killer (type of lymphocytes) in the blood as well as macrophages in tissues can phagocytose and destroy microbes.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>