<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="325" name="Human Reproduction">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>In human males, the testes are situated outside the abdominal cavity within a pouch called the scrotum. The purpose of this is to:</text>
            <option id="A">Protect them from mechanical shock</option>
            <option id="B">Maintain a lower temperature for spermatogenesis</option>
            <option id="C">Provide more space for sperm storage</option>
            <option id="D">Facilitate easy release of sperm</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The scrotum helps in maintaining the low temperature of the testes (2–2.5°C lower than the normal internal body temperature) necessary for spermatogenesis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which hormone is responsible for the intense uterine contractions during parturition?</text>
            <option id="A">Progesterone</option>
            <option id="B">Prolactin</option>
            <option id="C">Oxytocin</option>
            <option id="D">Estrogen</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Oxytocin acts on the uterine muscle and causes stronger uterine contractions, which in turn stimulates further secretion of oxytocin, leading to the expulsion of the baby (parturition).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The structure that connects the developing fetus to the maternal body for the exchange of nutrients and wastes is the:</text>
            <option id="A">Amnion</option>
            <option id="B">Umbilical cord</option>
            <option id="C">Placenta</option>
            <option id="D">Yolk sac</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The placenta facilitates the supply of oxygen and nutrients to the embryo and also the removal of carbon dioxide and excretory/waste materials produced by the embryo.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which part of the fallopian tube is the site of fertilization in humans?</text>
            <option id="A">Infundibulum</option>
            <option id="B">Ampulla</option>
            <option id="C">Isthmus</option>
            <option id="D">Cervix</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Fertilisation can only occur if the ovum and sperms are transported simultaneously to the ampullary region. This is the reason why not all copulations lead to fertilisation and pregnancy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of release of an ovum from a mature Graafian follicle is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Implantation</option>
            <option id="B">Gestation</option>
            <option id="C">Ovulation</option>
            <option id="D">Parturition</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The secondary oocyte forms a new membrane called zona pellucida around it. The Graafian follicle now ruptures to release the secondary oocyte (ovum) from the ovary by the process called ovulation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a male accessory gland?</text>
            <option id="A">Seminal vesicle</option>
            <option id="B">Prostate gland</option>
            <option id="C">Bulbourethral gland</option>
            <option id="D">Bartholin's gland</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The male accessory glands include paired seminal vesicles, a prostate and paired bulbourethral glands. Bartholin's glands are found in females, located on each side of the vaginal opening.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The male reproductive system is located in the:</text>
            <option id="A">Pelvic region</option>
            <option id="B">Thoracic region</option>
            <option id="C">Abdominal region</option>
            <option id="D">Cranial region</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The male reproductive system is located in the pelvis region. It includes a pair of testes along with accessory ducts, glands and the external genitalia.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the function of the scrotum?</text>
            <option id="A">Production of sperms</option>
            <option id="B">Secretion of testosterone</option>
            <option id="C">Maintaining low temperature of testes</option>
            <option id="D">Storage of seminal plasma</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The scrotum helps in maintaining the low temperature of the testes (2-2.5 degree C lower than the normal internal body temperature) necessary for spermatogenesis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The onset of puberty in human males is triggered by a significant increase in the secretion of:</text>
            <option id="A">Testosterone from Leydig cells</option>
            <option id="B">Gonadotropin releasing hormone (GnRH) from hypothalamus</option>
            <option id="C">FSH from anterior pituitary</option>
            <option id="D">Inhibin from Sertoli cells</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Spermatogenesis starts at the age of puberty due to significant increase in the secretion of gonadotropin releasing hormone (GnRH). This is a hypothalamic hormone.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Each testis has about how many compartments called testicular lobules?</text>
            <option id="A">50</option>
            <option id="B">150</option>
            <option id="C">250</option>
            <option id="D">500</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Each testis is oval in shape, with a length of about 4 to 5 cm and a width of about 2 to 3 cm. Each testis has about 250 compartments called testicular lobules.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Each testicular lobule contains one to three highly coiled structures where sperms are produced. What are they called?</text>
            <option id="A">Vasa efferentia</option>
            <option id="B">Epididymis</option>
            <option id="C">Seminiferous tubules</option>
            <option id="D">Rete testis</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Each lobule contains one to three highly coiled seminiferous tubules in which sperms are produced.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which cells synthesize and secrete testicular hormones called androgens?</text>
            <option id="A">Sertoli cells</option>
            <option id="B">Leydig cells (Interstitial cells)</option>
            <option id="C">Male germ cells (Spermatogonia)</option>
            <option id="D">Spermatozoa</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The regions outside the seminiferous tubules called interstitial spaces, contain small blood vessels and interstitial cells or Leydig cells. Leydig cells synthesise and secrete testicular hormones called androgens.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The male accessory glands include paired seminal vesicles, a prostate and paired bulbourethral glands. Secretions of these glands constitute the:</text>
            <option id="A">Semen</option>
            <option id="B">Seminal plasma</option>
            <option id="C">Sperm</option>
            <option id="D">Smegma</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The male accessory glands include paired seminal vesicles, a prostate and paired bulbourethral glands. Secretions of these glands constitute the seminal plasma which is rich in fructose, calcium and certain enzymes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the function of the bulbourethral glands?</text>
            <option id="A">Production of sperm</option>
            <option id="B">Secretion of testosterone</option>
            <option id="C">Lubrication of the penis</option>
            <option id="D">Storage of sperm</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The secretions of bulbourethral glands also helps in the lubrication of the penis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The female reproductive system consists of a pair of ovaries, along with a pair of oviducts, uterus, cervix, vagina and the external genitalia. Where is this system located?</text>
            <option id="A">Thoracic region</option>
            <option id="B">Abdominal cavity</option>
            <option id="C">Pelvic region</option>
            <option id="D">Pectoral region</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The female reproductive system consists of a pair of ovaries along with a pair of oviducts, uterus, cervix, vagina and the external genitalia located in pelvic region.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following hormones is NOT produced by the placenta?</text>
            <option id="A">Human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG)</option>
            <option id="B">Human placental lactogen (hPL)</option>
            <option id="C">Estrogens</option>
            <option id="D">Luteinizing hormone (LH)</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Placenta also acts as an endocrine tissue and produces several hormones like human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG), human placental lactogen (hPL), estrogens, progestogens, etc.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Relaxin is secreted by the:</text>
            <option id="A">Placenta</option>
            <option id="B">Ovary</option>
            <option id="C">Pituitary gland</option>
            <option id="D">Uterus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In the later phase of pregnancy, a hormone called relaxin is also secreted by the ovary. Let us remember that hCG, hPL and relaxin are produced in women only during pregnancy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first movements of the foetus and appearance of hair on the head are usually observed during which month of pregnancy?</text>
            <option id="A">Third month</option>
            <option id="B">Fourth month</option>
            <option id="C">Fifth month</option>
            <option id="D">Sixth month</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The first movements of the foetus and appearance of hair on the head are usually observed during the fifth month. By the end of about 24 weeks (end of second trimester), the body is covered with fine hair, eye-lids separate, and eyelashes are formed.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Each testis has about how many testicular lobules?</text>
            <option id="A">50</option>
            <option id="B">150</option>
            <option id="C">250</option>
            <option id="D">500</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Each testis is oval in shape, with a length of about 4 to 5 cm and a width of about 2 to 3 cm. The testis is covered by a dense covering. Each testis has about 250 compartments called testicular lobules.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which cells in the seminiferous tubules provide nutrition to the germ cells?</text>
            <option id="A">Leydig cells</option>
            <option id="B">Sertoli cells</option>
            <option id="C">Spermatogonia</option>
            <option id="D">Interstitial cells</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Each lobule contains one to three highly coiled seminiferous tubules in which sperms are produced. Each seminiferous tubule is lined on its inside by two types of cells called male germ cells (spermatogonia) and Sertoli cells. The Sertoli cells provide nutrition to the germ cells.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The male accessory glands include paired seminal vesicles, a prostate, and paired bulbourethral glands. What is the function of the bulbourethral glands?</text>
            <option id="A">Storage of sperms</option>
            <option id="B">Production of testosterone</option>
            <option id="C">Lubrication of the penis</option>
            <option id="D">Formation of the acrosome</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The male accessory glands include paired seminal vesicles, a prostate and paired bulbourethral glands. Secretions of these glands constitute the seminal plasma which is rich in fructose, calcium and certain enzymes. The secretions of bulbourethral glands also helps in the lubrication of the penis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following statements about human reproduction is correct?</text>
            <option id="A">Humans are oviparous</option>
            <option id="B">Humans are asexually reproducing</option>
            <option id="C">Humans are sexually reproducing and viviparous</option>
            <option id="D">Humans are hermaphrodites</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>As you are aware, humans are sexually reproducing and viviparous. The reproductive events in humans include formation of gametes (gametogenesis), i.e., sperms in males and ovum in females, transfer of sperms into the female genital tract (insemination) and fusion of male and female gametes (fertilisation).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of formation of gametes in males and females is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Gametogenesis</option>
            <option id="B">Insemination</option>
            <option id="C">Fertilisation</option>
            <option id="D">Gestation</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The reproductive events in humans include formation of gametes (gametogenesis), i.e., sperms in males and ovum in females.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The transfer of sperms into the female genital tract is termed:</text>
            <option id="A">Fertilisation</option>
            <option id="B">Insemination</option>
            <option id="C">Implantation</option>
            <option id="D">Parturition</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Transfer of sperms into the female genital tract is known as insemination.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which structure maintains the low temperature of the testes (2-2.5°C lower than normal internal body temperature), which is necessary for spermatogenesis?</text>
            <option id="A">Epididymis</option>
            <option id="B">Scrotum</option>
            <option id="C">Prostate gland</option>
            <option id="D">Vas deferens</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The testes are situated outside the abdominal cavity within a pouch called scrotum. The scrotum helps in maintaining the low temperature of the testes (2-2.50 C lower than the normal internal body temperature) necessary for spermatogenesis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Each testis in adults is oval in shape and has approximately how many testicular lobules?</text>
            <option id="A">50</option>
            <option id="B">100</option>
            <option id="C">250</option>
            <option id="D">500</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In adults, each testis is oval in shape, with a length of about 4 to 5 cm and a width of about 2 to 3 cm. The testis is covered by a dense covering. Each testis has about 250 compartments called testicular lobules.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Where are sperms produced within the testicular lobules?</text>
            <option id="A">In the Leydig cells</option>
            <option id="B">In the highly coiled seminiferous tubules</option>
            <option id="C">In the rete testis</option>
            <option id="D">In the vasa efferentia</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Each lobule contains one to three highly coiled seminiferous tubules in which sperms are produced.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The vas deferens receives a duct from the seminal vesicle and opens into the urethra as the:</text>
            <option id="A">Epididymis</option>
            <option id="B">Rete testis</option>
            <option id="C">Ejaculatory duct</option>
            <option id="D">Ureter</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The epididymis leads to vas deferens that ascends to the abdomen and loops over the urinary bladder. It receives a duct from seminal vesicle and opens into urethra as the ejaculatory duct.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the function of the ejaculatory ducts in the male reproductive system?</text>
            <option id="A">To produce sperms</option>
            <option id="B">To store and transport the sperms from the testis to the outside through urethra</option>
            <option id="C">To synthesize androgens</option>
            <option id="D">To provide nutrition to sperms</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>These ducts [ejaculatory ducts] store and transport the sperms from the testis to the outside through urethra.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The urethra originates from the urinary bladder and extends through the penis to its external opening called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Glans penis</option>
            <option id="B">Urethral meatus</option>
            <option id="C">Foreskin</option>
            <option id="D">Prostate</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The urethra originates from the urinary bladder and extends through the penis to its external opening called urethral meatus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The female accessory ducts include the fallopian tubes, uterus, and vagina. Approximately how long is each fallopian tube?</text>
            <option id="A">1-2 cm</option>
            <option id="B">5-8 cm</option>
            <option id="C">10-12 cm</option>
            <option id="D">15-20 cm</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The oviducts (fallopian tubes), uterus and vagina constitute the female accessory ducts. Each fallopian tube is about 10-12 cm long and extends from the periphery of each ovary to the uterus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The part of the fallopian tube closest to the ovary is funnel-shaped. What is it called?</text>
            <option id="A">Ampulla</option>
            <option id="B">Isthmus</option>
            <option id="C">Infundibulum</option>
            <option id="D">Cervix</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The part closer to the ovary is the funnel-shaped infundibulum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The edges of the infundibulum possess finger-like projections that help in the collection of the ovum after ovulation. What are these called?</text>
            <option id="A">Cilia</option>
            <option id="B">Fimbriae</option>
            <option id="C">Villi</option>
            <option id="D">Microvilli</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The edges of the infundibulum possess finger-like projections called fimbriae, which help in collection of the ovum after ovulation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The middle layer of the uterus is a thick layer of smooth muscle. What is it called?</text>
            <option id="A">Perimetrium</option>
            <option id="B">Endometrium</option>
            <option id="C">Myometrium</option>
            <option id="D">Mesometrium</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The wall of the uterus has three layers of tissue... middle thick layer of smooth muscle, myometrium...</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The inner glandular layer that lines the uterine cavity is called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Perimetrium</option>
            <option id="B">Myometrium</option>
            <option id="C">Endometrium</option>
            <option id="D">Epithelium</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>...and inner glandular layer called endometrium that lines the uterine cavity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which layer of the uterus undergoes cyclical changes during the menstrual cycle?</text>
            <option id="A">Perimetrium</option>
            <option id="B">Myometrium</option>
            <option id="C">Endometrium</option>
            <option id="D">Cervix</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The endometrium undergoes cyclical changes during menstrual cycle while the myometrium exhibits strong contraction during delivery of the baby.</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>Which cells in the testis synthesize and secrete testicular hormones called androgens?</text>
            <option id="A">Sertoli cells</option>
            <option id="B">Spermatogonia</option>
            <option id="C">Leydig cells</option>
            <option id="D">Primary spermatocytes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The regions outside the seminiferous tubules called interstitial spaces contain small blood vessels and interstitial cells or Leydig cells. Leydig cells synthesise and secrete testicular hormones called androgens.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the human female menstrual cycle, the rapid secretion of LH leading to its maximum level during the mid-cycle (about 14th day) induces:</text>
            <option id="A">Degeneration of the corpus luteum</option>
            <option id="B">Development of ovarian follicles</option>
            <option id="C">Rupture of the Graafian follicle and release of the ovum</option>
            <option id="D">Thickening of the endometrium</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Rapid secretion of LH leading to its maximum level during the mid-cycle is called the LH surge. It induces rupture of the Graafian follicle and thereby the release of ovum (ovulation).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first movements of the fetus and appearance of hair on the head are usually observed during which month of pregnancy?</text>
            <option id="A">Third month</option>
            <option id="B">Fourth month</option>
            <option id="C">Fifth month</option>
            <option id="D">Sixth month</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The first movements of the fetus and appearance of hair on the head are usually observed during the fifth month of human pregnancy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the correct sequence of spermatogenesis?</text>
            <option id="A">Spermatogonia -> Spermatids -> Primary spermatocytes -> Secondary spermatocytes -> Spermatozoa</option>
            <option id="B">Spermatogonia -> Primary spermatocytes -> Secondary spermatocytes -> Spermatids -> Spermatozoa</option>
            <option id="C">Primary spermatocytes -> Secondary spermatocytes -> Spermatogonia -> Spermatids -> Spermatozoa</option>
            <option id="D">Spermatogonia -> Primary spermatocytes -> Spermatids -> Secondary spermatocytes -> Spermatozoa</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Spermatogonia multiply by mitosis. Some grow into primary spermatocytes, which undergo meiosis I to form secondary spermatocytes, which undergo meiosis II to form spermatids. Spermatids transform into spermatozoa (sperms).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In humans, the blastocyst becomes embedded in the endometrium of the uterus. This process is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Cleavage</option>
            <option id="B">Implantation</option>
            <option id="C">Placentation</option>
            <option id="D">Gastrulation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The blastomeres in the blastocyst are arranged into an outer layer called trophoblast and an inner group of cells attached to trophoblast called the inner cell mass. The trophoblast layer then gets attached to the endometrium and the inner cell mass gets differentiated as the embryo. After attachment, the uterine cells divide rapidly and covers the blastocyst. As a result, the blastocyst becomes embedded in the endometrium of the uterus. This is called implantation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which hormone is primarily responsible for maintaining the corpus luteum during the early stages of pregnancy?</text>
            <option id="A">Progesterone</option>
            <option id="B">Estrogen</option>
            <option id="C">hCG (Human Chorionic Gonadotropin)</option>
            <option id="D">LH (Luteinizing Hormone)</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>If fertilization occurs, the developing embryo secretes hCG (Human Chorionic Gonadotropin), which is analogous to LH. It maintains the corpus luteum, which continues to secrete progesterone essential for the maintenance of the endometrium.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During spermatogenesis, the primary spermatocytes undergo which type of cell division to form secondary spermatocytes?</text>
            <option id="A">Mitosis</option>
            <option id="B">Meiosis I</option>
            <option id="C">Meiosis II</option>
            <option id="D">Amitosis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A primary spermatocyte completes the first meiotic division (reduction division) leading to formation of two equal, haploid cells called secondary spermatocytes, which have only 23 chromosomes each.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The milk produced during the initial few days of lactation is called colostrum. Which antibody is most abundant in it?</text>
            <option id="A">IgA</option>
            <option id="B">IgG</option>
            <option id="C">IgM</option>
            <option id="D">IgE</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The milk produced during the initial few days of lactation is called colostrum which contains several antibodies (abundantly IgA) absolutely essential to develop resistance for the new-born babies.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In human females, meiosis I of primary oocyte is completed:</text>
            <option id="A">Before birth</option>
            <option id="B">At the time of puberty</option>
            <option id="C">Prior to ovulation</option>
            <option id="D">At the time of fertilization</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The primary oocyte within the tertiary follicle grows in size and completes its first meiotic division prior to ovulation. It is an unequal division resulting in the formation of a large haploid secondary oocyte and a tiny first polar body.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The structure that provides a physical and physiological connection between the maternal body and the embryo is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Umbilical cord</option>
            <option id="B">Placenta</option>
            <option id="C">Amnion</option>
            <option id="D">Chorionic villi</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The chorionic villi and uterine tissue become interdigitated with each other and jointly form a structural and functional unit between developing embryo (foetus) and maternal body called placenta.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which hormone induces strong uterine contractions during parturition?</text>
            <option id="A">Relaxin</option>
            <option id="B">Estrogen</option>
            <option id="C">Oxytocin</option>
            <option id="D">Progesterone</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Oxytocin acts on the uterine muscle and causes stronger uterine contractions, which in turn stimulates further secretion of oxytocin, leading to expulsion of the baby out of the uterus through the birth canal.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the human menstrual cycle, ovulation usually occurs on which day (assuming a 28-day cycle)?</text>
            <option id="A">Day 1</option>
            <option id="B">Day 5</option>
            <option id="C">Day 14</option>
            <option id="D">Day 28</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Both LH and FSH attain a peak level in the middle of cycle (about 14th day). Rapid secretion of LH leading to its maximum level during the mid-cycle called LH surge induces rupture of Graafian follicle and thereby the release of ovum (ovulation).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The male accessory glands include paired seminal vesicles, a prostate, and paired bulbourethral glands. Secretions of which gland help in the lubrication of the penis?</text>
            <option id="A">Seminal vesicles</option>
            <option id="B">Prostate gland</option>
            <option id="C">Bulbourethral glands</option>
            <option id="D">All of the above</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The male accessory glands include paired seminal vesicles, a prostate and paired bulbourethral glands. Secretions of bulbourethral glands also helps in the lubrication of the penis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the human female reproductive system, the edges of the infundibulum possess finger-like projections which help in collection of the ovum after ovulation. These projections are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Ampulla</option>
            <option id="B">Isthmus</option>
            <option id="C">Fimbriae</option>
            <option id="D">Cervix</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The part of the fallopian tube closer to the ovary is the funnel-shaped infundibulum. The edges of the infundibulum possess finger-like projections called fimbriae, which help in collection of the ovum after ovulation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which layer of the uterus exhibits strong contraction during delivery of the baby?</text>
            <option id="A">Perimetrium</option>
            <option id="B">Myometrium</option>
            <option id="C">Endometrium</option>
            <option id="D">Epimetrium</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The wall of the uterus has three layers of tissue. The external thin membranous perimetrium, middle thick layer of smooth muscle, myometrium and inner glandular layer called endometrium. The myometrium exhibits strong contraction during delivery of the baby.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The female external genitalia include mons pubis, labia majora, labia minora, hymen and clitoris. Which of these is a cushion of fatty tissue covered by skin and pubic hair?</text>
            <option id="A">Mons pubis</option>
            <option id="B">Labia majora</option>
            <option id="C">Labia minora</option>
            <option id="D">Clitoris</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The mons pubis is a cushion of fatty tissue covered by skin and pubic hair.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Each ovary is almond-shaped and is covered by a thin epithelium which encloses the ovarian stroma. The stroma is divided into two zones:</text>
            <option id="A">An outer cortex and an inner medulla</option>
            <option id="B">An outer medulla and an inner cortex</option>
            <option id="C">An anterior cortex and a posterior medulla</option>
            <option id="D">A superior cortex and an inferior medulla</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Each ovary is covered by a thin epithelium which encloses the ovarian stroma. The stroma is divided into two zones - a peripheral cortex and an inner medulla.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The part of the oviduct (fallopian tube) closer to the ovary is the funnel-shaped:</text>
            <option id="A">Ampulla</option>
            <option id="B">Isthmus</option>
            <option id="C">Infundibulum</option>
            <option id="D">Fimbriae</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Each fallopian tube is about 10-12 cm long and extends from the periphery of each ovary to the uterus. The part closer to the ovary is the funnel-shaped infundibulum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The edges of the infundibulum possess finger-like projections called fimbriae, which help in:</text>
            <option id="A">Transport of sperm</option>
            <option id="B">Collection of the ovum after ovulation</option>
            <option id="C">Implantation of the embryo</option>
            <option id="D">Secretion of estrogen</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The edges of the infundibulum possess finger-like projections called fimbriae, which help in collection of the ovum after ovulation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The uterus is single and it is also called the womb. The shape of the uterus is like an inverted:</text>
            <option id="A">Apple</option>
            <option id="B">Pear</option>
            <option id="C">Pineapple</option>
            <option id="D">Banana</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The uterus is single and it is also called womb. The shape of the uterus is like an inverted pear. It is supported by ligaments attached to the pelvic wall.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of delivery of the foetus (childbirth) is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Gestation</option>
            <option id="B">Parturition</option>
            <option id="C">Implantation</option>
            <option id="D">Lactation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The average duration of human pregnancy is about 9 months which is called the gestation period. Vigorous contraction of the uterus at the end of pregnancy causes expulsion/delivery of the foetus. This process of delivery of the foetus (childbirth) is called parturition.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Parturition is induced by a complex neuroendocrine mechanism. The signals for parturition originate from the:</text>
            <option id="A">Maternal pituitary and hypothalamus</option>
            <option id="B">Fully developed foetus and the placenta</option>
            <option id="C">Ovary and fallopian tubes</option>
            <option id="D">Uterine myometrium</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Parturition is induced by a complex neuroendocrine mechanism. The signals for parturition originate from the fully developed foetus and the placenta which induce mild uterine contractions called foetal ejection reflex.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which maternal hormone plays a major role in inducing strong uterine contractions during parturition?</text>
            <option id="A">Estrogen</option>
            <option id="B">Progesterone</option>
            <option id="C">Oxytocin</option>
            <option id="D">Prolactin</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>This triggers release of oxytocin from the maternal pituitary. Oxytocin acts on the uterine muscle and causes stronger uterine contractions, which in turn stimulates further secretion of oxytocin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Colostrum, the yellowish milk produced during the initial few days of lactation, is extremely essential to impart resistance to the new-born babies because it contains abundant:</text>
            <option id="A">Proteins</option>
            <option id="B">Fats</option>
            <option id="C">Antibodies</option>
            <option id="D">Carbohydrates</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The milk produced during the initial few days of lactation is called colostrum which contains several antibodies absolutely essential to develop resistance for the new-born babies.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the ovary, each follicle contains a primary oocyte surrounded by a single layer of granulosa cells. What is this follicle called?</text>
            <option id="A">Secondary follicle</option>
            <option id="B">Tertiary follicle</option>
            <option id="C">Primary follicle</option>
            <option id="D">Graafian follicle</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Each primary oocyte then gets surrounded by a layer of granulosa cells and is called the primary follicle. A large number of these follicles degenerate during the phase from birth to puberty.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The tertiary follicle is characterized by a fluid-filled cavity called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Antrum</option>
            <option id="B">Zona pellucida</option>
            <option id="C">Corona radiata</option>
            <option id="D">Corpus luteum</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The secondary follicle soon transforms into a tertiary follicle which is characterised by a fluid filled cavity called antrum. The theca layer is organised into an inner theca interna and an outer theca externa.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Ovulation occurs when the Graafian follicle ruptures to release the secondary oocyte. This is typically induced by a surge in which hormone?</text>
            <option id="A">FSH</option>
            <option id="B">Estrogen</option>
            <option id="C">LH</option>
            <option id="D">Progesterone</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Rapid secretion of LH leading to its maximum level during the mid-cycle (about 14th day) called LH surge induces rupture of Graafian follicle and thereby the release of ovum (ovulation).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>After ovulation, the ruptured follicle transforms into a yellow glandular structure called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Corpus albicans</option>
            <option id="B">Corpus luteum</option>
            <option id="C">Cumulus oophorus</option>
            <option id="D">Follicular atresia</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>After ovulation, the remaining parts of the Graafian follicle transform as the corpus luteum. The corpus luteum secretes large amounts of progesterone which is essential for maintenance of the endometrium.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The fusion of male and female gametes leading to the formation of a zygote is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Gametogenesis</option>
            <option id="B">Insemination</option>
            <option id="C">Fertilisation</option>
            <option id="D">Implantation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Fusion of male and female gametes leading to formation of zygote is called fertilisation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The attachment of the blastocyst to the uterine wall is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Fertilisation</option>
            <option id="B">Implantation</option>
            <option id="C">Gestation</option>
            <option id="D">Parturition</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Fertilisation is followed by formation and development of blastocyst and its attachment to the uterine wall (implantation).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The embryonic development period in humans is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Gametogenesis</option>
            <option id="B">Insemination</option>
            <option id="C">Gestation</option>
            <option id="D">Parturition</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Embryonic development period is called gestation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of delivery of the baby is termed:</text>
            <option id="A">Insemination</option>
            <option id="B">Implantation</option>
            <option id="C">Gestation</option>
            <option id="D">Parturition</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The delivery of the baby is called parturition.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The inside of each seminiferous tubule is lined by two types of cells called:</text>
            <option id="A">Leydig cells and Sertoli cells</option>
            <option id="B">Male germ cells (spermatogonia) and Sertoli cells</option>
            <option id="C">Primary spermatocytes and Leydig cells</option>
            <option id="D">Spermatids and Interstitial cells</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Each seminiferous tubule is lined on its inside by two types of cells called male germ cells (spermatogonia) and Sertoli cells.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which cells in the seminiferous tubule undergo meiotic divisions leading to sperm formation?</text>
            <option id="A">Sertoli cells</option>
            <option id="B">Leydig cells</option>
            <option id="C">Male germ cells (spermatogonia)</option>
            <option id="D">Interstitial cells</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The male germ cells undergo meiotic divisions finally leading to sperm formation, while Sertoli cells provide nutrition to the germ cells.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the function of the Sertoli cells?</text>
            <option id="A">To undergo meiosis</option>
            <option id="B">To synthesize androgens</option>
            <option id="C">To provide nutrition to the germ cells</option>
            <option id="D">To transport sperms to the epididymis</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The male germ cells undergo meiotic divisions finally leading to sperm formation, while Sertoli cells provide nutrition to the germ cells.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The regions outside the seminiferous tubules called interstitial spaces contain blood vessels and specific cells that synthesize and secrete testicular hormones (androgens). These cells are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Sertoli cells</option>
            <option id="B">Leydig cells (Interstitial cells)</option>
            <option id="C">Spermatogonia</option>
            <option id="D">Prostate cells</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The regions outside the seminiferous tubules called interstitial spaces, contain small blood vessels and interstitial cells or Leydig cells. Leydig cells synthesise and secrete testicular hormones called androgens. Other immunologically competent cells are also present.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The penis is the male external genitalia. It is made up of special tissue that helps in what process to facilitate insemination?</text>
            <option id="A">Spermatogenesis</option>
            <option id="B">Erection</option>
            <option id="C">Ejaculation</option>
            <option id="D">Urine transport</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The penis is the male external genitalia. It is made up of special tissue that helps in erection of the penis to facilitate insemination.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The enlarged end of the penis is covered by a loose fold of skin called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Scrotum</option>
            <option id="B">Glans penis</option>
            <option id="C">Foreskin</option>
            <option id="D">Epididymis</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The enlarged end of penis called the glans penis is covered by a loose fold of skin called foreskin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The male accessory glands include paired seminal vesicles, a prostate, and paired bulbourethral glands. Their secretions constitute the:</text>
            <option id="A">Seminal plasma</option>
            <option id="B">Spermatogonia</option>
            <option id="C">Androgens</option>
            <option id="D">Smegma</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The male accessory glands include paired seminal vesicles, a prostate and paired bulbourethral glands. Secretions of these glands constitute the seminal plasma.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Seminal plasma, secreted by the male accessory glands, is rich in which of the following?</text>
            <option id="A">Glucose, iron, and enzymes</option>
            <option id="B">Fructose, calcium, and certain enzymes</option>
            <option id="C">Sucrose, potassium, and antibodies</option>
            <option id="D">Lactose, magnesium, and hormones</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Secretions of these glands constitute the seminal plasma which is rich in fructose, calcium and certain enzymes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The infundibulum leads to a wider part of the oviduct called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Isthmus</option>
            <option id="B">Ampulla</option>
            <option id="C">Uterus</option>
            <option id="D">Cervix</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The infundibulum leads to a wider part of the oviduct called ampulla.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the last part of the oviduct that has a narrow lumen and joins the uterus?</text>
            <option id="A">Ampulla</option>
            <option id="B">Infundibulum</option>
            <option id="C">Isthmus</option>
            <option id="D">Fimbriae</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The last part of the oviduct, isthmus has a narrow lumen and it joins the uterus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The uterus is single and is also known as the:</text>
            <option id="A">Vagina</option>
            <option id="B">Womb</option>
            <option id="C">Cervix</option>
            <option id="D">Oviduct</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The uterus is single and it is also called womb.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the general shape of the uterus?</text>
            <option id="A">Spherical</option>
            <option id="B">Like an inverted pear</option>
            <option id="C">Like a kidney</option>
            <option id="D">Tubular</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The shape of the uterus is like an inverted pear. It is supported by ligaments attached to the pelvic wall.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which layer of the uterus exhibits strong contraction during the delivery of a baby?</text>
            <option id="A">Endometrium</option>
            <option id="B">Perimetrium</option>
            <option id="C">Myometrium</option>
            <option id="D">Vagina</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>...while the myometrium exhibits strong contraction during delivery of the baby.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The female external genitalia include the mons pubis, labia majora, labia minora, hymen, and clitoris. What is the mons pubis?</text>
            <option id="A">A tiny finger-like structure above the urethral opening</option>
            <option id="B">A cushion of fatty tissue covered by skin and pubic hair</option>
            <option id="C">A membrane partially covering the opening of the vagina</option>
            <option id="D">Fleshy folds of tissue that surround the vaginal opening</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The female external genitalia include mons pubis, labia majora, labia minora, hymen and clitoris. Mons pubis is a cushion of fatty tissue covered by skin and pubic hair.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What are the fleshy folds of tissue which extend down from the mons pubis and surround the vaginal opening called?</text>
            <option id="A">Labia minora</option>
            <option id="B">Labia majora</option>
            <option id="C">Hymen</option>
            <option id="D">Clitoris</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The labia majora are fleshy folds of tissue, which extend down from the mons pubis and surround the vaginal opening.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What are the paired folds of tissue located under the labia majora called?</text>
            <option id="A">Mons pubis</option>
            <option id="B">Labia minora</option>
            <option id="C">Hymen</option>
            <option id="D">Clitoris</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The labia minora are paired folds of tissue under the labia majora.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>During fertilization, the sperm comes in contact with which layer of the ovum to induce changes in the membrane that block the entry of additional sperms?</text>
            <option id="A">Corona radiata</option>
            <option id="B">Zona pellucida</option>
            <option id="C">Vitelline membrane</option>
            <option id="D">Plasma membrane</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>During fertilisation, a sperm comes in contact with the zona pellucida layer of the ovum and induces changes in the membrane that block the entry of additional sperms, thus ensuring monospermy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The acrosome of the sperm is a modified organelle that is essential for fertilization. Which cellular organelle gives rise to the acrosome?</text>
            <option id="A">Mitochondria</option>
            <option id="B">Endoplasmic reticulum</option>
            <option id="C">Golgi body</option>
            <option id="D">Lysosome</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The acrosome is a cap-like structure at the anterior part of the sperm head, filled with enzymes that help fertilize the ovum. It is derived from the Golgi apparatus during spermiogenesis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT secreted by the human placenta?</text>
            <option id="A">hCG (Human Chorionic Gonadotropin)</option>
            <option id="B">hPL (Human Placental Lactogen)</option>
            <option id="C">Estrogens</option>
            <option id="D">Relaxin</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The placenta acts as an endocrine tissue and produces several hormones like hCG, hPL, estrogens, progestogens, etc. Relaxin is secreted by the ovary in the later phase of pregnancy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following events is NOT associated with the luteal phase of the menstrual cycle?</text>
            <option id="A">Formation of corpus luteum</option>
            <option id="B">Secretion of large amounts of progesterone</option>
            <option id="C">Thickening of the endometrium</option>
            <option id="D">Primary follicle grows to become a fully mature Graafian follicle</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The primary follicle grows to become a fully mature Graafian follicle during the follicular phase, not the luteal phase. In the luteal phase, the remaining parts of the ruptured Graafian follicle transform as the corpus luteum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the correct ploidy level of spermatogonia, primary spermatocyte, secondary spermatocyte, and spermatid respectively?</text>
            <option id="A">2n, n, n, n</option>
            <option id="B">2n, 2n, n, n</option>
            <option id="C">n, 2n, n, n</option>
            <option id="D">2n, 2n, 2n, n</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Spermatogonia are diploid (2n=46). Some of them periodically undergo meiosis as primary spermatocytes (2n=46). They complete meiosis I to form secondary spermatocytes (n=23). These complete meiosis II to form spermatids (n=23).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The inner glandular layer that lines the uterine cavity is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Perimetrium</option>
            <option id="B">Myometrium</option>
            <option id="C">Endometrium</option>
            <option id="D">Mesometrium</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The wall of the uterus has three layers of tissue. The external thin membranous perimetrium, middle thick layer of smooth muscle, myometrium and inner glandular layer called endometrium that lines the uterine cavity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following sequences represents the correct pathway of sperm transport in human males?</text>
            <option id="A">Seminiferous tubules -> Rete testis -> Vasa efferentia -> Epididymis -> Vas deferens</option>
            <option id="B">Seminiferous tubules -> Vasa efferentia -> Epididymis -> Rete testis -> Vas deferens</option>
            <option id="C">Testis -> Epididymis -> Vasa efferentia -> Rete testis -> Urethra</option>
            <option id="D">Rete testis -> Seminiferous tubules -> Vas deferens -> Epididymis</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The seminiferous tubules of the testis open into the vasa efferentia through rete testis. The vasa efferentia leave the testis and open into epididymis located along the posterior surface of each testis. The epididymis leads to vas deferens that ascends to the abdomen.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first movements of the foetus and appearance of hair on the head are usually observed during which month of pregnancy?</text>
            <option id="A">Third month</option>
            <option id="B">Fourth month</option>
            <option id="C">Fifth month</option>
            <option id="D">Sixth month</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The first movements of the foetus and appearance of hair on the head are usually observed during the fifth month.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which layer of the ovum is essential to ensure that only one sperm fertilizes the ovum (preventing polyspermy)?</text>
            <option id="A">Corona radiata</option>
            <option id="B">Zona pellucida</option>
            <option id="C">Vitelline membrane</option>
            <option id="D">Plasma membrane</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>During fertilisation, a sperm comes in contact with the zona pellucida layer of the ovum and induces changes in the membrane that block the entry of additional sperms. Thus, it ensures that only one sperm can fertilise an ovum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of formation of a mature female gamete is called oogenesis. When is oogenesis initiated in human females?</text>
            <option id="A">At puberty</option>
            <option id="B">During the embryonic development stage</option>
            <option id="C">Just before ovulation</option>
            <option id="D">At the time of fertilization</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Oogenesis is initiated during the embryonic development stage when a couple of million gamete mother cells (oogonia) are formed within each foetal ovary; no more oogonia are formed and added after birth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The primary follicles in the ovary get surrounded by more layers of granulosa cells and a new theca and are called secondary follicles. The secondary follicle soon transforms into a tertiary follicle which is characterised by a fluid-filled cavity called:</text>
            <option id="A">Antrum</option>
            <option id="B">Blastocoel</option>
            <option id="C">Amniotic cavity</option>
            <option id="D">Chorionic cavity</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The secondary follicle soon transforms into a tertiary follicle which is characterised by a fluid filled cavity called antrum. The theca layer is organised into an inner theca interna and an outer theca externa.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The menstrual cycle consists of four phases. During which phase do the primary follicles in the ovary grow to become a fully mature Graafian follicle and simultaneously the endometrium of uterus regenerates through proliferation?</text>
            <option id="A">Menstrual phase</option>
            <option id="B">Follicular phase (Proliferative phase)</option>
            <option id="C">Ovulatory phase</option>
            <option id="D">Luteal phase (Secretory phase)</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The menstrual phase is followed by the follicular phase. During this phase, the primary follicles in the ovary grow to become a fully mature Graafian follicle and simultaneously the endometrium of uterus regenerates through proliferation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The wall of the uterus has three layers of tissue. The external thin membranous layer is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Myometrium</option>
            <option id="B">Endometrium</option>
            <option id="C">Perimetrium</option>
            <option id="D">Mesometrium</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The wall of the uterus has three layers of tissue. The external thin membranous perimetrium, middle thick layer of smooth muscle, myometrium and inner glandular layer called endometrium.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which layer of the uterus undergoes cyclical changes during menstrual cycle?</text>
            <option id="A">Perimetrium</option>
            <option id="B">Myometrium</option>
            <option id="C">Endometrium</option>
            <option id="D">All of the above</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The endometrium undergoes cyclical changes during menstrual cycle while the myometrium exhibits strong contraction during delivery of the baby.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The female external genitalia include mons pubis, labia majora, labia minora, hymen and clitoris. What is the clitoris?</text>
            <option id="A">A cushion of fatty tissue covered by skin and pubic hair</option>
            <option id="B">Fleshy folds of tissue that surround the vaginal opening</option>
            <option id="C">A tiny finger-like structure which lies at the upper junction of the two labia minora</option>
            <option id="D">A membrane that partially covers the opening of the vagina</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The clitoris is a tiny finger-like structure which lies at the upper junction of the two labia minora above the urethral opening.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Spermatogenesis is initiated at puberty due to a significant increase in the secretion of which hypothalamic hormone?</text>
            <option id="A">Follicle Stimulating Hormone (FSH)</option>
            <option id="B">Luteinizing Hormone (LH)</option>
            <option id="C">Gonadotropin Releasing Hormone (GnRH)</option>
            <option id="D">Testosterone</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Spermatogenesis starts at the age of puberty due to significant increase in the secretion of gonadotropin releasing hormone (GnRH). This, if you recall, is a hypothalamic hormone.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In males, LH acts on which cells to stimulate the synthesis and secretion of androgens?</text>
            <option id="A">Sertoli cells</option>
            <option id="B">Leydig cells</option>
            <option id="C">Spermatogonia</option>
            <option id="D">Primary spermatocytes</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>LH acts at the Leydig cells and stimulates synthesis and secretion of androgens. Androgens, in turn, stimulate the process of spermatogenesis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the function of the acrosome in a mammalian sperm?</text>
            <option id="A">It provides energy for swimming</option>
            <option id="B">It contains enzymes that help in fertilisation of the ovum</option>
            <option id="C">It contains the haploid nucleus</option>
            <option id="D">It controls the movement of the tail</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The anterior portion of which is covered by a cap-like structure, acrosome. The acrosome is filled with enzymes that help fertilisation of the ovum. The middle piece possesses numerous mitochondria, which produce energy for the movement of tail.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During fertilization, a sperm comes in contact with which layer of the ovum to induce changes in the membrane that block the entry of additional sperms?</text>
            <option id="A">Corona radiata</option>
            <option id="B">Zona pellucida</option>
            <option id="C">Plasma membrane</option>
            <option id="D">Perivitelline space</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>During fertilisation, a sperm comes in contact with the zona pellucida layer of the ovum and induces changes in the membrane that block the entry of additional sperms. Thus, it ensures that only one sperm can fertilise an ovum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The blastomeres in the blastocyst are arranged into an outer layer called trophoblast and an inner group of cells attached to the trophoblast called the inner cell mass. Which part gets attached to the endometrium?</text>
            <option id="A">Inner cell mass</option>
            <option id="B">Trophoblast</option>
            <option id="C">Blastocoel</option>
            <option id="D">Zona pellucida</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The blastomeres in the blastocyst are arranged into an outer layer called trophoblast and an inner group of cells attached to trophoblast called the inner cell mass. The trophoblast layer then gets attached to the endometrium and the inner cell mass gets differentiated as the embryo.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Immediately after implantation, the inner cell mass (embryo) differentiates into an outer layer called ectoderm and an inner layer called endoderm. A middle layer, the mesoderm, soon appears. What unique cells does the inner cell mass contain that have the potency to give rise to all the tissues and organs?</text>
            <option id="A">Trophoblast cells</option>
            <option id="B">Sertoli cells</option>
            <option id="C">Stem cells</option>
            <option id="D">Leydig cells</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>It needs to be mentioned here that the inner cell mass contains certain cells called stem cells which have the potency to give rise to all the tissues and organs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>At what stage of life do reproductive events typically occur in humans?</text>
            <option id="A">Immediately after birth</option>
            <option id="B">During childhood</option>
            <option id="C">After puberty</option>
            <option id="D">During old age</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>These reproductive events occur after puberty.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following describes a key difference between male and female reproductive events?</text>
            <option id="A">Sperm formation continues even in old men, but formation of ovum ceases in women around the age of fifty years</option>
            <option id="B">Sperm formation ceases at fifty years, while ovum formation continues</option>
            <option id="C">Both sperm and ovum formation cease at fifty years</option>
            <option id="D">Both sperm and ovum formation continue throughout life</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>There are remarkable differences between the reproductive events in the male and in the female, for example, sperm formation continues even in old men, but formation of ovum ceases in women around the age of fifty years.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The male reproductive system is located in which region of the body?</text>
            <option id="A">Thoracic region</option>
            <option id="B">Abdominal region</option>
            <option id="C">Pelvis region</option>
            <option id="D">Cranial region</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The male reproductive system is located in the pelvis region. It includes a pair of testes alongwith accessory ducts, glands and the external genitalia.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a male sex accessory duct?</text>
            <option id="A">Rete testis</option>
            <option id="B">Vasa efferentia</option>
            <option id="C">Epididymis</option>
            <option id="D">Seminal vesicle</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The male sex accessory ducts include rete testis, vasa efferentia, epididymis and vas deferens. [The seminal vesicle is a gland, not a duct].</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The seminiferous tubules of the testis open into the vasa efferentia through the:</text>
            <option id="A">Epididymis</option>
            <option id="B">Rete testis</option>
            <option id="C">Vas deferens</option>
            <option id="D">Ejaculatory duct</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The seminiferous tubules of the testis open into the vasa efferentia through rete testis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The epididymis leads to the vas deferens that ascends to the abdomen and loops over the:</text>
            <option id="A">Prostate gland</option>
            <option id="B">Urinary bladder</option>
            <option id="C">Urethra</option>
            <option id="D">Seminal vesicle</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The vasa efferentia leave the testis and open into epididymis located along the posterior surface of each testis. The epididymis leads to vas deferens that ascends to the abdomen and loops over the urinary bladder.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The secretions of which male accessory gland also help in the lubrication of the penis?</text>
            <option id="A">Seminal vesicles</option>
            <option id="B">Prostate gland</option>
            <option id="C">Bulbourethral glands</option>
            <option id="D">Testes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The secretions of bulbourethral glands also helps in the lubrication of the penis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The female reproductive system consists of a pair of ovaries along with oviducts, uterus, cervix, vagina, and the external genitalia located in the pelvic region. These parts are structurally and functionally integrated with a pair of which glands to support ovulation, fertilisation, pregnancy, birth, and child care?</text>
            <option id="A">Thyroid glands</option>
            <option id="B">Mammary glands</option>
            <option id="C">Adrenal glands</option>
            <option id="D">Pituitary glands</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>These parts of the system along with a pair of the mammary glands are integrated structurally and functionally to support the processes of ovulation, fertilisation, pregnancy, birth and child care.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Ovaries are the primary female sex organs that produce the female gamete (ovum) and several steroid hormones called:</text>
            <option id="A">Androgens</option>
            <option id="B">Testosterones</option>
            <option id="C">Ovarian hormones</option>
            <option id="D">Corticosteroids</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Ovaries are the primary female sex organs that produce the female gamete (ovum) and several steroid hormones (ovarian hormones).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The uterus opens into the vagina through a narrow structure called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Isthmus</option>
            <option id="B">Ampulla</option>
            <option id="C">Cervix</option>
            <option id="D">Infundibulum</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The uterus opens into vagina through a narrow cervix.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The cavity of the cervix is called the cervical canal. Along with the vagina, what does the cervical canal form?</text>
            <option id="A">The fallopian tube</option>
            <option id="B">The birth canal</option>
            <option id="C">The ejaculatory duct</option>
            <option id="D">The uterine cavity</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The cavity of the cervix is called cervical canal which along with vagina forms the birth canal.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The wall of the uterus has three layers of tissue. What is the external thin membranous layer called?</text>
            <option id="A">Myometrium</option>
            <option id="B">Endometrium</option>
            <option id="C">Perimetrium</option>
            <option id="D">Epithelium</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The wall of the uterus has three layers of tissue. The external thin membranous perimetrium...</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The opening of the vagina is often covered partially by a membrane called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Labia minora</option>
            <option id="B">Clitoris</option>
            <option id="C">Hymen</option>
            <option id="D">Cervix</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The opening of the vagina is often covered partially by a membrane called hymen.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the tiny finger-like structure which lies at the upper junction of the two labia minora above the urethral opening called?</text>
            <option id="A">Mons pubis</option>
            <option id="B">Hymen</option>
            <option id="C">Clitoris</option>
            <option id="D">Ampulla</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The clitoris is a tiny finger-like structure which lies at the upper junction of the two labia minora above the urethral opening.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Is the presence or absence of the hymen a reliable indicator of virginity or sexual experience?</text>
            <option id="A">Yes, it is always torn during first coitus</option>
            <option id="B">No, it can be torn by other activities or persist after coitus</option>
            <option id="C">Yes, it cannot be torn except by coitus</option>
            <option id="D">No, because it regenerates rapidly</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The hymen is often torn during the first coitus (intercourse). However, it can also be broken by a sudden fall or jolt, insertion of a vaginal tampon, active participation in some sports like horseback riding, cycling, etc. In some women the hymen persists even after coitus. In fact, the presence or absence of hymen is not a reliable indicator of virginity or sexual experience.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>