<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="332" name="Microbes in Human Welfare">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>Which microbe is used in the commercial production of citric acid?</text>
            <option id="A">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <option id="B">Acetobacter aceti</option>
            <option id="C">Clostridium butylicum</option>
            <option id="D">Lactobacillus</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Aspergillus niger (a fungus) is used for the production of citric acid. Acetobacter aceti produces acetic acid, Clostridium butylicum produces butyric acid, and Lactobacillus produces lactic acid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The large holes in 'Swiss cheese' are due to the production of a large amount of CO2 by a bacterium named:</text>
            <option id="A">Penicillium roqueforti</option>
            <option id="B">Propionibacterium sharmanii</option>
            <option id="C">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="D">Streptococcus thermophilus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The large holes in 'Swiss cheese' are due to production of a large amount of CO2 by a bacterium named Propionibacterium sharmanii.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is used as a biological control agent to control butterfly caterpillars?</text>
            <option id="A">Trichoderma</option>
            <option id="B">Baculovirus</option>
            <option id="C">Bacillus thuringiensis</option>
            <option id="D">Glomus</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Bacillus thuringiensis (Bt) is a bacterium available as spores that are mixed with water and sprayed onto vulnerable plants to kill butterfly caterpillars.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following alcoholic beverages is produced without distillation?</text>
            <option id="A">Whisky</option>
            <option id="B">Brandy</option>
            <option id="C">Rum</option>
            <option id="D">Wine</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Wine and beer are produced without distillation whereas whisky, brandy and rum are produced by distillation of the fermented broth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first antibiotic discovered was:</text>
            <option id="A">Streptomycin</option>
            <option id="B">Penicillin</option>
            <option id="C">Tetracycline</option>
            <option id="D">Erythromycin</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Penicillin was the first antibiotic to be discovered, and it was a chance discovery by Alexander Fleming while working on Staphylococci bacteria.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Methanogens, which produce large amounts of methane along with CO2 and H2, are commonly found in:</text>
            <option id="A">Aerobic sludge</option>
            <option id="B">Rumen of cattle</option>
            <option id="C">River water</option>
            <option id="D">Sandy soil</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Methanogens are commonly found in the anaerobic sludge during sewage treatment. These bacteria are also present in the rumen (a part of stomach) of cattle, where they help in the breakdown of cellulose.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which bacterium is responsible for turning milk into curd?</text>
            <option id="A">Lactobacillus</option>
            <option id="B">Acetobacter</option>
            <option id="C">Streptococcus</option>
            <option id="D">Rhizobium</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Micro-organisms such as Lactobacillus and others commonly called lactic acid bacteria (LAB) grow in milk and convert it to curd.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The large holes in 'Swiss cheese' are due to the production of a large amount of CO2 by which bacterium?</text>
            <option id="A">Propionibacterium sharmanii</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="C">Penicillium roqueforti</option>
            <option id="D">Clostridium butylicum</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The large holes in 'Swiss cheese' are due to production of a large amount of CO2 by a bacterium named Propionibacterium sharmanii.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following organic acids is produced by the fungus Aspergillus niger?</text>
            <option id="A">Acetic acid</option>
            <option id="B">Lactic acid</option>
            <option id="C">Citric acid</option>
            <option id="D">Butyric acid</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Aspergillus niger (a fungus) is used for the commercial production of citric acid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following describes the role of Lactic Acid Bacteria (LAB) in milk?</text>
            <option id="A">They convert milk proteins into carbohydrates.</option>
            <option id="B">They produce acids that coagulate and partially digest the milk proteins.</option>
            <option id="C">They decrease the nutritional quality of milk.</option>
            <option id="D">They inhibit the absorption of Vitamin B12.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>During growth, the LAB produce acids that coagulate and partially digest the milk proteins. A small amount of curd added to the fresh milk as inoculum contains millions of LAB, which at suitable temperatures multiply, thus converting milk to curd.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the scientific name of the baker's yeast used for fermenting dough?</text>
            <option id="A">Propionibacterium sharmanii</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="C">Lactobacillus acidophilus</option>
            <option id="D">Acetobacter aceti</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The dough, which is used for making bread, is fermented using baker's yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae). The puffed-up appearance of dough is due to the production of CO2 gas.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Roquefort cheese is ripened by growing a specific organism on it, which gives it a particular flavour. Which organism is used?</text>
            <option id="A">A specific bacterium</option>
            <option id="B">A specific yeast</option>
            <option id="C">A specific fungi</option>
            <option id="D">A specific protozoan</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The 'Roquefort cheese' are ripened by growing a specific fungi (Penicillium roqueforti) on them, which gives them a particular flavour.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which bacterium is responsible for the production of 'Swiss cheese', characterized by its large holes?</text>
            <option id="A">Lactobacillus acidophilus</option>
            <option id="B">Propionibacterium sharmanii</option>
            <option id="C">Streptococcus thermophilus</option>
            <option id="D">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The large holes in 'Swiss cheese' are due to production of a large amount of CO2 by a bacterium named Propionibacterium sharmanii.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Roquefort cheese owes its specific flavour to which of the following?</text>
            <option id="A">A specific bacterium</option>
            <option id="B">A specific fungus</option>
            <option id="C">A specific virus</option>
            <option id="D">Added artificial flavouring</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The 'Roquefort cheese' are ripened by growing a specific fungi on them, which gives them a particular flavour.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which yeast is commonly known as 'brewer's yeast' and is used for fermenting malted cereals and fruit juices to produce ethanol?</text>
            <option id="A">Candida albicans</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="C">Penicillium notatum</option>
            <option id="D">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Saccharomyces cerevisiae, used for bread-making and commonly called brewer's yeast, is used for fermenting malted cereals and fruit juices, to produce ethanol.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following statements about baculoviruses is INCORRECT?</text>
            <option id="A">They are pathogens that attack insects and other arthropods</option>
            <option id="B">The majority of them used as biological control agents are in the genus Nucleopolyhedrovirus</option>
            <option id="C">They have a broad-spectrum insecticidal application</option>
            <option id="D">They have no negative impacts on plants, mammals, birds, fish or even non-target insects</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Baculoviruses are pathogens that attack insects and other arthropods. The majority of baculoviruses used as biological control agents are in the genus Nucleopolyhedrovirus. These viruses are excellent candidates for species-specific, narrow spectrum insecticidal applications.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Microbes that enrich the nutrient quality of the soil are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Biofertilizers</option>
            <option id="B">Biopesticides</option>
            <option id="C">Weedicides</option>
            <option id="D">Pathogens</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Biofertilisers are organisms that enrich the nutrient quality of the soil. The main sources of biofertilisers are bacteria, fungi and cyanobacteria.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Rhizobium bacteria form a symbiotic association with the roots of which plants?</text>
            <option id="A">Cereals</option>
            <option id="B">Leguminous plants</option>
            <option id="C">Gymnosperms</option>
            <option id="D">Ferns</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The nodules on the roots of leguminous plants formed by the symbiotic association of Rhizobium. These bacteria fix atmospheric nitrogen into organic forms, which is used by the plant as nutrient.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following describes the role of the bacterium Lactobacillus in human households?</text>
            <option id="A">It converts milk to curd and improves its nutritional quality by increasing vitamin B12</option>
            <option id="B">It is used to ferment fruit juices into wine</option>
            <option id="C">It produces large quantities of carbon dioxide in bread-making</option>
            <option id="D">It is used to ripen Swiss cheese</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Micro-organisms such as Lactobacillus and others commonly called lactic acid bacteria (LAB) grow in milk and convert it to curd. During growth, the LAB produce acids that coagulate and partially digest the milk proteins. It also improves its nutritional quality by increasing vitamin B12.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The puffed-up appearance of dough used for making bread is due to the production of CO2 gas by which organism?</text>
            <option id="A">Lactobacillus acidophilus</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="C">Propionibacterium sharmanii</option>
            <option id="D">Penicillium roqueforti</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Similarly, the dough, which is used for making bread, is fermented using baker's yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae). The puffed-up appearance of dough is due to the production of CO2 gas.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The large holes in 'Swiss cheese' are due to the production of a large amount of CO2 by the bacterium:</text>
            <option id="A">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="B">Propionibacterium sharmanii</option>
            <option id="C">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <option id="D">Acetobacter aceti</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The large holes in 'Swiss cheese' are due to production of a large amount of CO2 by a bacterium named Propionibacterium sharmanii. The 'Roquefort cheese' are ripened by growing a specific fungi on them.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Microbes are present everywhere. Which of the following environments can they NOT be found in?</text>
            <option id="A">Deep inside thermal vents</option>
            <option id="B">Under layers of snow</option>
            <option id="C">Highly acidic environments</option>
            <option id="D">Microbes can be found in all of these environments</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Microbes are present everywhere – in soil, water, air, inside our bodies and that of other animals and plants. They are present even at sites where no other life-form could possibly exist– sites such as deep inside the geysers (thermal vents) where the temperature may be as high as 1000C, deep in the soil, under the layers of snow several metres thick, and in highly acidic environments.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is not a microbe?</text>
            <option id="A">Protozoa</option>
            <option id="B">Bacteria</option>
            <option id="C">Viruses</option>
            <option id="D">Plants</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Microbes are diverse–protozoa, bacteria, fungi and microscopic animal and plant viruses, viroids and also prions that are proteinacious infectious agents.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the purpose of growing microbes like bacteria and many fungi on nutritive media in laboratories?</text>
            <option id="A">To make them visible to the naked eye for study</option>
            <option id="B">To increase their pathogenicity</option>
            <option id="C">To make them sterile</option>
            <option id="D">To extract their DNA only</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Microbes like bacteria and many fungi can be grown on nutritive media to form colonies, that can be seen with the naked eyes. Such cultures are useful in studies on micro-organisms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which traditional drink of some parts of southern India is made by fermenting sap from palms?</text>
            <option id="A">Feni</option>
            <option id="B">Toddy</option>
            <option id="C">Arrack</option>
            <option id="D">Kefir</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A number of traditional drinks and foods are also made by fermentation by the microbes. 'Toddy', a traditional drink of some parts of southern India is made by fermenting sap from palms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Microbes are also used to ferment fish, soyabean, and bamboo-shoots to make:</text>
            <option id="A">Antibiotics</option>
            <option id="B">Foods</option>
            <option id="C">Biofertilizers</option>
            <option id="D">Biogas</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Microbes are also used to ferment fish, soyabean and bamboo-shoots to make foods.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cheese, one of the oldest food items in which microbes were used, gets its characteristic texture, flavor, and taste from:</text>
            <option id="A">The specific microbe used</option>
            <option id="B">The temperature of fermentation</option>
            <option id="C">The type of milk used (cow vs. goat)</option>
            <option id="D">The amount of salt added</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Cheese, is one of the oldest food items in which microbes were used. Different varieties of cheese are known by their characteristic texture, flavour and taste, the specificity coming from the microbes used.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The first antibiotic discovered was Penicillin. Who discovered it?</text>
            <option id="A">Howard Florey</option>
            <option id="B">Ernest Chain</option>
            <option id="C">Alexander Fleming</option>
            <option id="D">Louis Pasteur</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Penicillin was the first antibiotic to be discovered, and it was a chance discovery. Alexander Fleming while working on Staphylococci bacteria, once observed a mould growing in one of his unwashed culture plates around which Staphylococci could not grow.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Penicillin was discovered from a mould (fungus). What was the name of this mould?</text>
            <option id="A">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <option id="B">Penicillium notatum</option>
            <option id="C">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="D">Trichoderma polysporum</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>He found out that it was due to a chemical produced by the mould and he named it Penicillin after the mould Penicillium notatum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who established the full potential of Penicillin as an effective antibiotic, which was later extensively used to treat American soldiers in World War II?</text>
            <option id="A">Alexander Fleming</option>
            <option id="B">Ernest Chain and Howard Florey</option>
            <option id="C">James Watson and Francis Crick</option>
            <option id="D">Robert Koch</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>However, its full potential as an effective antibiotic was established much later by Ernest Chain and Howard Florey. This antibiotic was extensively used to treat American soldiers wounded in World War II.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which microbe is used to produce streptokinase, a modified enzyme used as a 'clot buster'?</text>
            <option id="A">Staphylococcus</option>
            <option id="B">Streptococcus</option>
            <option id="C">Saccharomyces</option>
            <option id="D">Streptomyces</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Streptokinase produced by the bacterium Streptococcus and modified by genetic engineering is used as a 'clot buster' for removing clots from the blood vessels of patients who have undergone myocardial infarction leading to heart attack.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the medical use of the enzyme streptokinase?</text>
            <option id="A">To lower blood cholesterol</option>
            <option id="B">As an immunosuppressive agent</option>
            <option id="C">As a 'clot buster' to remove clots from blood vessels</option>
            <option id="D">To aid in digestion</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Streptokinase produced by the bacterium Streptococcus and modified by genetic engineering is used as a 'clot buster' for removing clots from the blood vessels of patients who have undergone myocardial infarction leading to heart attack.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cyclosporin A is a bioactive molecule used as an immunosuppressive agent in organ-transplant patients. Which microbe produces it?</text>
            <option id="A">Monascus purpureus</option>
            <option id="B">Trichoderma polysporum</option>
            <option id="C">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <option id="D">Penicillium notatum</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Another bioactive molecule, cyclosporin A, that is used as an immunosuppressive agent in organ-transplant patients, is produced by the fungus Trichoderma polysporum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During secondary sewage treatment, the primary effluent is passed into large aeration tanks. What happens in these tanks?</text>
            <option id="A">Chemicals are added to kill all microbes</option>
            <option id="B">The effluent is heated to boiling point</option>
            <option id="C">The effluent is constantly agitated mechanically and air is pumped into it</option>
            <option id="D">The effluent is kept completely still in anaerobic conditions</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Secondary treatment or Biological treatment: The primary effluent is passed into large aeration tanks where it is constantly agitated mechanically and air is pumped into it.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the aeration tanks of secondary treatment, vigorous growth of useful aerobic microbes forms 'flocs'. What are flocs?</text>
            <option id="A">Solid inorganic waste</option>
            <option id="B">Masses of bacteria associated with fungal filaments to form mesh-like structures</option>
            <option id="C">Floating plastic debris</option>
            <option id="D">Chemical coagulants</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>This allows vigorous growth of useful aerobic microbes into flocs (masses of bacteria associated with fungal filaments to form mesh like structures).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>While growing in the aeration tanks, what do the microbial flocs consume from the effluent?</text>
            <option id="A">Heavy metals</option>
            <option id="B">The major part of the organic matter</option>
            <option id="C">Dissolved oxygen only</option>
            <option id="D">Inorganic salts</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>While growing, these microbes consume the major part of the organic matter in the effluent. This significantly reduces the BOD (biochemical oxygen demand) of the effluent.</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>Cyclosporin A, used as an immunosuppressive agent in organ-transplant patients, is produced by the fungus:</text>
            <option id="A">Monascus purpureus</option>
            <option id="B">Trichoderma polysporum</option>
            <option id="C">Penicillium notatum</option>
            <option id="D">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Cyclosporin A is produced by the fungus Trichoderma polysporum. It is heavily used as an immunosuppressive agent in organ-transplant patients.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Statins, which are used as blood-cholesterol lowering agents, are produced by:</text>
            <option id="A">A bacterium</option>
            <option id="B">A virus</option>
            <option id="C">A yeast</option>
            <option id="D">A protozoan</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Statins are produced by the yeast Monascus purpureus. They act by competitively inhibiting the enzyme responsible for synthesis of cholesterol.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During sewage treatment, 'flocs' refer to:</text>
            <option id="A">Primary sludge settled at the bottom</option>
            <option id="B">Masses of bacteria associated with fungal filaments to form mesh-like structures</option>
            <option id="C">Anaerobic bacteria degrading organic matter</option>
            <option id="D">Biogas produced in the digestor</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>During secondary treatment, vigorous growth of useful aerobic microbes takes place into flocs, which are masses of bacteria associated with fungal filaments to form mesh like structures.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following serves as an important biofertilizer in paddy fields?</text>
            <option id="A">Rhizobium</option>
            <option id="B">Azotobacter</option>
            <option id="C">Cyanobacteria</option>
            <option id="D">Mycorrhiza</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Cyanobacteria (like Anabaena, Nostoc, Oscillatoria) are autotrophic microbes widely distributed in aquatic and terrestrial environments, many of which can fix atmospheric nitrogen. In paddy fields, cyanobacteria serve as an important biofertilizer.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The dough, which is used for making bread, is fermented by using baker's yeast, which is scientifically known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="B">Lactobacillus acidophilus</option>
            <option id="C">Streptococcus lactis</option>
            <option id="D">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The dough, which is used for making bread, is fermented using baker's yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Mycorrhiza is a symbiotic association between:</text>
            <option id="A">Bacteria and roots of higher plants</option>
            <option id="B">Fungi and roots of higher plants</option>
            <option id="C">Algae and fungi</option>
            <option id="D">Cyanobacteria and ferns</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Fungi are also known to form symbiotic associations with plants (mycorrhiza). Many members of the genus Glomus form mycorrhiza, which help in absorbing phosphorus from the soil and pass it to the plant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Biogas is a mixture of gases containing predominantly:</text>
            <option id="A">Methane</option>
            <option id="B">Carbon dioxide</option>
            <option id="C">Hydrogen sulphide</option>
            <option id="D">Carbon monoxide</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Biogas is a mixture of gases (containing predominantly methane) produced by the microbial activity and which may be used as fuel.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the role of microbes in the production of toddy?</text>
            <option id="A">Fermentation of sap from palms</option>
            <option id="B">Distillation of fruit juices</option>
            <option id="C">Pasteurization of milk</option>
            <option id="D">Maturation of cheese</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>'Toddy', a traditional drink of some parts of southern India, is made by fermenting sap from palms using microbes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which bioactive molecule is used as an immunosuppressive agent in organ-transplant patients?</text>
            <option id="A">Statins</option>
            <option id="B">Cyclosporin A</option>
            <option id="C">Streptokinase</option>
            <option id="D">Penicillin</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Cyclosporin A, produced by the fungus Trichoderma polysporum, is used as an immunosuppressive agent in organ-transplant patients.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Statins, used as blood-cholesterol lowering agents, are produced by which of the following?</text>
            <option id="A">A bacterium</option>
            <option id="B">A virus</option>
            <option id="C">A yeast</option>
            <option id="D">A protozoan</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Statins are produced by the yeast Monascus purpureus and have been commercialised as blood-cholesterol lowering agents.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In sewage treatment, BOD refers to the amount of oxygen that would be consumed if all the organic matter in one liter of water were oxidized by bacteria. What does BOD stand for?</text>
            <option id="A">Biological Oxygen Demand</option>
            <option id="B">Biochemical Oxygen Demand</option>
            <option id="C">Bacterial Oxygen Dissipation</option>
            <option id="D">Biomass Oxidation Demand</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>BOD refers to Biochemical Oxygen Demand. It is a measure of the organic matter present in the water.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During secondary treatment of sewage, what is the 'floc'?</text>
            <option id="A">Masses of bacteria associated with fungal filaments to form mesh like structures</option>
            <option id="B">Large solid particles that settle at the bottom</option>
            <option id="C">The floating debris removed during primary treatment</option>
            <option id="D">Anaerobic bacteria that produce methane</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>During secondary treatment, vigorous growth of useful aerobic microbes into flocs takes place. Flocs are masses of bacteria associated with fungal filaments to form mesh like structures.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Penicillin was the first antibiotic to be discovered, and it was a chance discovery. Who discovered Penicillin?</text>
            <option id="A">Howard Florey</option>
            <option id="B">Ernest Chain</option>
            <option id="C">Alexander Fleming</option>
            <option id="D">Louis Pasteur</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Alexander Fleming while working on Staphylococci bacteria, once observed a mould growing in one of his unwashed culture plates around which Staphylococci could not grow. He found out that it was due to a chemical produced by the mould and he named it Penicillin after the mould Penicillium notatum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Who among the following scientists established the full potential of Penicillin as an effective antibiotic, leading to their shared Nobel Prize with Alexander Fleming in 1945?</text>
            <option id="A">Watson and Crick</option>
            <option id="B">Ernest Chain and Howard Florey</option>
            <option id="C">Jacob and Monod</option>
            <option id="D">Hershey and Chase</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>However, its full potential as an effective antibiotic was established much later by Ernest Chain and Howard Florey. This antibiotic was extensively used to treat American soldiers wounded in World War II. Fleming, Chain and Florey were awarded the Nobel Prize in 1945.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which enzyme is used as a 'clot buster' for removing clots from the blood vessels of patients who have undergone myocardial infarction?</text>
            <option id="A">Lipase</option>
            <option id="B">Streptokinase</option>
            <option id="C">Protease</option>
            <option id="D">Pectinase</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Streptokinase produced by the bacterium Streptococcus and modified by genetic engineering is used as a 'clot buster' for removing clots from the blood vessels of patients who have undergone myocardial infarction leading to heart attack.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Lipases are commonly used in which of the following everyday products?</text>
            <option id="A">Detergent formulations</option>
            <option id="B">Bottled fruit juices to clear them</option>
            <option id="C">Cheese making</option>
            <option id="D">Bread making</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Lipases are used in detergent formulations and are helpful in removing oily stains from the laundry. (Proteases and pectinases are used to clear bottled fruit juices).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following alcoholic drinks are produced without distillation?</text>
            <option id="A">Wine and beer</option>
            <option id="B">Whisky and brandy</option>
            <option id="C">Rum and vodka</option>
            <option id="D">Gin and tequila</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Wine and beer are produced without distillation whereas whisky, brandy and rum are produced by distillation of the fermented broth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Alexander Fleming discovered Penicillin while working on which bacterium?</text>
            <option id="A">Streptococcus pneumoniae</option>
            <option id="B">Staphylococcus</option>
            <option id="C">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</option>
            <option id="D">Escherichia coli</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Alexander Fleming while working on Staphylococci bacteria, once observed a mould growing in one of his unwashed culture plates around which Staphylococci could not grow. He found out that it was due to a chemical produced by the mould and he named it Penicillin after the mould Penicillium notatum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which microbe is used for the commercial production of citric acid?</text>
            <option id="A">Aspergillus niger (a fungus)</option>
            <option id="B">Acetobacter aceti (a bacterium)</option>
            <option id="C">Clostridium butylicum (a bacterium)</option>
            <option id="D">Lactobacillus (a bacterium)</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Aspergillus niger (a fungus) is used for the production of citric acid. Acetobacter aceti is used for acetic acid, Clostridium butylicum for butyric acid, and Lactobacillus for lactic acid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Statins, produced by the yeast Monascus purpureus, are used as:</text>
            <option id="A">Clot busters</option>
            <option id="B">Immunosuppressive agents</option>
            <option id="C">Blood-cholesterol lowering agents</option>
            <option id="D">Antibiotics</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Statins produced by the yeast Monascus purpureus have been commercialised as blood-cholesterol lowering agents. It acts by competitively inhibiting the enzyme responsible for synthesis of cholesterol.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following are free-living, nitrogen-fixing bacteria in the soil?</text>
            <option id="A">Rhizobium and Frankia</option>
            <option id="B">Azospirillum and Azotobacter</option>
            <option id="C">Glomus and Trichoderma</option>
            <option id="D">Streptococcus and Staphylococcus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Other bacteria can fix atmospheric nitrogen while free-living in the soil (examples Azospirillum and Azotobacter), thus enriching the nitrogen content of the soil.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Many members of the genus Glomus form mycorrhiza. What role do they play in this symbiotic association?</text>
            <option id="A">They fix atmospheric nitrogen</option>
            <option id="B">They absorb phosphorus from soil and pass it to the plant</option>
            <option id="C">They protect the plant from viral diseases</option>
            <option id="D">They perform photosynthesis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Fungi are also known to form symbiotic associations with plants (mycorrhiza). Many members of the genus Glomus form mycorrhiza. The fungal symbiont in these associations absorbs phosphorus from soil and passes it to the plant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cyanobacteria are autotrophic microbes widely distributed in aquatic and terrestrial environments. Which of the following is NOT a nitrogen-fixing cyanobacterium?</text>
            <option id="A">Anabaena</option>
            <option id="B">Nostoc</option>
            <option id="C">Oscillatoria</option>
            <option id="D">Aspergillus</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Cyanobacteria are autotrophic microbes widely distributed in aquatic and terrestrial environments many of which can fix atmospheric nitrogen, e.g. Anabaena, Nostoc, Oscillatoria, etc. Aspergillus is a fungus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which biofertilizer serves as an important primary nitrogen fixer in paddy fields?</text>
            <option id="A">Rhizobium</option>
            <option id="B">Cyanobacteria</option>
            <option id="C">Mycorrhiza</option>
            <option id="D">Azotobacter</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In paddy fields, cyanobacteria serve as an important biofertiliser. Blue green algae also add organic matter to the soil and increase its fertility.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following organic acids is produced by the fungus Aspergillus niger?</text>
            <option id="A">Acetic acid</option>
            <option id="B">Lactic acid</option>
            <option id="C">Citric acid</option>
            <option id="D">Butyric acid</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Microbes are also used for commercial and industrial production of certain chemicals like organic acids, alcohols and enzymes. Examples of acid producers are Aspergillus niger (a fungus) of citric acid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Acetobacter aceti, a bacterium, is commercially used for the production of:</text>
            <option id="A">Citric acid</option>
            <option id="B">Acetic acid</option>
            <option id="C">Butyric acid</option>
            <option id="D">Lactic acid</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Acetobacter aceti (a bacterium) is used for the production of acetic acid; Clostridium butylicum (a bacterium) for butyric acid and Lactobacillus (a bacterium) for lactic acid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which enzymes are used in detergent formulations and are helpful in removing oily stains from the laundry?</text>
            <option id="A">Amylases</option>
            <option id="B">Proteases</option>
            <option id="C">Lipases</option>
            <option id="D">Pectinases</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Lipases are used in detergent formulations and are helpful in removing oily stains from the laundry.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The bottled fruit juices bought from the market are clearer than those made at home because they are clarified by the use of:</text>
            <option id="A">Lipases and Proteases</option>
            <option id="B">Pectinases and Proteases</option>
            <option id="C">Amylases and Pectinases</option>
            <option id="D">Streptokinase</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>You must have noticed that bottled fruit juices bought from the market are clearer as compared to those made at home. This is because the bottled juices are clarified by the use of pectinases and proteases.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A common example of the use of microbes in household products is the production of curd from milk. Which microorganism is primarily responsible for this?</text>
            <option id="A">Lactobacillus</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="C">Propionibacterium sharmanii</option>
            <option id="D">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Micro-organisms such as Lactobacillus and others commonly called lactic acid bacteria (LAB) grow in milk and convert it to curd.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During growth, Lactic Acid Bacteria (LAB) produce acids that do what to milk?</text>
            <option id="A">Coagulate and partially digest the milk proteins</option>
            <option id="B">Ferment the lactose into alcohol</option>
            <option id="C">Break down the fats into fatty acids</option>
            <option id="D">Increase the pH of the milk</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>During growth, the LAB produce acids that coagulate and partially digest the milk proteins.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the function of the 'inoculum' or 'starter' added to fresh milk when making curd?</text>
            <option id="A">To add flavor to the curd</option>
            <option id="B">To act as a preservative</option>
            <option id="C">To provide millions of LAB that multiply at suitable temperatures</option>
            <option id="D">To break down vitamins</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>A small amount of curd added to the fresh milk as inoculum or starter contain millions of LAB, which at suitable temperatures multiply, thus converting milk to curd.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Apart from converting milk to curd, Lactic Acid Bacteria (LAB) also improve its nutritional quality by increasing the content of:</text>
            <option id="A">Vitamin A</option>
            <option id="B">Vitamin B12</option>
            <option id="C">Vitamin C</option>
            <option id="D">Vitamin D</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>LAB also improves its nutritional quality by increasing vitamin B12.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The large holes in 'Swiss cheese' are due to the production of a large amount of CO2 by which bacterium?</text>
            <option id="A">Lactobacillus acidophilus</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="C">Propionibacterium sharmanii</option>
            <option id="D">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>For example, the large holes in 'Swiss cheese' are due to production of a large amount of CO2 by a bacterium named Propionibacterium sharmanii.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The 'Roquefort cheese' is ripened by growing a specific what on them, which gives them a particular flavour?</text>
            <option id="A">Bacterium</option>
            <option id="B">Virus</option>
            <option id="C">Fungi</option>
            <option id="D">Protozoan</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The 'Roquefort cheese' are ripened by growing a specific fungi on them, which gives them a particular flavour.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Even in industry, microbes are used to synthesise a number of products valuable to human beings. Production on an industrial scale requires growing microbes in very large vessels called:</text>
            <option id="A">Petri dishes</option>
            <option id="B">Fermentors</option>
            <option id="C">Autoclaves</option>
            <option id="D">Incubators</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Even in industry, microbes are used to synthesise a number of products valuable to human beings. Beverages and antibiotics are some examples. Production on an industrial scale, requires growing microbes in very large vessels called fermentors.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>For time immemorial, which microbe has been used for the production of beverages like wine, beer, whisky, brandy, or rum?</text>
            <option id="A">Lactobacillus</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharomyces cerevisiae (Yeast)</option>
            <option id="C">Penicillium notatum</option>
            <option id="D">Streptococcus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Microbes especially yeasts have been used from time immemorial for the production of beverages like wine, beer, whisky, brandy or rum. For this purpose the same yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae used for bread-making and commonly called brewer's yeast, is used for fermenting malted cereals and fruit juices, to produce ethanol.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which three scientists were awarded the Nobel Prize in 1945 for the discovery and development of Penicillin?</text>
            <option id="A">Fleming, Chain, and Florey</option>
            <option id="B">Watson, Crick, and Wilkins</option>
            <option id="C">Pasteur, Koch, and Lister</option>
            <option id="D">Jacob, Monod, and Lwoff</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Fleming, Chain and Florey were awarded the Nobel Prize in 1945, for this discovery.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Microbes are used for commercial and industrial production of certain chemicals like organic acids. Which microbe is used to produce citric acid?</text>
            <option id="A">Acetobacter aceti</option>
            <option id="B">Clostridium butylicum</option>
            <option id="C">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <option id="D">Lactobacillus</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Microbes are also used for commercial and industrial production of certain chemicals like organic acids, alcohols and enzymes. Examples of acid producers are Aspergillus niger (a fungus) of citric acid, Acetobacter aceti (a bacterium) of acetic acid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which microbe is responsible for the production of acetic acid (vinegar)?</text>
            <option id="A">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <option id="B">Acetobacter aceti</option>
            <option id="C">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="D">Clostridium butylicum</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Acetobacter aceti (a bacterium) of acetic acid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Clostridium butylicum, a bacterium, is used for the production of which organic acid?</text>
            <option id="A">Citric acid</option>
            <option id="B">Acetic acid</option>
            <option id="C">Butyric acid</option>
            <option id="D">Lactic acid</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Clostridium butylicum (a bacterium) of butyric acid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the medical application of Cyclosporin A?</text>
            <option id="A">It is used as a clot buster</option>
            <option id="B">It is used to lower blood cholesterol</option>
            <option id="C">It is used as an immunosuppressive agent in organ-transplant patients</option>
            <option id="D">It is used as a broad-spectrum antibiotic</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Another bioactive molecule, cyclosporin A, that is used as an immunosuppressive agent in organ-transplant patients, is produced by the fungus Trichoderma polysporum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Statins, which are used as blood-cholesterol lowering agents, are produced by which microbe?</text>
            <option id="A">Streptococcus bacteria</option>
            <option id="B">Monascus purpureus yeast</option>
            <option id="C">Trichoderma polysporum fungus</option>
            <option id="D">Acetobacter aceti bacteria</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Statins produced by the yeast Monascus purpureus have been commercialised as blood-cholesterol lowering agents.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How do statins function to lower blood cholesterol levels?</text>
            <option id="A">By destroying cholesterol in the blood</option>
            <option id="B">By preventing the absorption of cholesterol in the intestine</option>
            <option id="C">By acting as a competitive inhibitor of the enzyme responsible for synthesis of cholesterol</option>
            <option id="D">By converting cholesterol into bile acids</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Statins produced by the yeast Monascus purpureus have been commercialised as blood-cholesterol lowering agents. It acts by competitively inhibiting the enzyme responsible for synthesis of cholesterol.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Sewage is treated in sewage treatment plants (STPs) before disposal. This treatment is carried out by heterotrophic microbes naturally present in the sewage. What is the primary purpose of the primary treatment?</text>
            <option id="A">Biological removal of dissolved organic matter</option>
            <option id="B">Physical removal of particles (large and small) through filtration and sedimentation</option>
            <option id="C">Chemical disinfection using chlorine</option>
            <option id="D">Anaerobic digestion of sludge</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Primary treatment: These treatment steps basically involve physical removal of particles – large and small – from the sewage through filtration and sedimentation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What does BOD stand for in the context of sewage treatment?</text>
            <option id="A">Biological Organism Death</option>
            <option id="B">Biochemical Oxygen Demand</option>
            <option id="C">Basic Oxygen Depletion</option>
            <option id="D">Bacterial Oxidation Degradation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>This significantly reduces the BOD (biochemical oxygen demand) of the effluent.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What does BOD essentially measure?</text>
            <option id="A">The amount of oxygen consumed if all organic matter in one liter of water were oxidized by bacteria</option>
            <option id="B">The total number of bacteria in one liter of water</option>
            <option id="C">The amount of inorganic salts in the water</option>
            <option id="D">The physical clarity of the water</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>BOD refers to the amount of the oxygen that would be consumed if all the organic matter in one liter of water were oxidised by bacteria.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How is the BOD of a wastewater sample related to its polluting potential?</text>
            <option id="A">The greater the BOD, the less its polluting potential</option>
            <option id="B">The greater the BOD, the more is its polluting potential</option>
            <option id="C">BOD has no relation to polluting potential</option>
            <option id="D">Only zero BOD indicates pollution</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The BOD test measures the rate of uptake of oxygen by micro-organisms in a sample of water and thus, indirectly, BOD is a measure of the organic matter present in the water. The greater the BOD of waste water, more is its polluting potential.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Once the BOD of sewage is reduced significantly during secondary treatment, the effluent is passed into a settling tank. What happens to the bacterial 'flocs' here?</text>
            <option id="A">They rise to the top as scum</option>
            <option id="B">They are evaporated</option>
            <option id="C">They are allowed to sediment</option>
            <option id="D">They are chemically dissolved</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Once the BOD of sewage or waste water is reduced significantly, the effluent is then passed into a settling tank where the bacterial 'flocs' are allowed to sediment.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is TRUE about the virus belonging to the genus Nucleopolyhedrovirus?</text>
            <option id="A">They have broad-spectrum insecticidal applications.</option>
            <option id="B">They are excellent candidates for species-specific, narrow spectrum insecticidal applications.</option>
            <option id="C">They have severe negative impacts on plants and non-target insects.</option>
            <option id="D">They are used primarily to control fungal pathogens on plant roots.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Baculoviruses (genus Nucleopolyhedrovirus) are excellent candidates for species-specific, narrow spectrum insecticidal applications. They have been shown to have no negative impacts on plants, mammals, birds, fish or even on non-target insects.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During the secondary treatment of sewage, what is the role of the anaerobic sludge digester?</text>
            <option id="A">To rapidly multiply aerobic bacteria and reduce BOD.</option>
            <option id="B">To digest the activated sludge and produce biogas.</option>
            <option id="C">To physically filter out large debris like plastic and wood.</option>
            <option id="D">To add chlorine and UV light to disinfect the water.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In the anaerobic sludge digester, anaerobic bacteria grow and digest the aerobic bacteria and the fungi in the sludge. During this digestion, a mixture of gases such as methane, hydrogen sulphide and carbon dioxide are produced, forming biogas.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The enzyme 'Streptokinase' produced by the bacterium Streptococcus and modified by genetic engineering is used as a:</text>
            <option id="A">Clot buster</option>
            <option id="B">Cholesterol lowering agent</option>
            <option id="C">Immunosuppressive agent</option>
            <option id="D">Blood thinner to prevent platelet aggregation</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Streptokinase produced by the bacterium Streptococcus and modified by genetic engineering is used as a 'clot buster' for removing clots from the blood vessels of patients who have undergone myocardial infarction leading to heart attack.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following acts as a biofertilizer by fixing atmospheric nitrogen both in free-living state and in symbiotic association?</text>
            <option id="A">Rhizobium</option>
            <option id="B">Anabaena</option>
            <option id="C">Azotobacter</option>
            <option id="D">Glomus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Cyanobacteria like Anabaena can fix atmospheric nitrogen in free-living state (in soil/water) and also symbiotically (e.g., in the leaves of Azolla or coralloid roots of Cycas).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Baculoviruses are pathogens that attack insects and other arthropods. They are primarily used as:</text>
            <option id="A">Chemical fertilizers</option>
            <option id="B">Biological control agents</option>
            <option id="C">Vectors in genetic engineering of plants</option>
            <option id="D">Antibiotics</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Baculoviruses are pathogens that attack insects and other arthropods. The majority of baculoviruses used as biological control agents are in the genus Nucleopolyhedrovirus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of primary treatment of sewage involves:</text>
            <option id="A">Sequential filtration and sedimentation</option>
            <option id="B">Aeration and microbial digestion</option>
            <option id="C">Chlorination and UV treatment</option>
            <option id="D">Anaerobic digestion of sludge</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Primary treatment basically involves physical removal of particles - large and small - from the sewage through filtration and sedimentation. Initially, floating debris is removed by sequential filtration.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The free-living fungus Trichoderma is very common in root ecosystems and is used as:</text>
            <option id="A">An antibiotic</option>
            <option id="B">A biofertilizer</option>
            <option id="C">A biocontrol agent for several plant pathogens</option>
            <option id="D">A source of single-cell protein</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>A biological control being developed for use in the treatment of plant disease is the fungus Trichoderma. Trichoderma species are free-living fungi that are very common in the root ecosystems. They are effective biocontrol agents of several plant pathogens.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following microbes is used in the commercial production of butyric acid?</text>
            <option id="A">Acetobacter aceti</option>
            <option id="B">Clostridium butylicum</option>
            <option id="C">Lactobacillus</option>
            <option id="D">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Clostridium butylicum (a bacterium) is used for the production of butyric acid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Baculoviruses belong to the genus Nucleopolyhedrovirus and are excellent candidates for species-specific, narrow spectrum insecticidal applications. What is their effect on non-target organisms?</text>
            <option id="A">They kill all insects indiscriminately.</option>
            <option id="B">They are toxic to plants.</option>
            <option id="C">They have no negative impacts on plants, mammals, birds, fish or even on non-target insects.</option>
            <option id="D">They cause diseases in humans.</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Baculoviruses are excellent candidates for species-specific, narrow spectrum insecticidal applications. They have been shown to have no negative impacts on plants, mammals, birds, fish or even on non-target insects. This is especially desirable when beneficial insects are being conserved.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During primary treatment of sewage, how is the grit (soil and small pebbles) removed?</text>
            <option id="A">By sequential filtration</option>
            <option id="B">By anaerobic digestion</option>
            <option id="C">By sedimentation</option>
            <option id="D">By biological flocs</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Primary treatment basically involves physical removal of particles. Initially, floating debris is removed by sequential filtration. Then the grit (soil and small pebbles) are removed by sedimentation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What constitutes the 'primary sludge' in a sewage treatment plant?</text>
            <option id="A">The floating debris removed during filtration</option>
            <option id="B">All solids that settle down after primary treatment</option>
            <option id="C">The effluent from the primary settling tank</option>
            <option id="D">The masses of bacteria formed during secondary treatment</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>All solids that settle form the primary sludge, and the supernatant forms the effluent. The effluent from the primary settling tank is taken for secondary treatment.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Once the BOD of sewage or waste water is reduced significantly during secondary treatment, the effluent is then passed into a settling tank where the bacterial 'flocs' are allowed to sediment. This sediment is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Primary sludge</option>
            <option id="B">Activated sludge</option>
            <option id="C">Anaerobic sludge</option>
            <option id="D">Biogas</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Once the BOD of sewage or waste water is reduced significantly, the effluent is then passed into a settling tank where the bacterial 'flocs' are allowed to sediment. This sediment is called activated sludge. A small part of the activated sludge is pumped back into the aeration tank to serve as the inoculum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In a sewage treatment plant, what is the purpose of primary treatment?</text>
            <option id="A">Removal of dissolved organic matter using microbes</option>
            <option id="B">Physical removal of large and small particles through filtration and sedimentation</option>
            <option id="C">Disinfection of water using chlorine or UV radiation</option>
            <option id="D">Removal of heavy metals using chemical precipitation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Primary treatment basically involves physical removal of particles - large and small - from the sewage through filtration and sedimentation. These are removed in stages; initially, floating debris is removed by sequential filtration.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During secondary treatment, what are 'flocs'?</text>
            <option id="A">Masses of bacteria associated with fungal filaments to form mesh-like structures</option>
            <option id="B">Solid waste that settles at the bottom of the primary settling tank</option>
            <option id="C">Anaerobic bacteria that produce biogas</option>
            <option id="D">Floating debris removed by sequential filtration</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>During secondary treatment, the primary effluent is passed into large aeration tanks. This allows vigorous growth of useful aerobic microbes into flocs (masses of bacteria associated with fungal filaments to form mesh-like structures).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Methanogens are bacteria that grow anaerobically on cellulosic material and produce large amounts of methane along with CO2 and H2. Which is a common example of a methanogen?</text>
            <option id="A">Rhizobium</option>
            <option id="B">Methanobacterium</option>
            <option id="C">Azotobacter</option>
            <option id="D">Bacillus thuringiensis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Certain bacteria, which grow anaerobically on cellulosic material, produce large amount of methane along with CO2 and H2. These bacteria are collectively called methanogens, and one such common bacterium is Methanobacterium.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Cyclosporin A, used as an immunosuppressive agent in organ-transplant patients, is produced by the fungus:</text>
            <option id="A">Trichoderma polysporum</option>
            <option id="B">Monascus purpureus</option>
            <option id="C">Penicillium notatum</option>
            <option id="D">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>A bioactive molecule, cyclosporin A, that is used as an immunosuppressive agent in organ-transplant patients, is produced by the fungus Trichoderma polysporum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which enzyme, produced by the bacterium Streptococcus and modified by genetic engineering, is used as a 'clot buster'?</text>
            <option id="A">Lipase</option>
            <option id="B">Protease</option>
            <option id="C">Streptokinase</option>
            <option id="D">Amylase</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Streptokinase produced by the bacterium Streptococcus and modified by genetic engineering is used as a 'clot buster' for removing clots from the blood vessels of patients who have undergone myocardial infarction leading to heart attack.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The biocontrol agent Trichoderma is a:</text>
            <option id="A">Free-living fungus that is very common in the root ecosystems</option>
            <option id="B">Bacterium that produces toxic proteins against insects</option>
            <option id="C">Virus that infects only specific insect pests</option>
            <option id="D">Protozoan that causes diseases in caterpillars</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>A biological control being developed for use in the treatment of plant disease is the fungus Trichoderma. Trichoderma species are free-living fungi that are very common in the root ecosystems. They are effective biocontrol agents of several plant pathogens.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During primary treatment of sewage, what is removed by sequential filtration and sedimentation?</text>
            <option id="A">Dissolved organic matter</option>
            <option id="B">Pathogenic bacteria</option>
            <option id="C">Floating debris and grit (soil and small pebbles)</option>
            <option id="D">Heavy metals and toxic chemicals</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Primary treatment basically involves physical removal of particles - large and small - from the sewage through filtration and sedimentation. Initially, floating debris is removed by sequential filtration. Then the grit (soil and small pebbles) are removed by sedimentation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is 'flocs' in the context of secondary sewage treatment?</text>
            <option id="A">Masses of anaerobic bacteria</option>
            <option id="B">Masses of bacteria associated with fungal filaments to form mesh-like structures</option>
            <option id="C">The solid portion of the primary sludge</option>
            <option id="D">Chemicals added to precipitate the dissolved solids</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>During secondary treatment, the primary effluent is passed into large aeration tanks where it is constantly agitated mechanically and air is pumped into it. This allows vigorous growth of useful aerobic microbes into flocs (masses of bacteria associated with fungal filaments to form mesh like structures).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Biochemical Oxygen Demand (BOD) is a measure of the organic matter present in the water. A higher BOD indicates:</text>
            <option id="A">More dissolved oxygen in the water</option>
            <option id="B">Less organic matter in the water</option>
            <option id="C">Higher polluting potential of the water</option>
            <option id="D">The water is safe for drinking</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>BOD is a measure of the organic matter present in the water. The greater the BOD of waste water, more is its polluting potential. As the BOD of the sewage or waste water is reduced significantly, the effluent is then passed into a settling tank.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What beneficial role do LAB play in the human stomach?</text>
            <option id="A">They digest cellulose</option>
            <option id="B">They check disease-causing microbes</option>
            <option id="C">They produce gastric juice</option>
            <option id="D">They absorb water</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In our stomach too, the LAB play very beneficial role in checking disease-causing microbes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The dough, which is used for making foods such as dosa and idli, is fermented by bacteria. The puffed-up appearance of dough is due to the production of:</text>
            <option id="A">Oxygen gas</option>
            <option id="B">Carbon dioxide gas</option>
            <option id="C">Methane gas</option>
            <option id="D">Nitrogen gas</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The dough, which is used for making foods such as dosa and idli is also fermented by bacteria. The puffed-up appearance of dough is due to the production of CO2 gas.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Baker's yeast, used for fermenting dough for bread making, is scientifically known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Lactobacillus acidophilus</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</option>
            <option id="C">Penicillium notatum</option>
            <option id="D">Streptococcus thermophilus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Similarly the dough, which is used for making bread, is fermented using baker's yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What does Saccharomyces cerevisiae ferment in malted cereals and fruit juices to produce ethanol?</text>
            <option id="A">Proteins</option>
            <option id="B">Sugars (Carbohydrates)</option>
            <option id="C">Fats</option>
            <option id="D">Vitamins</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>For this purpose the same yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae used for bread-making and commonly called brewer's yeast, is used for fermenting malted cereals and fruit juices, to produce ethanol.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Depending on the type of raw material used for fermentation and the type of processing, different types of alcoholic drinks are obtained. Which of the following are produced WITHOUT distillation?</text>
            <option id="A">Whisky and Brandy</option>
            <option id="B">Wine and Beer</option>
            <option id="C">Rum and Whisky</option>
            <option id="D">Brandy and Rum</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Depending on the type of the raw material used for fermentation and the type of processing (with or without distillation) different types of alcoholic drinks are obtained. Wine and beer are produced without distillation whereas whisky, brandy and rum are produced by distillation of the fermented broth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Antibiotics are chemical substances produced by some microbes. What is their function?</text>
            <option id="A">To promote the growth of other microbes</option>
            <option id="B">To kill or retard the growth of other (disease-causing) microbes</option>
            <option id="C">To provide immunity directly to humans</option>
            <option id="D">To ferment sugars into alcohol</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Antibiotics produced by microbes are regarded as one of the most significant discoveries of the twentieth century and have greatly contributed towards the welfare of the human society... 'antibiotic' literally means 'against life' (in the context of disease causing organisms)... Antibiotics are chemical substances, which are produced by some microbes and can kill or retard the growth of other (disease-causing) microbes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which microbe is extensively used for the commercial production of ethanol?</text>
            <option id="A">Lactobacillus</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharomyces cerevisiae (yeast)</option>
            <option id="C">Aspergillus niger</option>
            <option id="D">Penicillium notatum</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae) is used for commercial production of ethanol.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Microbes are also used for production of enzymes. Which enzyme, produced by microbes, is used in detergent formulations and helps in removing oily stains from the laundry?</text>
            <option id="A">Proteases</option>
            <option id="B">Pectinases</option>
            <option id="C">Lipases</option>
            <option id="D">Streptokinase</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Microbes are also used for production of enzymes. Lipases are used in detergent formulations and are helpful in removing oily stains from the laundry.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Why are bottled fruit juices bought from the market clearer than those made at home?</text>
            <option id="A">They are filtered through very fine paper</option>
            <option id="B">They are treated with boiling water</option>
            <option id="C">They are clarified by the use of pectinases and proteases</option>
            <option id="D">They contain fewer real fruit particles</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>You must have noticed that bottled fruit juices bought from the market are clearer as compared to those made at home. This is because the bottled juices are clarified by the use of pectinases and proteases.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In primary sewage treatment, how is floating debris initially removed?</text>
            <option id="A">By sedimentation</option>
            <option id="B">By anaerobic digestion</option>
            <option id="C">By sequential filtration</option>
            <option id="D">By aeration</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Initially, floating debris is removed by sequential filtration.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>After filtration in primary treatment, how are the soil and small pebbles (grit) removed?</text>
            <option id="A">By chlorination</option>
            <option id="B">By sedimentation</option>
            <option id="C">By adding flocculating chemicals</option>
            <option id="D">By heating</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Initially, floating debris is removed by sequential filtration. Then the grit (soil and small pebbles) are removed by sedimentation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>All solids that settle down during primary treatment form the primary sludge, and the supernatant forms the effluent. Where is this effluent taken next?</text>
            <option id="A">Directly into the river</option>
            <option id="B">For secondary treatment</option>
            <option id="C">To an anaerobic sludge digester</option>
            <option id="D">For chlorination</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>All solids that settle form the primary sludge, and the supernatant forms the effluent. The effluent from the primary settling tank is taken for secondary treatment.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The sedimented bacterial flocs in the settling tank of secondary treatment are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Primary sludge</option>
            <option id="B">Activated sludge</option>
            <option id="C">Anaerobic sludge</option>
            <option id="D">Effluent</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>...the effluent is then passed into a settling tank where the bacterial 'flocs' are allowed to sediment. This sediment is called activated sludge.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A small part of the activated sludge is pumped back into the aeration tank. What is its purpose there?</text>
            <option id="A">To act as food for fishes</option>
            <option id="B">To serve as the inoculum</option>
            <option id="C">To chemically clean the tank</option>
            <option id="D">To stop the aeration process</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A small part of the activated sludge is pumped back into the aeration tank to serve as the inoculum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Where is the remaining major part of the activated sludge pumped into after the settling tank?</text>
            <option id="A">Directly into the river</option>
            <option id="B">Back into the primary settling tank</option>
            <option id="C">Into large tanks called anaerobic sludge digesters</option>
            <option id="D">Onto agricultural fields immediately</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The remaining major part of the sludge is pumped into large tanks called anaerobic sludge digesters.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>