<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="335" name="Organisms and Populations">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>The process by which organisms maintain a constant internal environment despite fluctuating external environmental conditions is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Acclimatization</option>
            <option id="B">Homeostasis</option>
            <option id="C">Adaptation</option>
            <option id="D">Hibernation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Homeostasis is the process by which an organism tries to maintain the constancy of its internal environment (such as body temperature and osmotic concentration) despite varying external environmental conditions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Organisms that can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Stenothermal</option>
            <option id="B">Eurythermal</option>
            <option id="C">Poikilothermal</option>
            <option id="D">Endothermal</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A few organisms can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures; they are called eurythermal. A vast majority of them are restricted to a narrow range of temperatures and are called stenothermal.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>An interaction between two species in which one is benefited and the other is neither harmed nor benefited is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Mutualism</option>
            <option id="B">Commensalism</option>
            <option id="C">Amensalism</option>
            <option id="D">Parasitism</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Commensalism is an interaction in which one species benefits and the other is neither harmed nor benefited. Example: an orchid growing as an epiphyte on a mango branch.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following describes an adaptation where an organism resembles its background to hide from predators?</text>
            <option id="A">Mimicry</option>
            <option id="B">Camouflage</option>
            <option id="C">Aestivation</option>
            <option id="D">Hibernation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Camouflage (cryptic coloration) is an adaptation where some species of insects and frogs are cryptically-coloured to avoid being detected easily by their predators.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which age pyramid shape represents a rapidly growing population?</text>
            <option id="A">Urn-shaped</option>
            <option id="B">Bell-shaped</option>
            <option id="C">Pyramid with a broad base</option>
            <option id="D">Spindle-shaped</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>A population pyramid with a broad base represents a rapidly growing population, as it indicates a high proportion of individuals in the pre-reproductive age group.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The type of interaction where one organism catches, kills, and eats another organism is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Parasitism</option>
            <option id="B">Predation</option>
            <option id="C">Amensalism</option>
            <option id="D">Competition</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Predation is nature's way of transferring to higher trophic levels the energy fixed by plants, where one organism (predator) catches, kills, and eats another organism (prey).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The study of interactions among organisms and between the organism and its physical (abiotic) environment is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Ethology</option>
            <option id="B">Ecology</option>
            <option id="C">Evolution</option>
            <option id="D">Genetics</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Ecology is basically concerned with four levels of biological organisation - organisms, populations, communities and biomes. It is the study of interactions among organisms and between the organism and its physical environment.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an abiotic factor that heavily influences the distribution of organisms?</text>
            <option id="A">Predators</option>
            <option id="B">Parasites</option>
            <option id="C">Temperature</option>
            <option id="D">Competitors</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Temperature is the most ecologically relevant environmental factor (abiotic factor). The average temperature on land varies seasonally and influences the distribution of organisms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Organisms that can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Stenothermal</option>
            <option id="B">Eurythermal</option>
            <option id="C">Poikilothermic</option>
            <option id="D">Homeothermic</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A few organisms can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures (they are called eurythermal), but, a vast majority of them are restricted to a narrow range of temperatures (such organisms are called stenothermal).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered the most ecologically relevant environmental factor?</text>
            <option id="A">Water</option>
            <option id="B">Light</option>
            <option id="C">Temperature</option>
            <option id="D">Soil</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Temperature is the most ecologically relevant environmental factor. You are aware that the average temperature on land varies seasonally, decreases progressively from the equator towards the poles.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Organisms that can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Stenothermal</option>
            <option id="B">Eurythermal</option>
            <option id="C">Poikilothermal</option>
            <option id="D">Homeothermal</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A few organisms can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures (they are called eurythermal), but, a vast majority of them are restricted to a narrow range of temperatures (such organisms are called stenothermal).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>For aquatic organisms, the quality (chemical composition, pH) of water becomes important. The salt concentration (measured as salinity in parts per thousand), is less than 5 in inland waters, and ________ in the sea.</text>
            <option id="A">10-15</option>
            <option id="B">30-35</option>
            <option id="C">50-60</option>
            <option id="D">More than 100</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The salt concentration (measured as salinity in parts per thousand), is less than 5 in inland waters, 30-35 in the sea and > 100 in some hypersaline lagoons.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Many tribes live in the high altitude of Himalayas. They have a higher red blood cell count than people living in the plains. This is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Behavioural adaptation</option>
            <option id="B">Physiological adaptation</option>
            <option id="C">Morphological adaptation</option>
            <option id="D">Genetic drift</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>At high altitude places, the body compensates for low oxygen availability by increasing red blood cell production, decreasing the binding affinity of hemoglobin and by increasing breathing rate. Many tribes live in the high altitude of Himalayas, and they have a higher RBC count.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Desert lizards manage to keep their body temperature fairly constant by absorbing heat from the sun when their body temperature drops below the comfort zone, and moving into shade when the ambient temperature starts increasing. This is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Physiological adaptation</option>
            <option id="B">Behavioural adaptation</option>
            <option id="C">Morphological adaptation</option>
            <option id="D">Biochemical adaptation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Desert lizards lack the physiological ability that mammals have to deal with the high temperatures of their habitat, but manage to keep their body temperature fairly constant by behavioural means.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The number of births plus immigration minus the number of deaths plus emigration determines the:</text>
            <option id="A">Population density</option>
            <option id="B">Carrying capacity</option>
            <option id="C">Intrinsic rate of increase</option>
            <option id="D">Change in population size</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The density of a population in a given habitat during a given period, fluctuates due to changes in four basic processes: Natality, Mortality, Immigration, and Emigration. N(t+1) = N(t) + [(B + I) - (D + E)].</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Ecology is fundamentally concerned with how many levels of biological organisation?</text>
            <option id="A">Two (Organisms and Populations)</option>
            <option id="B">Three (Organisms, Populations, and Communities)</option>
            <option id="C">Four (Organisms, Populations, Communities, and Biomes)</option>
            <option id="D">Five (Cells, Tissues, Organs, Organisms, and Populations)</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Ecology is basically concerned with four levels of biological organisation - organisms, populations, communities and biomes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is the most ecologically relevant environmental factor?</text>
            <option id="A">Temperature</option>
            <option id="B">Water</option>
            <option id="C">Light</option>
            <option id="D">Soil</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Temperature is the most ecologically relevant environmental factor. You are aware that the average temperature on land varies seasonally, decreases progressively from the equator towards the poles and from plains to the mountain tops.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Organisms that can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Stenothermal</option>
            <option id="B">Eurythermal</option>
            <option id="C">Euryhaline</option>
            <option id="D">Stenohaline</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A few organisms can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures (they are called eurythermal), but, a vast majority of them are restricted to a narrow range of temperatures (such organisms are called stenothermal).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Ecology at the organismic level is essentially physiological ecology which tries to understand how different organisms are adapted to their environments in terms of not only survival but also:</text>
            <option id="A">Migration</option>
            <option id="B">Reproduction</option>
            <option id="C">Competition</option>
            <option id="D">Predation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Ecology at the organismic level is essentially physiological ecology which tries to understand how different organisms are adapted to their environments in terms of not only survival but also reproduction.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is the most ecologically relevant environmental factor?</text>
            <option id="A">Light</option>
            <option id="B">Water</option>
            <option id="C">Temperature</option>
            <option id="D">Soil</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Temperature is the most ecologically relevant environmental factor. You are aware that the average temperature on land varies seasonally, decreases progressively from the equator towards the poles and from plains to the mountain tops.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Organisms that can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Stenothermal</option>
            <option id="B">Eurythermal</option>
            <option id="C">Poikilothermal</option>
            <option id="D">Homoiothermal</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A few organisms can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures (they are called eurythermal), but, a vast majority of them are restricted to a narrow range of temperatures (such organisms are called stenothermal).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In nature, which of the following describes the level at which we find populations?</text>
            <option id="A">A single individual</option>
            <option id="B">A group of individuals of the same species living in a well-defined geographical area</option>
            <option id="C">A community of different species</option>
            <option id="D">An entire ecosystem</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In nature, we rarely find isolated, single individuals of any species; majority of them live in groups in a well defined geographical area, share or compete for similar resources, potentially interbreed and thus constitute a population.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Although the term interbreeding implies sexual reproduction, a group of individuals resulting from which other process is also generally considered a population for the purpose of ecological studies?</text>
            <option id="A">Spontaneous generation</option>
            <option id="B">Asexual reproduction</option>
            <option id="C">Mutation</option>
            <option id="D">Migration</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Although the term interbreeding implies sexual reproduction, a group of individuals resulting from even asexual reproduction is also generally considered a population for the purpose of ecological studies.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT an example of a population?</text>
            <option id="A">All the cormorants in a wetland</option>
            <option id="B">Rats in an abandoned dwelling</option>
            <option id="C">Teakwood trees in a forest tract</option>
            <option id="D">A single lotus plant in a pond</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>All the cormorants in a wetland, rats in an abandoned dwelling, teakwood trees in a forest tract, bacteria in a culture plate and lotus plants in a pond, are some examples of a population.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If an organism can regulate its internal environment to maintain a constant body temperature and constant osmotic concentration despite varying external conditions, it is called a:</text>
            <option id="A">Conformer</option>
            <option id="B">Regulator</option>
            <option id="C">Migrator</option>
            <option id="D">Suspender</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some organisms are able to maintain homeostasis by physiological (sometimes behavioural also) means which ensures constant body temperature, constant osmotic concentration, etc. All birds and mammals, and a very few lower vertebrate and invertebrate species are indeed capable of such regulation (thermoregulation and osmoregulation).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the evolutionary success of mammals largely attributed to?</text>
            <option id="A">Their ability to run fast</option>
            <option id="B">Their varied diets</option>
            <option id="C">Their ability to maintain a constant body temperature and thrive in diverse climates</option>
            <option id="D">Their large brains</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Evolutionary biologists believe that the 'success' of mammals is largely due to their ability to maintain a constant body temperature and thrive whether they live in Antarctica or in the Sahara desert.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>An overwhelming majority (99 per cent) of animals and nearly all plants cannot maintain a constant internal environment. Their body temperature changes with the ambient temperature. These organisms are known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Regulators</option>
            <option id="B">Conformers</option>
            <option id="C">Migrators</option>
            <option id="D">Endotherms</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>An overwhelming majority (99 per cent) of animals and nearly all plants cannot maintain a constant internal environment. Their body temperature changes with the ambient temperature. In aquatic animals, the osmotic concentration of the body fluids change with that of the ambient air, water osmotic concentration. These animals and plants are simply conformers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT one of the four basic processes that fluctuate population density in a given habitat?</text>
            <option id="A">Natality</option>
            <option id="B">Mortality</option>
            <option id="C">Mutation</option>
            <option id="D">Immigration</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The density of a population in a given habitat during a given period, fluctuates due to changes in four basic processes: Natality, Mortality, Immigration and Emigration. Mutation is not one of them.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What term describes the number of births during a given period in the population that are added to the initial density?</text>
            <option id="A">Mortality</option>
            <option id="B">Natality</option>
            <option id="C">Immigration</option>
            <option id="D">Emigration</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Natality refers to the number of births during a given period in the population that are added to the initial density.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Immigration is the number of individuals of the same species that have:</text>
            <option id="A">Left the habitat</option>
            <option id="B">Died in the habitat</option>
            <option id="C">Come into the habitat from elsewhere during the time period under consideration</option>
            <option id="D">Been born in the habitat</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Immigration is the number of individuals of the same species that have come into the habitat from elsewhere during the time period under consideration.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In nature, populations rarely have unlimited resources, leading to competition. This competition eventually leaves the 'fittest' individual to survive and reproduce. This type of growth is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Exponential growth</option>
            <option id="B">Logistic growth</option>
            <option id="C">Geometric growth</option>
            <option id="D">Unrestricted growth</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In nature, a given habitat has enough resources to support a maximum possible number, beyond which no further growth is possible. A population growing in a habitat with limited resources show initially a lag phase... This type of population growth is called Verhulst-Pearl Logistic Growth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The maximum number of individuals of a population that a given habitat can support with its available resources is called its:</text>
            <option id="A">Biotic potential</option>
            <option id="B">Carrying capacity (K)</option>
            <option id="C">Intrinsic rate (r)</option>
            <option id="D">Saturation point</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In nature, a given habitat has enough resources to support a maximum possible number, beyond which no further growth is possible. Let us call this limit as nature's carrying capacity (K) for that species in that habitat.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A population growing in a habitat with limited resources shows a characteristic curve when N (population density) is plotted against time (t). What is the shape of this curve?</text>
            <option id="A">J-shaped</option>
            <option id="B">Linear</option>
            <option id="C">Sigmoid</option>
            <option id="D">U-shaped</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>A population growing in a habitat with limited resources show initially a lag phase, followed by phases of acceleration and deceleration and finally an asymptote, when the population density reaches the carrying capacity. A plot of N in relation to time (t) results in a sigmoid curve.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Animals that have a constant body temperature and can regulate their internal environment are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Conformers</option>
            <option id="B">Regulators</option>
            <option id="C">Migrators</option>
            <option id="D">Poikilotherms</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Regulate: Some organisms are able to maintain homeostasis by physiological (sometimes behavioural also) means which ensures constant body temperature, constant osmotic concentration, etc.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following groups of animals are mostly regulators?</text>
            <option id="A">All reptiles and amphibians</option>
            <option id="B">All birds and mammals</option>
            <option id="C">All fishes and insects</option>
            <option id="D">Most invertebrates</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>All birds and mammals, and a very few lower vertebrate and invertebrate species are indeed capable of such regulation (thermoregulation and osmoregulation).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the mechanism used by mammals to regulate their body temperature similar to?</text>
            <option id="A">The mechanism used by reptiles</option>
            <option id="B">The mechanism used by amphibians</option>
            <option id="C">The mechanism used by human beings</option>
            <option id="D">The mechanism used by fishes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The mechanisms used by most mammals to regulate their body temperature are similar to the ones that we humans use. We maintain a constant body temperature of 37 degree C.</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>When a population grows in a habitat with limited resources, it exhibits a logistic growth curve. The equation for this curve is dN/dt = rN((K-N)/K). What does 'K' represent?</text>
            <option id="A">Intrinsic rate of natural increase</option>
            <option id="B">Carrying capacity</option>
            <option id="C">Population density at time t</option>
            <option id="D">Environmental resistance</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In the logistic growth equation, K represents the carrying capacity, which is the maximum population size of a biological species that can be sustained in that specific environment, given the food, habitat, water, and other necessities available.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of a morphological adaptation for minimizing water loss in desert plants?</text>
            <option id="A">Presence of a special photosynthetic pathway (CAM)</option>
            <option id="B">Leaves reduced to spines</option>
            <option id="C">Stomata that remain open during the day</option>
            <option id="D">Production of antifreeze proteins</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Many desert plants like Opuntia have their leaves reduced to spines to minimize water loss through transpiration, and the photosynthetic function is taken over by the flattened stems. CAM pathway is a physiological adaptation, not morphological.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Gause's 'Competitive Exclusion Principle' states that:</text>
            <option id="A">Two closely related species competing for the same resources can co-exist indefinitely.</option>
            <option id="B">Two closely related species competing for the same resources cannot co-exist indefinitely and the competitively inferior one will be eliminated.</option>
            <option id="C">Predators play an important role in maintaining species diversity in a community.</option>
            <option id="D">Parasites always evolve to become less virulent to their hosts over time.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Gause's 'Competitive Exclusion Principle' states that two closely related species competing for the same resources cannot co-exist indefinitely and the competitively inferior one will be eliminated eventually.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The association between a sea anemone and a clown fish is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Mutualism</option>
            <option id="B">Commensalism</option>
            <option id="C">Amensalism</option>
            <option id="D">Parasitism</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The interaction between sea anemone that has stinging tentacles and the clown fish that lives among them is an example of commensalism. The fish gets protection from predators, while the anemone does not appear to derive any benefit.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If 'N' is the population density at time 't', then its density at time t+1 is: N_t+1 = N_t + [(B + I) - (D + E)]. What do B and E stand for respectively?</text>
            <option id="A">Birth rate and Emigration</option>
            <option id="B">Birth rate and Immigration</option>
            <option id="C">Biomass and Energy</option>
            <option id="D">Base rate and Extinction</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In the population density equation, B stands for the number of births (Birth rate), I for Immigration, D for Deaths (Death rate), and E for Emigration.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the principle of Allen's Rule?</text>
            <option id="A">Mammals from colder climates generally have shorter ears and limbs to minimize heat loss.</option>
            <option id="B">Animals in colder climates have thicker layers of fat.</option>
            <option id="C">Birds in warmer climates have longer wings.</option>
            <option id="D">Reptiles adapt to desert climates by becoming nocturnal.</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Allen's Rule states that mammals from colder climates generally have shorter ears and limbs to minimize heat loss.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following interactions is an example of amensalism?</text>
            <option id="A">A tick feeding on a dog</option>
            <option id="B">Penicillium secreting penicillin which kills nearby bacteria</option>
            <option id="C">A clownfish living among the tentacles of a sea anemone</option>
            <option id="D">Lichen</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Amensalism is an interaction where one species is harmed (-) and the other is unaffected (0). The classic example is the mold Penicillium secreting penicillin, which kills bacteria without Penicillium gaining any obvious benefit or harm from the interaction itself.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In altitude sickness, the body compensates for low oxygen availability by:</text>
            <option id="A">Increasing red blood cell production</option>
            <option id="B">Decreasing the breathing rate</option>
            <option id="C">Increasing the binding affinity of hemoglobin</option>
            <option id="D">Decreasing the heart rate</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The body compensates low oxygen availability at high altitudes by increasing red blood cell production, decreasing the binding affinity of hemoglobin, and by increasing breathing rate.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In a growing population of a country, the age pyramid will be:</text>
            <option id="A">Bell-shaped</option>
            <option id="B">Urn-shaped</option>
            <option id="C">Triangular with a broad base</option>
            <option id="D">Linear</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>If the age distribution is plotted for the population, the resulting structure is called an age pyramid. For human population, a pyramid with a broad base represents a rapidly growing (expanding) population because there is a large number of pre-reproductive individuals.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The maximum number of individuals of a population that a given environment can sustain indefinitely is called its:</text>
            <option id="A">Biotic potential</option>
            <option id="B">Carrying capacity (K)</option>
            <option id="C">Environmental resistance</option>
            <option id="D">Intrinsic rate of increase (r)</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In nature, a given habitat has enough resources to support a maximum possible number, beyond which no further growth is possible. This limit is called nature's carrying capacity (K) for that species in that habitat.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The interaction where one species benefits and the other is neither harmed nor benefited is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Mutualism</option>
            <option id="B">Commensalism</option>
            <option id="C">Amensalism</option>
            <option id="D">Parasitism</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Commensalism is the interaction in which one species benefits and the other is neither harmed nor benefited (+/0 interaction). An orchid growing as an epiphyte on a mango branch is a classic example.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Gause's 'Competitive Exclusion Principle' states that:</text>
            <option id="A">Two closely related species competing for the same resources can easily co-exist.</option>
            <option id="B">Competition only occurs between organisms of different species.</option>
            <option id="C">Two closely related species competing for the same resources cannot co-exist indefinitely.</option>
            <option id="D">Predators completely eliminate their prey to exclude competitors.</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Gause's 'Competitive Exclusion Principle' states that two closely related species competing for the same resources cannot co-exist indefinitely and the competitively inferior one will be eliminated eventually.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Organisms that are tolerant of a wide range of salinities are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Stenohaline</option>
            <option id="B">Euryhaline</option>
            <option id="C">Osmoconformers</option>
            <option id="D">Osmoregulators</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some organisms are tolerant of a wide range of salinities (euryhaline) but others are restricted to a narrow range (stenohaline).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process by which organisms maintain a constant internal environment (e.g., constant body temperature and osmotic concentration) despite varying external environmental conditions is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Acclimatization</option>
            <option id="B">Homeostasis</option>
            <option id="C">Diapause</option>
            <option id="D">Aestivation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The organism must try to maintain the constancy of its internal environment (a process called homeostasis) despite varying external environmental conditions that tend to upset its homeostasis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In animals, nearly all plants cannot maintain a constant internal environment. Their body temperature changes with the ambient temperature. Such organisms are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Regulators</option>
            <option id="B">Conformers</option>
            <option id="C">Migrators</option>
            <option id="D">Hibernators</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>An overwhelming majority (99 per cent) of animals and nearly all plants cannot maintain a constant internal environment. Their body temperature changes with the ambient temperature. These animals and plants are simply conformers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of an organism undergoing aestivation to avoid summer-related problems like heat and desiccation?</text>
            <option id="A">Bear</option>
            <option id="B">Snail</option>
            <option id="C">Zooplankton</option>
            <option id="D">Siberian Crane</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some snails and fish go into aestivation to avoid summer-related problems-heat and desiccation. Bears going into hibernation during winter is an example of escape in time.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If a population is growing exponentially, its growth curve will be:</text>
            <option id="A">J-shaped</option>
            <option id="B">S-shaped</option>
            <option id="C">Linear</option>
            <option id="D">Bell-shaped</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>When resources in the habitat are unlimited, each species has the ability to realise fully its innate potential to grow in number. Then the population grows in an exponential or geometric fashion, resulting in a J-shaped curve.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The maximum number of individuals of a population that can be supported by the available resources in a given habitat is called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Biotic potential</option>
            <option id="B">Carrying capacity</option>
            <option id="C">Intrinsic rate of natural increase</option>
            <option id="D">Environmental resistance</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In nature, a given habitat has enough resources to support a maximum possible number, beyond which no further growth is possible. Let us call this limit as nature's carrying capacity (K) for that species in that habitat.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Populations growing in a habitat with limited resources initially show a lag phase, followed by phases of acceleration and deceleration, and finally an asymptote. This type of population growth is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Exponential growth</option>
            <option id="B">Logistic growth</option>
            <option id="C">Geometric growth</option>
            <option id="D">Arithmetic growth</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A population growing in a habitat with limited resources show initially a lag phase, followed by phases of acceleration and deceleration and finally an asymptote, when the population density reaches the carrying capacity. A plot of N in relation to time (t) results in a sigmoid curve. This type of population growth is called Verhulst-Pearl Logistic Growth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following interactions is detrimental to both the species involved?</text>
            <option id="A">Predation</option>
            <option id="B">Parasitism</option>
            <option id="C">Competition</option>
            <option id="D">Amensalism</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In competition, the interaction is detrimental to both species (- , -). In predation and parasitism, one benefits and the other is harmed (+ , -).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of behavioural adaptation to cope with extreme variations in the environment?</text>
            <option id="A">Presence of thick cuticle on the leaf surface</option>
            <option id="B">Desert lizards basking in the sun and absorbing heat when their body temperature drops</option>
            <option id="C">Production of antifreeze proteins in Antarctic fishes</option>
            <option id="D">Increased red blood cell production at high altitudes</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some organisms show behavioural responses to cope with variations in their environment. Desert lizards lack the physiological ability that mammals have to deal with the high temperatures of their habitat, but manage to keep their body temperature fairly constant by behavioural means. They bask in the sun and absorb heat when their body temperature drops below the comfort zone, but move into shade when the ambient temperature starts increasing.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If 'N' is the population density at time 't', then its density at time t + 1 is given by the equation: Nt+1 = Nt + [(B + I) - (D + E)]. What does 'E' represent in this equation?</text>
            <option id="A">Extinction</option>
            <option id="B">Emigration</option>
            <option id="C">Evolution</option>
            <option id="D">Environment</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Emigration (E) is the number of individuals of the population who left the habitat and gone elsewhere during the time period under consideration. Thus, if N is the population density at time t, then its density at time t +1 is: Nt+1 = Nt + [(B + I) - (D + E)].</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Under normal conditions, which two factors are the most important in influencing population density?</text>
            <option id="A">Immigration and Emigration</option>
            <option id="B">Births and Deaths</option>
            <option id="C">Births and Immigration</option>
            <option id="D">Deaths and Emigration</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Under normal conditions, births and deaths are the most important factors influencing population density, the other two factors assuming importance only under special conditions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the logistic growth equation, dN/dt = rN((K-N)/K), what does 'K' stand for?</text>
            <option id="A">Intrinsic rate of natural increase</option>
            <option id="B">Carrying capacity</option>
            <option id="C">Population density at time t</option>
            <option id="D">Environmental resistance</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In nature, a given habitat has enough resources to support a maximum possible number, beyond which no further growth is possible. Let us call this limit as nature's carrying capacity (K) for that species in that habitat.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In aquatic environments, the salt concentration (measured as salinity in parts per thousand) is less than 5 in inland waters, 30-35 in the sea, and > 100 in:</text>
            <option id="A">Estuaries</option>
            <option id="B">Some hypersaline lagoons</option>
            <option id="C">Deep sea hydrothermal vents</option>
            <option id="D">Rivers</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The salt concentration (measured as salinity in parts per thousand), is less than 5 in inland waters, 30-35 in the sea and &gt; 100 in some hypersaline lagoons.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following organisms are capable of maintaining homeostasis by physiological means which ensures constant body temperature, constant osmotic concentration, etc.?</text>
            <option id="A">All reptiles</option>
            <option id="B">All amphibians</option>
            <option id="C">Birds and mammals</option>
            <option id="D">Fishes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Some organisms are able to maintain homeostasis by physiological (sometimes behavioural also) means which ensures constant body temperature, constant osmotic concentration, etc. All birds and mammals, and a very few lower vertebrate and invertebrate species are indeed capable of such regulation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During summer, if the outside temperature is more than our body temperature, we sweat profusely. The resulting evaporative cooling brings down the body temperature. This is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Conformation</option>
            <option id="B">Regulation</option>
            <option id="C">Migration</option>
            <option id="D">Suspension</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>This is an example of regulation. When it is cold outside, we shiver, a kind of exercise which produces heat and raises the body temperature. Plants, on the other hand, do not have such mechanisms to maintain internal temperatures.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If the stressful external conditions are localised or remain only for a short duration, the organism has two other alternatives for survival: migrate or:</text>
            <option id="A">Conform</option>
            <option id="B">Regulate</option>
            <option id="C">Suspend</option>
            <option id="D">Adapt</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>If the stressful external conditions are localised or remain only for a short duration, the organism has two other alternatives for survival. 1. Migrate 2. Suspend.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In a population, what does the sex ratio represent?</text>
            <option id="A">The total number of males and females combined</option>
            <option id="B">The ratio of males to females in a population</option>
            <option id="C">The number of offspring born each year</option>
            <option id="D">The lifespan of males compared to females</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A population has certain attributes whereas, an individual organism does not. An individual may have births and deaths, but a population has birth rates and death rates. Another attribute characteristic of a population is sex ratio. An individual is either a male or a female but a population has a sex ratio (e.g., 60 per cent of the population are females and 40 per cent males).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A population at any given time is composed of individuals of different ages. What is the resulting structure when the age distribution is plotted for the population called?</text>
            <option id="A">Age histogram</option>
            <option id="B">Age pyramid</option>
            <option id="C">Survivorship curve</option>
            <option id="D">Life table</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A population at any given time is composed of individuals of different ages. If the age distribution (per cent individuals of a given age or age group) is plotted for the population, the resulting structure is called an age pyramid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>For human population, age pyramids generally show age distribution of males and females in a diagram. The shape of the pyramids reflects the:</text>
            <option id="A">Geographical distribution of the population</option>
            <option id="B">Growth status of the population (growing, stable, or declining)</option>
            <option id="C">Average lifespan of the population</option>
            <option id="D">Genetic diversity of the population</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>For human population, the age pyramids generally show age distribution of males and females in a diagram. The shape of the pyramids reflects the growth status of the population - (a) whether it is growing, (b) stable or (c) declining.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The size of the population tells us a lot about its status in the habitat. What is the technical term used for population size in ecology?</text>
            <option id="A">Population magnitude</option>
            <option id="B">Population density (N)</option>
            <option id="C">Carrying capacity (K)</option>
            <option id="D">Biotic potential (r)</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The size of the population tells us a lot about its status in the habitat. Population size, technically called population density (designated as N), need not necessarily be measured in numbers only.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Why are very small animals like shrews and hummingbirds rarely found in polar regions?</text>
            <option id="A">They cannot find enough food</option>
            <option id="B">Their surface area is large relative to their volume, causing them to lose body heat very fast in cold environments</option>
            <option id="C">They cannot camouflage well in the snow</option>
            <option id="D">They are preyed upon more frequently</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Thermoregulation is energetically expensive for many organisms. This is particularly true for small animals like shrews and humming birds. Heat loss or heat gain is a function of surface area. Since small animals have a larger surface area relative to their volume, they tend to lose body heat very fast when it is cold outside; then they have to expend much energy to generate body heat through metabolism. This is the main reason why very small animals are rarely found in polar regions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When you move to a high altitude place (>3,500m) like Rohtang Pass, you might experience 'altitude sickness' characterized by nausea, fatigue, and heart palpitations. This is because:</text>
            <option id="A">The body is freezing</option>
            <option id="B">Low atmospheric pressure leads to inadequate oxygen availability</option>
            <option id="C">The UV radiation is too strong</option>
            <option id="D">The gravity is stronger</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>This is because in the low atmospheric pressure of high altitudes, the body does not get enough oxygen. But, gradually you get acclimatised and stop experiencing altitude sickness.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How does the human body eventually acclimatize and overcome altitude sickness at high altitudes?</text>
            <option id="A">By decreasing red blood cell production</option>
            <option id="B">By decreasing the breathing rate</option>
            <option id="C">By increasing red blood cell production, decreasing the binding affinity of hemoglobin, and increasing breathing rate</option>
            <option id="D">By shivering</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>How did the body solve this problem? The body compensates low oxygen availability by increasing red blood cell production, decreasing the binding affinity of hemoglobin and by increasing breathing rate.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In most animals, the metabolic reactions and all the physiological functions proceed optimally in a narrow temperature range (in humans, it is 37°C). However, some microbes (archaebacteria) flourish in hot springs and deep sea hydrothermal vents where temperatures far exceed:</text>
            <option id="A">50°C</option>
            <option id="B">80°C</option>
            <option id="C">100°C</option>
            <option id="D">150°C</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>But there are microbes (archaebacteria) that flourish in hot springs and deep sea hydrothermal vents where temperatures far exceed 1000C.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which two basic processes contribute to an increase in population density?</text>
            <option id="A">Natality and Mortality</option>
            <option id="B">Natality and Immigration</option>
            <option id="C">Mortality and Emigration</option>
            <option id="D">Immigration and Emigration</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Natality and immigration contribute to an increase in population density.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which two basic processes contribute to a decrease in population density?</text>
            <option id="A">Natality and Mortality</option>
            <option id="B">Natality and Immigration</option>
            <option id="C">Mortality and Emigration</option>
            <option id="D">Immigration and Emigration</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Mortality and emigration contribute to a decrease in population density.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If N is the population density at time t, then its density at time t+1 is calculated as Nt+1 = Nt + [(B + I) - (D + E)]. In this equation, what does 'E' represent?</text>
            <option id="A">Energy</option>
            <option id="B">Environment</option>
            <option id="C">Emigration</option>
            <option id="D">Extinction</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In the equation Nt+1 = Nt + [(B + I) - (D + E)], E represents Emigration (the number of individuals of the population who left the habitat and gone elsewhere during the time period under consideration).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Under normal conditions, births and deaths are the most important factors influencing population density. However, if a new habitat is just being colonised, which factor may contribute more significantly to population growth than birth rates?</text>
            <option id="A">Immigration</option>
            <option id="B">Emigration</option>
            <option id="C">Mortality</option>
            <option id="D">Mutation</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Under normal conditions, births and deaths are the most important factors influencing population density... But if a new habitat is just being colonised, immigration may contribute more significantly to population growth than birth rates.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Verhulst-Pearl Logistic Growth is described by the equation dN/dt = rN((K-N)/K). What does 'K' stand for in this equation?</text>
            <option id="A">Intrinsic rate of natural increase</option>
            <option id="B">Population density at time t</option>
            <option id="C">Carrying capacity</option>
            <option id="D">Kinetic energy</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>This type of population growth is called Verhulst-Pearl Logistic Growth... where K = Carrying capacity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Since resources for growth for most animal populations are finite and become limiting sooner or later, which growth model is considered more realistic?</text>
            <option id="A">Exponential growth model</option>
            <option id="B">Logistic growth model</option>
            <option id="C">Geometric growth model</option>
            <option id="D">Malthusian growth model</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Since resources for growth for most animal populations are finite and become limiting sooner or later, the logistic growth model is considered a more realistic one.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Under a particular set of selection pressures, organisms evolve towards the most efficient reproductive strategy. Which of the following organisms breeds only once in its lifetime?</text>
            <option id="A">Birds</option>
            <option id="B">Mammals</option>
            <option id="C">Pacific salmon fish and bamboo</option>
            <option id="D">Oysters and pelagic fishes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Some organisms breed only once in their lifetime (Pacific salmon fish, bamboo) while others breed many times during their lifetime (most birds and mammals).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following organisms produce a large number of small-sized offspring as their reproductive strategy?</text>
            <option id="A">Birds</option>
            <option id="B">Mammals</option>
            <option id="C">Oysters and pelagic fishes</option>
            <option id="D">Bamboo</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Some produce a large number of small-sized offspring (Oysters, pelagic fishes) while others produce a small number of large-sized offspring (birds, mammals).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During summer, when the outside temperature is more than our body temperature, how do humans thermoregulate?</text>
            <option id="A">By shivering</option>
            <option id="B">By sweating profusely</option>
            <option id="C">By increasing metabolic rate</option>
            <option id="D">By seeking dark places</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In summer, when outside temperature is more than our body temperature, we sweat profusely. The resulting evaporative cooling... brings down the body temperature.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The overwhelming majority (99 percent) of animals and nearly all plants cannot maintain a constant internal environment. Their body temperature changes with the ambient temperature. These are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Regulators</option>
            <option id="B">Conformers</option>
            <option id="C">Migrators</option>
            <option id="D">Hibernators</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Conform: An overwhelming majority (99 per cent) of animals and nearly all plants cannot maintain a constant internal environment. Their body temperature changes with the ambient temperature... These animals and plants are simply conformers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Why haven't conformers evolved to become regulators, considering the benefits of a constant internal environment?</text>
            <option id="A">Because they lack the genetic mutation</option>
            <option id="B">Because thermoregulation is energetically expensive for many organisms</option>
            <option id="C">Because they live in environments that never change</option>
            <option id="D">Because regulation requires a large brain</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Thermoregulation is energetically expensive for many organisms. This is particularly true for small animals like shrews and humming birds.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Heat loss or heat gain is a function of surface area. Why are very small animals rarely found in polar regions?</text>
            <option id="A">Their surface area is very small relative to their volume</option>
            <option id="B">Their surface area is very large relative to their volume</option>
            <option id="C">They do not have fur</option>
            <option id="D">They cannot find food in the snow</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Heat loss or heat gain is a function of surface area. Since small animals have a larger surface area relative to their volume, they tend to lose body heat very fast when it is cold outside... This is the main reason why very small animals are rarely found in polar regions.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>MacArthur showed that five closely related species of warblers living on the same tree were able to avoid competition and co-exist. This was achieved through:</text>
            <option id="A">Competitive exclusion</option>
            <option id="B">Character displacement</option>
            <option id="C">Resource partitioning</option>
            <option id="D">Predation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>MacArthur showed that five closely related species of warblers living on the same tree were able to avoid competition and co-exist due to behavioral differences in their foraging activities, a mechanism known as resource partitioning.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Verhulst-Pearl logistic growth is described by a specific curve shape. What is the shape of this population growth curve?</text>
            <option id="A">J-shaped</option>
            <option id="B">Sigmoid (S-shaped)</option>
            <option id="C">U-shaped</option>
            <option id="D">Linear</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A population growing in a habitat with limited resources shows initially a lag phase, followed by phases of acceleration and deceleration, and finally an asymptote when the population density reaches the carrying capacity. A plot of N in relation to time t results in a sigmoid (S-shaped) curve.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the context of population attributes, if in a pond there were 20 lotus plants last year and through reproduction 8 new plants are added, taking the current population to 28, what is the birth rate?</text>
            <option id="A">0.4 offspring per lotus per year</option>
            <option id="B">0.8 offspring per lotus per year</option>
            <option id="C">2.5 offspring per lotus per year</option>
            <option id="D">8 offspring per lotus per year</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Birth rate is expressed as change in numbers (increase) with respect to members of the population. Here, the birth rate is 8 / 20 = 0.4 offspring per lotus per year.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The "Prickly Pear Cactus" introduced into Australia in the 1920s caused havoc by spreading rapidly into millions of hectares of rangeland. It was finally brought under control by introducing:</text>
            <option id="A">A competing plant species</option>
            <option id="B">A cactus-feeding moth</option>
            <option id="C">A fungal pathogen</option>
            <option id="D">A viral disease</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The prickly pear cactus introduced into Australia was finally brought under control only after a cactus-feeding predator (a moth) from its natural habitat was introduced into the country.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT an adaptation of parasites to their host?</text>
            <option id="A">Loss of unnecessary sense organs</option>
            <option id="B">Presence of adhesive organs or suckers</option>
            <option id="C">Development of a highly complex digestive system</option>
            <option id="D">High reproductive capacity</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Parasites often have a simple digestive system or lose it entirely because they absorb pre-digested nutrients directly from their host. They do not develop a complex digestive system.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Mediterranean orchid Ophrys employs which highly specialized mechanism to ensure pollination by bees?</text>
            <option id="A">Offering a safe place to lay eggs</option>
            <option id="B">Producing a high volume of concentrated nectar</option>
            <option id="C">Sexual deceit</option>
            <option id="D">Emitting a foul odor resembling rotting meat</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The Mediterranean orchid Ophrys employs 'sexual deceit'. One petal of its flower bears an uncanny resemblance to the female of the bee species in size, colour and markings. The male bee is attracted to what it perceives as a female, 'pseudocopulates' with the flower, and during that process is dusted with pollen.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Many desert plants have a special photosynthetic pathway called CAM. What is the primary advantage of this pathway in desert conditions?</text>
            <option id="A">It allows them to photosynthesize only using green light.</option>
            <option id="B">It enables their stomata to remain closed during daytime to minimise water loss.</option>
            <option id="C">It prevents them from being eaten by herbivores.</option>
            <option id="D">It allows them to fix nitrogen from the air.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Many desert plants have a special photosynthetic pathway (CAM) that enables their stomata to remain closed during daytime. This minimises water loss through transpiration.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a behavioral adaptation exhibited by desert lizards to manage their body temperature?</text>
            <option id="A">They have a thick layer of blubber.</option>
            <option id="B">They hibernate during the summer.</option>
            <option id="C">They bask in the sun and absorb heat when their body temperature drops, and move into shade when the ambient temperature starts increasing.</option>
            <option id="D">They sweat profusely to cool down.</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Desert lizards manage to keep their body temperature fairly constant by behavioural means. They bask in the sun and absorb heat when their body temperature drops below the comfort zone, but move into shade when the ambient temperature starts increasing.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The principle of 'resource partitioning' was shown by MacArthur using which group of birds?</text>
            <option id="A">Darwin's finches</option>
            <option id="B">Warblers</option>
            <option id="C">Hummingbirds</option>
            <option id="D">Pigeons</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>MacArthur showed that five closely related species of warblers living on the same tree were able to avoid competition and co-exist due to behavioural differences in their foraging activities. This is called resource partitioning.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Under unfavourable conditions, many zooplankton species in lakes and ponds are known to enter a stage of suspended development called:</text>
            <option id="A">Hibernation</option>
            <option id="B">Aestivation</option>
            <option id="C">Diapause</option>
            <option id="D">Dormancy</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Under unfavourable conditions many zooplankton species in lakes and ponds are known to enter diapause, a stage of suspended development.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Kangaroo rat in North American deserts is capable of meeting all its water requirements through:</text>
            <option id="A">Drinking large amounts of water when available</option>
            <option id="B">Absorbing moisture from the air</option>
            <option id="C">Internal fat oxidation</option>
            <option id="D">Eating succulent plants exclusively</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In the absence of an external source of water, the kangaroo rat in North American deserts is capable of meeting all its water requirements through its internal fat oxidation (in which water is a by product).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Mammals from colder climates generally have shorter ears and limbs to minimise heat loss. This is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Gause's Law</option>
            <option id="B">Allen's Rule</option>
            <option id="C">Bergmann's Rule</option>
            <option id="D">Cope's Rule</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Mammals from colder climates generally have shorter ears and limbs to minimise heat loss. (This is called the Allen's Rule.) In the polar seas aquatic mammals like seals have a thick layer of fat (blubber) below their skin that acts as an insulator.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which interaction is characterised by one species benefiting and the other being neither harmed nor benefited?</text>
            <option id="A">Mutualism</option>
            <option id="B">Commensalism</option>
            <option id="C">Amensalism</option>
            <option id="D">Parasitism</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Commensalism is the interaction in which one species benefits and the other is neither harmed nor benefited (+ , 0). An orchid growing as an epiphyte on a mango branch is an example.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The monarch butterfly is highly distasteful to its predator (bird) because of a special chemical present in its body. How does the butterfly acquire this chemical?</text>
            <option id="A">It synthesizes the chemical in its liver</option>
            <option id="B">It acquires the chemical by feeding on a poisonous weed during its caterpillar stage</option>
            <option id="C">It obtains the chemical from the nectar of specific flowers</option>
            <option id="D">The chemical is produced by a symbiotic bacteria in its gut</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Monarch butterfly is highly distasteful to its predator (bird) because of a special chemical present in its body. Interestingly, the butterfly acquires this chemical during its caterpillar stage by feeding on a poisonous weed.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Some plants like Acacia and Cactus have developed morphological means of defense against herbivores. What is this defense mechanism?</text>
            <option id="A">Production of toxic cardiac glycosides</option>
            <option id="B">Presence of thorns</option>
            <option id="C">Secretion of sticky resins</option>
            <option id="D">Camouflage</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>For plants, herbivores are the predators. Plants therefore have evolved an astonishing variety of morphological and chemical defences against herbivores. Thorns (Acacia, Cactus) are the most common morphological means of defence.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In which of the following population interactions do both the species benefit?</text>
            <option id="A">Mutualism</option>
            <option id="B">Competition</option>
            <option id="C">Commensalism</option>
            <option id="D">Amensalism</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Both the species benefit in mutualism and both lose in competition in their interactions with each other.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>An interaction where one species is harmed and the other is unaffected is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Commensalism</option>
            <option id="B">Amensalism</option>
            <option id="C">Parasitism</option>
            <option id="D">Predation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In amensalism on the other hand one species is harmed whereas the other is unaffected. In commensalism one species benefits and the other is neither harmed nor benefited.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which principle states that two closely related species competing for the same resources cannot co-exist indefinitely and the competitively inferior one will be eliminated eventually?</text>
            <option id="A">Hardy-Weinberg Principle</option>
            <option id="B">Gause's 'Competitive Exclusion Principle'</option>
            <option id="C">Allen's Rule</option>
            <option id="D">Competitive Release</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Gause's 'Competitive Exclusion Principle' states that two closely related species competing for the same resources cannot co-exist indefinitely and the competitively inferior one will be eliminated eventually. This may be true if resources are limiting, but not otherwise.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Under unfavorable conditions, many zooplankton species in lakes and ponds are known to enter a stage of suspended development called:</text>
            <option id="A">Hibernation</option>
            <option id="B">Aestivation</option>
            <option id="C">Diapause</option>
            <option id="D">Dormancy</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Under unfavourable conditions many zooplankton species in lakes and ponds are known to enter diapause, a stage of suspended development.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which rule states that mammals from colder climates generally have shorter ears and limbs to minimise heat loss?</text>
            <option id="A">Bergmann's rule</option>
            <option id="B">Allen's rule</option>
            <option id="C">Gloger's rule</option>
            <option id="D">Jordan's rule</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Mammals from colder climates generally have shorter ears and limbs to minimise heat loss. (This is called the Allen's Rule.) In the polar seas aquatic mammals like seals have a thick layer of fat (blubber) below their skin that acts as an insulator and reduces loss of body heat.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The population growth equation dN/dt = rN represents which type of growth?</text>
            <option id="A">Logistic growth</option>
            <option id="B">Exponential growth</option>
            <option id="C">Linear growth</option>
            <option id="D">Sigmoid growth</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The equation dN/dt = rN describes the exponential or geometric growth pattern of a population. 'r' is the 'intrinsic rate of natural increase'.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If in a pond there are 20 lotus plants last year and through reproduction 8 new plants are added, taking the current population to 28, what is the birth rate per lotus per year?</text>
            <option id="A">0.2</option>
            <option id="B">0.4</option>
            <option id="C">0.8</option>
            <option id="D">2.8</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>If in a pond there were 20 lotus plants last year and through reproduction 8 new plants are added, taking the current population to 28, we calculate the birth rate as 8/20 = 0.4 offspring per lotus per year.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If 4 individuals in a laboratory population of 40 fruitflies died during a specified time interval (say a week), the death rate in the population during that period is:</text>
            <option id="A">0.01 individuals per fruitfly per week</option>
            <option id="B">0.1 individuals per fruitfly per week</option>
            <option id="C">0.4 individuals per fruitfly per week</option>
            <option id="D">1.0 individuals per fruitfly per week</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>If 4 individuals in a laboratory population of 40 fruitflies died during a specified time interval, say a week, the death rate in the population during that period is 4/40 = 0.1 individuals per fruitfly per week.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In some cases, measuring population density by total number is difficult or impossible. In an area with 200 Parthenium plants but only a single huge banyan tree, stating that the population density of banyan is low relative to that of Parthenium amounts to underestimating the enormous role of the banyan. In such cases, what is a more meaningful measure of population size?</text>
            <option id="A">Total number</option>
            <option id="B">Per cent cover or biomass</option>
            <option id="C">Relative density</option>
            <option id="D">Birth rate</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Although total number is generally the most appropriate measure of population density, it is in some cases either meaningless or difficult to determine. In an area, if there are 200 carrot grass (Parthenium hysterophorus) plants but only a single huge banyan tree with a large canopy, stating that the population density of banyan is low relative to that of carrot grass amounts to underestimating the enormous role of the Banyan in that community. In such cases, the per cent cover or biomass is a more meaningful measure of the population size.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Desert lizards lack the physiological ability that mammals have to deal with high temperatures of their habitat, but manage to keep their body temperature fairly constant through:</text>
            <option id="A">Biochemical adaptations</option>
            <option id="B">Behavioural adaptations</option>
            <option id="C">Morphological adaptations</option>
            <option id="D">Hibernation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some organisms show behavioural responses to cope with variations in their environment. Desert lizards lack the physiological ability that mammals have to deal with the high temperatures of their habitat, but manage to keep their body temperature fairly constant by behavioural means.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How do desert lizards behave to regulate their body temperature when their temperature drops below the comfort zone?</text>
            <option id="A">They move into shade</option>
            <option id="B">They bask in the sun and absorb heat</option>
            <option id="C">They start shivering</option>
            <option id="D">They drink water to warm up</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>They bask in the sun and absorb heat when their body temperature drops below the comfort zone, but move into shade when the ambient temperature starts increasing.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Some species cope with environmental stress by burrowing into the soil to hide and escape from the above-ground heat. This is an example of a:</text>
            <option id="A">Physiological adaptation</option>
            <option id="B">Behavioural adaptation</option>
            <option id="C">Biochemical adaptation</option>
            <option id="D">Genetic mutation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some species are capable of burrowing into the soil to hide and escape from the above-ground heat. This is a behavioural means of adaptation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When resources in the habitat are unlimited, each species has the ability to realise fully its innate potential to grow in number. This results in what type of population growth pattern?</text>
            <option id="A">Logistic growth</option>
            <option id="B">Exponential or geometric growth</option>
            <option id="C">Linear growth</option>
            <option id="D">Sigmoid growth</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When resources in the habitat are unlimited, each species has the ability to realise fully its innate potential to grow in number, as Darwin observed... Then the population grows in an exponential or geometric fashion.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the exponential growth equation dN/dt = rN, the parameter 'r' is called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Carrying capacity</option>
            <option id="B">Intrinsic rate of natural increase</option>
            <option id="C">Net reproduction rate</option>
            <option id="D">Environmental resistance</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>If in a population of size N, the birth rates (not total number but per capita births) are represented as b and death rates again, per capita death rates as d, then the increase or decrease in N during a unit time period t (dN/dt) will be dN/dt = (b - d) × N. Let (b - d) = r, then dN/dt = rN. The r in this equation is called the 'intrinsic rate of natural increase'.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the significance of the parameter 'r' (intrinsic rate of natural increase) in ecological studies?</text>
            <option id="A">It determines the carrying capacity of an environment</option>
            <option id="B">It is a very important parameter chosen for assessing impacts of any biotic or abiotic factor on population growth</option>
            <option id="C">It only measures the death rate of a population</option>
            <option id="D">It represents the number of individuals migrating into a population</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The r in this equation is called the 'intrinsic rate of natural increase' and is a very important parameter chosen for assessing impacts of any biotic or abiotic factor on population growth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Populations of different species in a habitat do not live in isolation but interact in various ways. In an interaction where both species benefit, it is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Competition</option>
            <option id="B">Predation</option>
            <option id="C">Mutualism</option>
            <option id="D">Amensalism</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Interspecific interactions arise from the interaction of populations of two different species... Both the species benefit in mutualism.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In which of the following population interactions do both interacting species lose (-/-)?</text>
            <option id="A">Mutualism</option>
            <option id="B">Competition</option>
            <option id="C">Parasitism</option>
            <option id="D">Commensalism</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Interspecific interactions arise from the interaction of populations of two different species... and both lose in competition in their interactions with each other.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In parasitism and predation, how do the interacting species affect each other?</text>
            <option id="A">Both species benefit (+/+)</option>
            <option id="B">Both species are harmed (-/-)</option>
            <option id="C">One species benefits and the other is harmed (+/-)</option>
            <option id="D">One species benefits and the other is unaffected (+/0)</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In both parasitism and predation only one species benefits (parasite and predator, respectively) and the interaction is detrimental to the other species (host and prey, respectively).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Instead of regulating or conforming, some organisms move away temporarily from the stressful habitat to a more hospitable area and return when stressful period is over. This is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Hibernation</option>
            <option id="B">Aestivation</option>
            <option id="C">Migration</option>
            <option id="D">Diapause</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Migrate: The organism can move away temporarily from the stressful habitat to a more hospitable area and return when stressful period is over.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Every winter, the famous Keoladeo National Park (Bharatpur) in Rajasthan hosts thousands of migratory birds coming from:</text>
            <option id="A">Africa and Australia</option>
            <option id="B">Siberia and other extremely cold northern regions</option>
            <option id="C">South America</option>
            <option id="D">The Arabian Peninsula</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Every winter the famous Keoladeo National Park (Bharatpur) in Rajasthan host thousands of migratory birds coming from Siberia and other extremely cold northern regions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In bacteria, fungi and lower plants, various kinds of thick-walled spores are formed which help them to survive unfavourable conditions. What do these spores do when suitable environment returns?</text>
            <option id="A">They die</option>
            <option id="B">They undergo meiosis</option>
            <option id="C">They germinate</option>
            <option id="D">They form seeds</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Suspend: In bacteria, fungi and lower plants, various kinds of thick-walled spores are formed which help them to survive unfavourable conditions – these germinate on availability of suitable environment.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>