<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="335" name="Organisms and Populations">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>The process by which organisms maintain a constant internal environment despite fluctuating external environmental conditions is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Acclimatization</option>
            <option id="B">Homeostasis</option>
            <option id="C">Adaptation</option>
            <option id="D">Hibernation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Homeostasis is the process by which an organism tries to maintain the constancy of its internal environment (such as body temperature and osmotic concentration) despite varying external environmental conditions.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Organisms that can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Stenothermal</option>
            <option id="B">Eurythermal</option>
            <option id="C">Poikilothermal</option>
            <option id="D">Endothermal</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A few organisms can tolerate and thrive in a wide range of temperatures; they are called eurythermal. A vast majority of them are restricted to a narrow range of temperatures and are called stenothermal.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>An interaction between two species in which one is benefited and the other is neither harmed nor benefited is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Mutualism</option>
            <option id="B">Commensalism</option>
            <option id="C">Amensalism</option>
            <option id="D">Parasitism</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Commensalism is an interaction in which one species benefits and the other is neither harmed nor benefited. Example: an orchid growing as an epiphyte on a mango branch.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following describes an adaptation where an organism resembles its background to hide from predators?</text>
            <option id="A">Mimicry</option>
            <option id="B">Camouflage</option>
            <option id="C">Aestivation</option>
            <option id="D">Hibernation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Camouflage (cryptic coloration) is an adaptation where some species of insects and frogs are cryptically-coloured to avoid being detected easily by their predators.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which age pyramid shape represents a rapidly growing population?</text>
            <option id="A">Urn-shaped</option>
            <option id="B">Bell-shaped</option>
            <option id="C">Pyramid with a broad base</option>
            <option id="D">Spindle-shaped</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>A population pyramid with a broad base represents a rapidly growing population, as it indicates a high proportion of individuals in the pre-reproductive age group.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The type of interaction where one organism catches, kills, and eats another organism is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Parasitism</option>
            <option id="B">Predation</option>
            <option id="C">Amensalism</option>
            <option id="D">Competition</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Predation is nature's way of transferring to higher trophic levels the energy fixed by plants, where one organism (predator) catches, kills, and eats another organism (prey).</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>When a population grows in a habitat with limited resources, it exhibits a logistic growth curve. The equation for this curve is dN/dt = rN((K-N)/K). What does 'K' represent?</text>
            <option id="A">Intrinsic rate of natural increase</option>
            <option id="B">Carrying capacity</option>
            <option id="C">Population density at time t</option>
            <option id="D">Environmental resistance</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In the logistic growth equation, K represents the carrying capacity, which is the maximum population size of a biological species that can be sustained in that specific environment, given the food, habitat, water, and other necessities available.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of a morphological adaptation for minimizing water loss in desert plants?</text>
            <option id="A">Presence of a special photosynthetic pathway (CAM)</option>
            <option id="B">Leaves reduced to spines</option>
            <option id="C">Stomata that remain open during the day</option>
            <option id="D">Production of antifreeze proteins</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Many desert plants like Opuntia have their leaves reduced to spines to minimize water loss through transpiration, and the photosynthetic function is taken over by the flattened stems. CAM pathway is a physiological adaptation, not morphological.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Gause's 'Competitive Exclusion Principle' states that:</text>
            <option id="A">Two closely related species competing for the same resources can co-exist indefinitely.</option>
            <option id="B">Two closely related species competing for the same resources cannot co-exist indefinitely and the competitively inferior one will be eliminated.</option>
            <option id="C">Predators play an important role in maintaining species diversity in a community.</option>
            <option id="D">Parasites always evolve to become less virulent to their hosts over time.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Gause's 'Competitive Exclusion Principle' states that two closely related species competing for the same resources cannot co-exist indefinitely and the competitively inferior one will be eliminated eventually.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The association between a sea anemone and a clown fish is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Mutualism</option>
            <option id="B">Commensalism</option>
            <option id="C">Amensalism</option>
            <option id="D">Parasitism</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The interaction between sea anemone that has stinging tentacles and the clown fish that lives among them is an example of commensalism. The fish gets protection from predators, while the anemone does not appear to derive any benefit.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>If 'N' is the population density at time 't', then its density at time t+1 is: N_t+1 = N_t + [(B + I) - (D + E)]. What do B and E stand for respectively?</text>
            <option id="A">Birth rate and Emigration</option>
            <option id="B">Birth rate and Immigration</option>
            <option id="C">Biomass and Energy</option>
            <option id="D">Base rate and Extinction</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In the population density equation, B stands for the number of births (Birth rate), I for Immigration, D for Deaths (Death rate), and E for Emigration.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the principle of Allen's Rule?</text>
            <option id="A">Mammals from colder climates generally have shorter ears and limbs to minimize heat loss.</option>
            <option id="B">Animals in colder climates have thicker layers of fat.</option>
            <option id="C">Birds in warmer climates have longer wings.</option>
            <option id="D">Reptiles adapt to desert climates by becoming nocturnal.</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Allen's Rule states that mammals from colder climates generally have shorter ears and limbs to minimize heat loss.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following interactions is an example of amensalism?</text>
            <option id="A">A tick feeding on a dog</option>
            <option id="B">Penicillium secreting penicillin which kills nearby bacteria</option>
            <option id="C">A clownfish living among the tentacles of a sea anemone</option>
            <option id="D">Lichen</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Amensalism is an interaction where one species is harmed (-) and the other is unaffected (0). The classic example is the mold Penicillium secreting penicillin, which kills bacteria without Penicillium gaining any obvious benefit or harm from the interaction itself.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In altitude sickness, the body compensates for low oxygen availability by:</text>
            <option id="A">Increasing red blood cell production</option>
            <option id="B">Decreasing the breathing rate</option>
            <option id="C">Increasing the binding affinity of hemoglobin</option>
            <option id="D">Decreasing the heart rate</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The body compensates low oxygen availability at high altitudes by increasing red blood cell production, decreasing the binding affinity of hemoglobin, and by increasing breathing rate.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>MacArthur showed that five closely related species of warblers living on the same tree were able to avoid competition and co-exist. This was achieved through:</text>
            <option id="A">Competitive exclusion</option>
            <option id="B">Character displacement</option>
            <option id="C">Resource partitioning</option>
            <option id="D">Predation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>MacArthur showed that five closely related species of warblers living on the same tree were able to avoid competition and co-exist due to behavioral differences in their foraging activities, a mechanism known as resource partitioning.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Verhulst-Pearl logistic growth is described by a specific curve shape. What is the shape of this population growth curve?</text>
            <option id="A">J-shaped</option>
            <option id="B">Sigmoid (S-shaped)</option>
            <option id="C">U-shaped</option>
            <option id="D">Linear</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A population growing in a habitat with limited resources shows initially a lag phase, followed by phases of acceleration and deceleration, and finally an asymptote when the population density reaches the carrying capacity. A plot of N in relation to time t results in a sigmoid (S-shaped) curve.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the context of population attributes, if in a pond there were 20 lotus plants last year and through reproduction 8 new plants are added, taking the current population to 28, what is the birth rate?</text>
            <option id="A">0.4 offspring per lotus per year</option>
            <option id="B">0.8 offspring per lotus per year</option>
            <option id="C">2.5 offspring per lotus per year</option>
            <option id="D">8 offspring per lotus per year</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Birth rate is expressed as change in numbers (increase) with respect to members of the population. Here, the birth rate is 8 / 20 = 0.4 offspring per lotus per year.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The "Prickly Pear Cactus" introduced into Australia in the 1920s caused havoc by spreading rapidly into millions of hectares of rangeland. It was finally brought under control by introducing:</text>
            <option id="A">A competing plant species</option>
            <option id="B">A cactus-feeding moth</option>
            <option id="C">A fungal pathogen</option>
            <option id="D">A viral disease</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The prickly pear cactus introduced into Australia was finally brought under control only after a cactus-feeding predator (a moth) from its natural habitat was introduced into the country.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT an adaptation of parasites to their host?</text>
            <option id="A">Loss of unnecessary sense organs</option>
            <option id="B">Presence of adhesive organs or suckers</option>
            <option id="C">Development of a highly complex digestive system</option>
            <option id="D">High reproductive capacity</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Parasites often have a simple digestive system or lose it entirely because they absorb pre-digested nutrients directly from their host. They do not develop a complex digestive system.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Mediterranean orchid Ophrys employs which highly specialized mechanism to ensure pollination by bees?</text>
            <option id="A">Offering a safe place to lay eggs</option>
            <option id="B">Producing a high volume of concentrated nectar</option>
            <option id="C">Sexual deceit</option>
            <option id="D">Emitting a foul odor resembling rotting meat</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The Mediterranean orchid Ophrys employs 'sexual deceit'. One petal of its flower bears an uncanny resemblance to the female of the bee species in size, colour and markings. The male bee is attracted to what it perceives as a female, 'pseudocopulates' with the flower, and during that process is dusted with pollen.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>