<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="326" name="Reproductive Health">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a non-medicated IUD?</text>
            <option id="A">CuT</option>
            <option id="B">Lippes loop</option>
            <option id="C">Cu7</option>
            <option id="D">LNG-20</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Intra Uterine Devices (IUDs) are of three main types: non-medicated IUDs (e.g., Lippes loop), copper releasing IUDs (CuT, Cu7, Multiload 375), and the hormone releasing IUDs (Progestasert, LNG-20).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The technique in which sperm is directly injected into the ovum in the laboratory is called:</text>
            <option id="A">ZIFT</option>
            <option id="B">GIFT</option>
            <option id="C">ICSI</option>
            <option id="D">IUI</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>ICSI (Intra cytoplasmic sperm injection) is a specialized procedure to form an embryo in the laboratory in which a sperm is directly injected into the ovum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) is considered relatively safe up to how many weeks of pregnancy?</text>
            <option id="A">8 weeks</option>
            <option id="B">12 weeks</option>
            <option id="C">20 weeks</option>
            <option id="D">24 weeks</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>MTPs are considered relatively safe during the first trimester, i.e., up to 12 weeks of pregnancy. Second trimester abortions are much more risky.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The statutory ban on amniocentesis for sex-determination in India is primarily aimed at preventing:</text>
            <option id="A">Genetic disorders</option>
            <option id="B">Female foeticide</option>
            <option id="C">Maternal mortality</option>
            <option id="D">Multiple pregnancies</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Statutory ban on amniocentesis for sex-determination is to legally check increasing menace of female foeticide.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a barrier method of contraception?</text>
            <option id="A">Diaphragm</option>
            <option id="B">IUD</option>
            <option id="C">Oral pills</option>
            <option id="D">Tubectomy</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In barrier methods, ovum and sperms are prevented from physically meeting with the help of barriers. Diaphragms, cervical caps and vaults are barriers made of rubber that are inserted into the female reproductive tract.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the full form of RCH?</text>
            <option id="A">Reproductive and Child Health Care</option>
            <option id="B">Reproduction and Contraceptive Healthcare</option>
            <option id="C">Regional Child Health</option>
            <option id="D">Reproductive Care and Health</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>India was amongst the first countries in the world to initiate action plans and programmes at a national level to attain total reproductive health as a social goal. These programmes are currently in operation under the popular name 'Reproductive and Child Health Care (RCH) programmes'.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to the World Health Organisation (WHO), reproductive health means a total well-being in all aspects of reproduction. Which of the following is NOT typically listed as one of these aspects?</text>
            <option id="A">Physical</option>
            <option id="B">Emotional</option>
            <option id="C">Financial</option>
            <option id="D">Social</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>According to WHO, reproductive health means a total well-being in all aspects of reproduction, i.e., physical, emotional, behavioural and social. Financial aspect is not included in this definition.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of a natural method of contraception?</text>
            <option id="A">Condoms</option>
            <option id="B">Lactational amenorrhea</option>
            <option id="C">Copper T</option>
            <option id="D">Oral pills</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Natural methods work on the principle of avoiding chances of ovum and sperms meeting. Periodic abstinence, withdrawal or coitus interruptus, and lactational amenorrhea are natural methods.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the primary mechanism of action of copper-releasing IUDs like CuT?</text>
            <option id="A">They prevent ovulation.</option>
            <option id="B">They suppress sperm motility and the fertilising capacity of sperms.</option>
            <option id="C">They create a physical barrier at the cervix.</option>
            <option id="D">They alter the pH of the vagina.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>IUDs increase phagocytosis of sperms within the uterus and the Cu ions released suppress sperm motility and the fertilising capacity of sperms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to the World Health Organisation (WHO), reproductive health means a total well-being in all aspects of reproduction. Which of the following is NOT one of these aspects?</text>
            <option id="A">Physical</option>
            <option id="B">Emotional</option>
            <option id="C">Financial</option>
            <option id="D">Social</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>According to the World Health Organisation (WHO), reproductive health means a total well-being in all aspects of reproduction, i.e., physical, emotional, behavioural and social.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>India was amongst the first countries in the world to initiate action plans and programmes at a national level to attain total reproductive health as a social goal. In which year were these programmes called 'family planning' initiated?</text>
            <option id="A">1947</option>
            <option id="B">1951</option>
            <option id="C">1965</option>
            <option id="D">1971</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>India was amongst the first countries in the world to initiate action plans and programmes at a national level to attain total reproductive health as a social goal. These programmes called 'family planning' were initiated in 1951.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A statutory ban on which of the following procedures has been implemented in India to check increasing female foeticides?</text>
            <option id="A">Ultrasound</option>
            <option id="B">Amniocentesis for sex-determination</option>
            <option id="C">MRI scans</option>
            <option id="D">X-rays</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Statutory ban on amniocentesis for sex-determination to legally check increasing female foeticides, massive child immunisation, etc., are some programmes that merit mention in this connection.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In India, what is the statutory marriageable age for females and males, respectively?</text>
            <option id="A">18 years for females and 21 years for males</option>
            <option id="B">21 years for females and 18 years for males</option>
            <option id="C">18 years for both females and males</option>
            <option id="D">21 years for both females and males</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Statutory raising of marriageable age of the female to 18 years and that of males to 21 years, and incentives given to couples with small families are two of the other measures taken to tackle this problem of population growth.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a natural method of contraception that involves avoiding coitus from day 10 to 17 of the menstrual cycle?</text>
            <option id="A">Coitus interruptus</option>
            <option id="B">Lactational amenorrhea</option>
            <option id="C">Periodic abstinence</option>
            <option id="D">Withdrawal method</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Periodic abstinence is one such method in which the couples avoid or abstain from coitus from day 10 to 17 of the menstrual cycle when ovulation could be expected. As chances of fertilisation are very high during this period, it is called the fertile period.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Lactational amenorrhea is a natural method of contraception. It is effective only up to a maximum period of how many months following parturition?</text>
            <option id="A">Three months</option>
            <option id="B">Six months</option>
            <option id="C">Nine months</option>
            <option id="D">Twelve months</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Lactational amenorrhea (absence of menstruation) method is based on the fact that ovulation and therefore the cycle do not occur during the period of intense lactation following parturition. However, this method has been reported to be effective only upto a maximum period of six months following parturition.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act was legalized by the Government of India in which year, with strict conditions to avoid its misuse?</text>
            <option id="A">1951</option>
            <option id="B">1971</option>
            <option id="C">1981</option>
            <option id="D">2001</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Government of India legalised MTP in 1971 with some strict conditions to avoid its misuse. Such restrictions are all the more important to check indiscriminate and illegal female foeticides which are reported to be high in India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>MTPs are considered relatively safe during which trimester of pregnancy?</text>
            <option id="A">First trimester (up to 12 weeks of pregnancy)</option>
            <option id="B">Second trimester</option>
            <option id="C">Third trimester</option>
            <option id="D">Only during the first 4 weeks</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>MTPs are considered relatively safe during the first trimester, i.e., upto 12 weeks of pregnancy. Second trimester abortions are much more riskier.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a Sexually Transmitted Infection (STI)?</text>
            <option id="A">Gonorrhoea</option>
            <option id="B">Syphilis</option>
            <option id="C">Typhoid</option>
            <option id="D">Genital herpes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Diseases or infections which are transmitted through sexual intercourse are collectively called sexually transmitted infections (STI) or venereal diseases (VD) or reproductive tract infections (RTI). Gonorrhoea, syphilis, genital herpes, chlamydiasis, genital warts, trichomoniasis, hepatitis-B and of course, the most discussed infection in the recent years, HIV leading to AIDS are some of the common STIs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to the World Health Organisation (WHO), reproductive health means a total well-being in all aspects of reproduction, which includes:</text>
            <option id="A">Physical and emotional only</option>
            <option id="B">Physical, emotional, behavioural and social</option>
            <option id="C">Physical and social only</option>
            <option id="D">Emotional and social only</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>According to the World Health Organisation (WHO), reproductive health means a total well-being in all aspects of reproduction, i.e., physical, emotional, behavioural and social.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>India initiated family planning programmes in which year?</text>
            <option id="A">1947</option>
            <option id="B">1951</option>
            <option id="C">1965</option>
            <option id="D">1971</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>India was amongst the first countries in the world to initiate action plans and programmes at a national level to attain total reproductive health as a social goal. These programmes called 'family planning' were initiated in 1951 and were periodically assessed over the past decades.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A statutory ban on which technique was necessary to check increasing menace of female foeticides in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Ultrasound</option>
            <option id="B">Amniocentesis</option>
            <option id="C">In vitro fertilization (IVF)</option>
            <option id="D">Artificial insemination</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Statutory ban on amniocentesis for sex-determination to legally check increasing menace of female foeticides, massive child immunisation, etc., are some programmes that merit mention in this connection.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Amniocentesis is a medical procedure used primarily for:</text>
            <option id="A">Sex determination of the foetus</option>
            <option id="B">Detecting chromosomal abnormalities and certain genetic disorders</option>
            <option id="C">Inducing abortion</option>
            <option id="D">Preventing sexually transmitted infections</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Amniocentesis is a foetal sex determination and disorder test based on the chromosomal pattern in the amniotic fluid surrounding the developing embryo. It is meant to detect any genetic disorder like Down syndrome, haemophilia, sickle-cell anemia, etc., and to determine the survivability of the foetus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which fluid is extracted during amniocentesis for the purpose of genetic testing?</text>
            <option id="A">Cerebrospinal fluid</option>
            <option id="B">Amniotic fluid</option>
            <option id="C">Blood plasma</option>
            <option id="D">Lymph</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In amniocentesis some of the amniotic fluid of the developing foetus is taken to analyse the fetal cells and dissolved substances.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Research on various reproduction-related areas is encouraged and supported by governmental and non-governmental agencies. The Central Drug Research Institute (CDRI), which developed 'Saheli', is located in:</text>
            <option id="A">New Delhi</option>
            <option id="B">Mumbai</option>
            <option id="C">Lucknow</option>
            <option id="D">Chennai</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Research on various reproduction-related areas are encouraged and supported by governmental and non-governmental agencies to find out new methods and/or to improve upon the existing ones. Do you know that 'Saheli'–a new oral contraceptive for the females–was developed by scientists at Central Drug Research Institute (CDRI) in Lucknow, India?</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Contraceptive methods are broadly grouped into several categories. Which of the following is NOT one of these broad categories?</text>
            <option id="A">Natural/Traditional</option>
            <option id="B">Barrier</option>
            <option id="C">IUDs (Intra Uterine Devices)</option>
            <option id="D">Gene therapy</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>A wide range of contraceptive methods are presently available which could be broadly grouped into the following categories, namely Natural/Traditional, Barrier, IUDs, Oral contraceptives, Injectables, Implants and Surgical methods.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Natural methods of contraception work on the principle of avoiding chances of:</text>
            <option id="A">Ovum and sperms meeting</option>
            <option id="B">Implantation of the blastocyst</option>
            <option id="C">Sperm production</option>
            <option id="D">Ovulation occurring</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Natural methods work on the principle of avoiding chances of ovum and sperms meeting. Periodic abstinence is one such method in which the couples avoid or abstain from coitus from day 10 to 17 of the menstrual cycle.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the 'periodic abstinence' method, couples avoid coitus from day 10 to 17 of the menstrual cycle because during this period:</text>
            <option id="A">The chance of fertilization is very low</option>
            <option id="B">Ovulation could be expected and chances of fertilisation are very high</option>
            <option id="C">Menstruation occurs</option>
            <option id="D">Sperm count is lowest</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Periodic abstinence is one such method in which the couples avoid or abstain from coitus from day 10 to 17 of the menstrual cycle when ovulation could be expected. As chances of fertilisation are very high during this period, it is called the fertile period.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is another popular name for Intra Uterine Devices (IUDs) like Lippes loop?</text>
            <option id="A">Oral pills</option>
            <option id="B">Non-medicated IUDs</option>
            <option id="C">Copper releasing IUDs</option>
            <option id="D">Hormone releasing IUDs</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>These devices are inserted by doctors or expert nurses in the uterus through vagina. These Intra Uterine Devices are presently available as the non-medicated IUDs (e.g., Lippes loop)...</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>CuT, Cu7, and Multiload 375 are examples of which type of contraceptive method?</text>
            <option id="A">Barrier methods</option>
            <option id="B">Copper releasing IUDs</option>
            <option id="C">Hormone releasing IUDs</option>
            <option id="D">Oral contraceptives</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>These Intra Uterine Devices are presently available as... copper releasing IUDs (CuT, Cu7, Multiload 375)...</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Progestasert and LNG-20 are examples of which type of Intra Uterine Devices (IUDs)?</text>
            <option id="A">Non-medicated IUDs</option>
            <option id="B">Copper releasing IUDs</option>
            <option id="C">Hormone releasing IUDs</option>
            <option id="D">Barrier IUDs</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>These Intra Uterine Devices are presently available as... and the hormone releasing IUDs (Progestasert, LNG-20).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Some contraceptive pills like 'Saheli' are taken only once a week. What is a key characteristic of Saheli?</text>
            <option id="A">It is highly steroidal</option>
            <option id="B">It has high side effects</option>
            <option id="C">It contains a non-steroidal preparation</option>
            <option id="D">It has a low contraceptive value</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Saheli –the new oral contraceptive for the females– contains a non-steroidal preparation. It is a 'once a week' pill with very few side effects and high contraceptive value.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Progestogens alone or in combination with estrogen can be used by females as injections or implants under the skin. How does their mode of action compare to oral pills?</text>
            <option id="A">It is completely different</option>
            <option id="B">It is exactly the same</option>
            <option id="C">It relies on a physical barrier</option>
            <option id="D">It only kills sperms</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Progestogens alone or in combination with estrogen can also be used by females as injections or implants under the skin... Their mode of action is similar to that of pills and their effective periods are much longer.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Administration of progestogens or progestogen-estrogen combinations or IUDs within how many hours of coitus have been found to be very effective as emergency contraceptives?</text>
            <option id="A">24 hours</option>
            <option id="B">48 hours</option>
            <option id="C">72 hours</option>
            <option id="D">1 week</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Administration of progestogens or progestogen-estrogen combinations or IUDs within 72 hours of coitus have been found to be very effective as emergency contraceptives as they could be used to avoid possible pregnancy due to rape or casual unprotected intercourse.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Medical termination of pregnancy (MTP) was legalised in India in which year, with some strict conditions to avoid its misuse?</text>
            <option id="A">1951</option>
            <option id="B">1971</option>
            <option id="C">1981</option>
            <option id="D">1991</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Government of India legalised MTP in 1971 with some strict conditions to avoid its misuse.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>MTPs are considered relatively safe during which trimester of pregnancy?</text>
            <option id="A">First trimester</option>
            <option id="B">Second trimester</option>
            <option id="C">Third trimester</option>
            <option id="D">Safe during any trimester</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>MTPs are considered relatively safe during the first trimester, i.e., upto 12 weeks of pregnancy. Second trimester abortions are much more riskier.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Why are second trimester abortions considered much more risky than first trimester ones?</text>
            <option id="A">Because the fetus is larger and more developed</option>
            <option id="B">Because the mother's immune system rejects it</option>
            <option id="C">Because the amniotic fluid is toxic</option>
            <option id="D">Because the placenta is fully formed</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Second trimester abortions are much more riskier.</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>How do copper-releasing IUDs prevent conception?</text>
            <option id="A">They suppress sperm motility and the fertilizing capacity of sperms.</option>
            <option id="B">They make the uterus unsuitable for implantation.</option>
            <option id="C">They inhibit ovulation.</option>
            <option id="D">They block the entry of sperms through the cervix.</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>IUDs increase phagocytosis of sperms within the uterus and the Cu ions released suppress sperm motility and the fertilising capacity of sperms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the context of ART, what does ZIFT stand for?</text>
            <option id="A">Zygote internal fallopian transfer</option>
            <option id="B">Zygote intra fallopian transfer</option>
            <option id="C">Zygote in vitro fertilization technique</option>
            <option id="D">Zygote inter fallopian transfer</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>ZIFT stands for Zygote intra fallopian transfer. In this technique, the zygote or early embryos (with up to 8 blastomeres) are transferred into the fallopian tube.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following sexually transmitted infections is completely curable if detected early and treated properly?</text>
            <option id="A">Hepatitis-B</option>
            <option id="B">Genital herpes</option>
            <option id="C">HIV infections</option>
            <option id="D">Syphilis</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Except for hepatitis-B, genital herpes and HIV infections, other sexually transmitted diseases (like syphilis, gonorrhoea, chlamydiasis) are completely curable if detected early and treated properly.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Saheli, an oral contraceptive pill for females, contains a non-steroidal preparation and is taken:</text>
            <option id="A">Daily</option>
            <option id="B">Weekly</option>
            <option id="C">Monthly</option>
            <option id="D">Only after coitus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>'Saheli' is a new oral contraceptive for the females. It contains a non-steroidal preparation. It is a 'once a week' pill with very few side effects and high contraceptive value.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following hormone-releasing IUDs makes the uterus unsuitable for implantation and the cervix hostile to the sperms?</text>
            <option id="A">Lippes loop</option>
            <option id="B">CuT</option>
            <option id="C">Multiload 375</option>
            <option id="D">LNG-20</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The hormone releasing IUDs, such as Progestasert and LNG-20, make the uterus unsuitable for implantation and the cervix hostile to the sperms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The surgical method of contraception in males is called vasectomy. In this procedure, a small part of the:</text>
            <option id="A">Epididymis is removed or tied up</option>
            <option id="B">Vas deferens is removed or tied up</option>
            <option id="C">Urethra is blocked</option>
            <option id="D">Seminal vesicle is removed</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In vasectomy, a small part of the vas deferens is removed or tied up through a small incision on the scrotum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Emergency contraceptives can be used to prevent pregnancy if taken within how many hours of unprotected coitus?</text>
            <option id="A">24 hours</option>
            <option id="B">48 hours</option>
            <option id="C">72 hours</option>
            <option id="D">7 days</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Administration of progestogens or progestogen-estrogen combinations or IUDs within 72 hours of coitus have been found to be very effective as emergency contraceptives.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following ART procedures involves the transfer of an ovum collected from a donor into the fallopian tube of another female who cannot produce one?</text>
            <option id="A">ZIFT</option>
            <option id="B">GIFT</option>
            <option id="C">ICSI</option>
            <option id="D">IUI</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>GIFT stands for Gamete intra fallopian transfer. It is the transfer of an ovum collected from a donor into the fallopian tube of another female who cannot produce one, but can provide suitable environment for fertilization and further development.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the major component of the widely used oral contraceptive pills for females?</text>
            <option id="A">Progestogens or progestogen-estrogen combinations</option>
            <option id="B">Only high doses of estrogen</option>
            <option id="C">FSH and LH</option>
            <option id="D">Testosterone derivatives</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Oral administration of small doses of either progestogens or progestogen-estrogen combinations is another contraceptive method used by the females. They are used in the form of tablets and hence are popularly called the pills.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The surgical method of contraception in females is called tubectomy. In this procedure, a small part of the:</text>
            <option id="A">Uterus is removed</option>
            <option id="B">Ovary is removed</option>
            <option id="C">Fallopian tube is removed or tied up</option>
            <option id="D">Cervix is blocked</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In tubectomy, a small part of the fallopian tube is removed or tied up through a small incision in the abdomen or through vagina.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) was legalized in India in which year?</text>
            <option id="A">1951</option>
            <option id="B">1971</option>
            <option id="C">1981</option>
            <option id="D">1991</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Government of India legalised MTP in 1971 with some strict conditions to avoid its misuse.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following sexually transmitted infections is completely curable if detected early and treated properly?</text>
            <option id="A">Hepatitis-B</option>
            <option id="B">Genital herpes</option>
            <option id="C">HIV infections</option>
            <option id="D">Syphilis</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Except for hepatitis-B, genital herpes and HIV infections, other diseases (like syphilis, gonorrhoea, chlamydiasis, etc.) are completely curable if detected early and treated properly.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of a barrier method of contraception used by females?</text>
            <option id="A">Condoms</option>
            <option id="B">Diaphragms, cervical caps and vaults</option>
            <option id="C">Lippes loop</option>
            <option id="D">Multiload 375</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Diaphragms, cervical caps and vaults are also barriers made of rubber that are inserted into the female reproductive tract to cover the cervix during coitus. They prevent conception by blocking the entry of sperms through the cervix.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Intra Uterine Devices (IUDs) are currently one of the most widely accepted methods of contraception in India. Which of the following is a hormone-releasing IUD?</text>
            <option id="A">Lippes loop</option>
            <option id="B">CuT</option>
            <option id="C">LNG-20</option>
            <option id="D">Multiload 375</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>These devices are presently available as the non-medicated IUDs (e.g., Lippes loop), copper releasing IUDs (CuT, Cu7, Multiload 375) and the hormone releasing IUDs (Progestasert, LNG-20).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How do copper-releasing IUDs primarily prevent conception?</text>
            <option id="A">They suppress sperm motility and the fertilising capacity of sperms.</option>
            <option id="B">They make the uterus unsuitable for implantation.</option>
            <option id="C">They inhibit ovulation.</option>
            <option id="D">They block the fallopian tubes.</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>IUDs increase phagocytosis of sperms within the uterus and the Cu ions released suppress sperm motility and the fertilising capacity of sperms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Oral contraceptive pills have to be taken daily for a period of 21 days starting preferably within the first five days of the menstrual cycle. What do these pills primarily contain?</text>
            <option id="A">Only estrogen</option>
            <option id="B">Progestogens or progestogen-estrogen combinations</option>
            <option id="C">Follicle Stimulating Hormone (FSH)</option>
            <option id="D">Luteinizing Hormone (LH)</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Oral administration of small doses of either progestogens or progestogen-estrogen combinations is another contraceptive method used by the females. They are used in the form of tablets and hence are popularly called the pills.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following barrier methods of contraception also protects the user from contracting STIs and AIDS?</text>
            <option id="A">Diaphragms</option>
            <option id="B">Cervical caps</option>
            <option id="C">Condoms</option>
            <option id="D">Vaults</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Condoms are barriers made of thin rubber/latex sheath that are used to cover the penis in the male or vagina and cervix in the female. Both the male and the female condoms are disposable, can be self-inserted and thereby gives privacy to the user. Use of condoms has increased in recent years due to its additional benefit of protecting the user from contracting STIs and AIDS.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Saheli is an oral contraceptive pill for females that was developed by scientists at CDRI, Lucknow. What makes it unique?</text>
            <option id="A">It is taken daily and is steroidal</option>
            <option id="B">It is a once-a-week pill and is non-steroidal</option>
            <option id="C">It contains only estrogen</option>
            <option id="D">It is administered via injection</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Saheli-the new oral contraceptive for the females-contains a non-steroidal preparation. It is a 'once a week' pill with very few side effects and high contraceptive value.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Surgical methods, also called sterilisation, are generally advised for the male/female partner as a terminal method to prevent any more pregnancies. The sterilisation procedure in males is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Tubectomy</option>
            <option id="B">Vasectomy</option>
            <option id="C">Oophorectomy</option>
            <option id="D">Hysterectomy</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Sterilisation procedure in the male is called 'vasectomy' and that in the female, 'tubectomy'. In vasectomy, a small part of the vas deferens is removed or tied up through a small incision on the scrotum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the tubectomy procedure for female sterilisation, which part of the reproductive system is removed or tied up?</text>
            <option id="A">Ovary</option>
            <option id="B">Fallopian tube</option>
            <option id="C">Uterus</option>
            <option id="D">Cervix</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In tubectomy, a small part of the fallopian tube is removed or tied up through a small incision in the abdomen or through vagina.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Except for which three diseases, are all other Sexually Transmitted Infections completely curable if detected early and treated properly?</text>
            <option id="A">Syphilis, Gonorrhoea, and Chlamydiasis</option>
            <option id="B">Hepatitis-B, Genital herpes, and HIV infections</option>
            <option id="C">Genital warts, Trichomoniasis, and Syphilis</option>
            <option id="D">Gonorrhoea, HIV, and Genital herpes</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Except for hepatitis-B, genital herpes and HIV infections, other diseases are completely curable if detected early and treated properly.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a symptom of early-stage Sexually Transmitted Infections (STIs)?</text>
            <option id="A">Pelvic Inflammatory Diseases (PID)</option>
            <option id="B">Ectopic pregnancies</option>
            <option id="C">Itching, fluid discharge, slight pain, and swellings in the genital region</option>
            <option id="D">Infertility or cancer of the reproductive tract</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Early symptoms of most of these are minor and include itching, fluid discharge, slight pain, swellings, etc., in the genital region. Pelvic inflammatory diseases, ectopic pregnancies, infertility or even cancer are later complications.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>STIs are reported to be very high among persons in the age group of:</text>
            <option id="A">10-14 years</option>
            <option id="B">15-24 years</option>
            <option id="C">25-40 years</option>
            <option id="D">40-55 years</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Incidences of these infections are reported to be very high among persons in the age group of 15-24 years - the age group to which you also belong.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Assisted Reproductive Technology (ART) procedure known as IUT stands for:</text>
            <option id="A">Intra Uterine Transfer</option>
            <option id="B">Intra Uterine Test</option>
            <option id="C">Internal Uterine Therapy</option>
            <option id="D">Intra Uterine Tube</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In vitro fertilisation (IVF-fertilisation outside the body in almost similar conditions as that in the body) followed by embryo transfer (ET) is one of such methods. The zygote or early embryos (with upto 8 blastomeres) could then be transferred into the fallopian tube (ZIFT) and embryos with more than 8 blastomeres, into the uterus (IUT - intra uterine transfer), to complete its further development.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the principle of natural methods of contraception?</text>
            <option id="A">Preventing ovulation</option>
            <option id="B">Avoiding chances of ovum and sperms meeting</option>
            <option id="C">Killing the sperms in the vagina</option>
            <option id="D">Preventing implantation of the embryo</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Natural methods work on the principle of avoiding chances of ovum and sperms meeting. Periodic abstinence is one such method in which the couples avoid or abstain from coitus from day 10 to 17 of the menstrual cycle when ovulation could be expected.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a barrier method of contraception that also protects the user from contracting STIs and AIDS?</text>
            <option id="A">Diaphragms</option>
            <option id="B">Cervical caps</option>
            <option id="C">Condoms</option>
            <option id="D">Vaults</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Condoms are barriers made of thin rubber/ latex sheath that are used to cover the penis in the male or vagina and cervix in the female, just before coitus so that the ejaculated semen would not enter into the female reproductive tract. This can prevent conception. Use of condoms has increased in recent years due to its additional benefit of protecting the user from contracting STIs and AIDS.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Intra Uterine Devices (IUDs) are inserted by doctors or expert nurses in the uterus through the vagina. Which of the following is a hormone-releasing IUD?</text>
            <option id="A">Lippes loop</option>
            <option id="B">CuT</option>
            <option id="C">Multiload 375</option>
            <option id="D">LNG-20</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Another effective and popular method is the use of Intra Uterine Devices (IUDs). These devices are inserted by doctors or expert nurses in the uterus through vagina. These Intra Uterine Devices are presently available as the non-medicated IUDs (e.g., Lippes loop), copper releasing IUDs (CuT, Cu7, Multiload 375) and the hormone releasing IUDs (Progestasert, LNG-20).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How do copper-releasing IUDs prevent conception?</text>
            <option id="A">They make the uterus unsuitable for implantation</option>
            <option id="B">They suppress sperm motility and the fertilising capacity of sperms</option>
            <option id="C">They inhibit ovulation</option>
            <option id="D">They block the fallopian tubes</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>IUDs increase phagocytosis of sperms within the uterus and the Cu ions released suppress sperm motility and the fertilising capacity of sperms. The hormone releasing IUDs, in addition, make the uterus unsuitable for implantation and the cervix hostile to the sperms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered an indicator of improved reproductive health of a society?</text>
            <option id="A">Increased maternal and infant mortality rates</option>
            <option id="B">Decreased number of medically assisted deliveries</option>
            <option id="C">Better detection and cure of STIs</option>
            <option id="D">Larger family sizes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Better awareness about sex related matters, increased number of medically assisted deliveries and better post-natal care leading to decreased maternal and infant mortality rates, increased number of couples with small families, better detection and cure of STIs and overall increased medical facilities for all sex-related problems, etc. all indicate improved reproductive health of the society.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What was the world population around the year 1900?</text>
            <option id="A">1 billion</option>
            <option id="B">2 billion</option>
            <option id="C">3 billion</option>
            <option id="D">6 billion</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The world population which was around 2 billion (2000 million) in 1900 rocketed to about 6 billion by 2000 and 7.2 billion in 2011.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A rapid decline in death rate, maternal mortality rate (MMR), and infant mortality rate (IMR), along with an increase in the number of people in reproducible age, are probable reasons for:</text>
            <option id="A">Population explosion</option>
            <option id="B">Population stabilization</option>
            <option id="C">Population decline</option>
            <option id="D">Zero population growth</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>A rapid decline in death rate, maternal mortality rate (MMR) and infant mortality rate (IMR) as well as an increase in number of people in reproducible age are probable reasons for this [population explosion].</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>According to the 2011 census report, the population growth rate of India was less than:</text>
            <option id="A">1 per cent</option>
            <option id="B">2 per cent</option>
            <option id="C">3 per cent</option>
            <option id="D">4 per cent</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>According to the 2011 census report, the population growth rate was less than 2 per cent, i.e., 20/1000/year, a rate at which our population could increase rapidly.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The withdrawal method of contraception, where the male partner withdraws his penis from the vagina just before ejaculation, is also known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Periodic abstinence</option>
            <option id="B">Coitus interruptus</option>
            <option id="C">Lactational amenorrhea</option>
            <option id="D">Rhythm method</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Withdrawal or coitus interruptus is another method in which the male partner withdraws his penis from the vagina just before ejaculation so as to avoid insemination.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Lactational amenorrhea is a natural method of contraception based on the fact that:</text>
            <option id="A">Ovulation and the menstrual cycle do not occur during the period of intense lactation following parturition</option>
            <option id="B">Sperm cannot survive in the female reproductive tract during lactation</option>
            <option id="C">The cervical mucus becomes too thick for sperms to pass</option>
            <option id="D">Breastfeeding destroys sperm</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Lactational amenorrhea (absence of menstruation) method is based on the fact that ovulation and therefore the cycle do not occur during the period of intense lactation following parturition.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How long is the lactational amenorrhea method generally considered effective following parturition?</text>
            <option id="A">Up to 1 year</option>
            <option id="B">Up to a maximum period of six months</option>
            <option id="C">Up to 3 months</option>
            <option id="D">For as long as the mother breastfeeds</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Therefore, as long as the mother breast-feeds the child fully, chances of conception are almost nil. However, this method has been reported to be effective only upto a maximum period of six months following parturition.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In barrier methods of contraception, what is used to prevent the ovum and sperms from physically meeting?</text>
            <option id="A">Hormones</option>
            <option id="B">Chemicals that kill sperm</option>
            <option id="C">Barriers like condoms</option>
            <option id="D">Intrauterine devices</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In barrier methods, ovum and sperms are prevented from physically meeting with the help of barriers. Such methods are available for both males and females.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How do Intra Uterine Devices (IUDs) primarily work to prevent conception?</text>
            <option id="A">By preventing ovulation</option>
            <option id="B">By blocking the fallopian tubes</option>
            <option id="C">By increasing phagocytosis of sperms within the uterus</option>
            <option id="D">By killing the ovum</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>IUDs increase phagocytosis of sperms within the uterus and the Cu ions released suppress sperm motility and the fertilising capacity of sperms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In copper-releasing IUDs, what is the specific role of the copper ions?</text>
            <option id="A">They stimulate the release of estrogen</option>
            <option id="B">They suppress sperm motility and the fertilising capacity of sperms</option>
            <option id="C">They prevent the implantation of the embryo</option>
            <option id="D">They cause early menstruation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>IUDs increase phagocytosis of sperms within the uterus and the Cu ions released suppress sperm motility and the fertilising capacity of sperms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How do hormone-releasing IUDs act to prevent pregnancy?</text>
            <option id="A">They make the uterus unsuitable for implantation and the cervix hostile to the sperms</option>
            <option id="B">They kill all sperms entering the vagina</option>
            <option id="C">They induce abortion</option>
            <option id="D">They physically block the entrance to the cervix</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The hormone releasing IUDs, in addition, make the uterus unsuitable for implantation and the cervix hostile to the sperms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Oral contraceptives for females usually contain small doses of which hormones?</text>
            <option id="A">Testosterone and FSH</option>
            <option id="B">Oxytocin and prolactin</option>
            <option id="C">Progestogens or progestogen-estrogen combinations</option>
            <option id="D">LH and GnRH</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Oral administration of small doses of either progestogens or progestogen-estrogen combinations is another contraceptive method used by the females.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Surgical methods of contraception are generally advised as a terminal method to prevent any more pregnancies. What is the surgical method in males called?</text>
            <option id="A">Tubectomy</option>
            <option id="B">Vasectomy</option>
            <option id="C">Hysterectomy</option>
            <option id="D">Castration</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Surgical methods, also called sterilisation, are generally advised for the male/female partner as a terminal method to prevent any more pregnancies... Sterilisation procedure in the male is called 'vasectomy'.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the surgical method of sterilization in females called?</text>
            <option id="A">Tubectomy</option>
            <option id="B">Vasectomy</option>
            <option id="C">Oophorectomy</option>
            <option id="D">Cervical cap</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Sterilisation procedure in the male is called 'vasectomy' and that in the female, 'tubectomy'.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In vasectomy, a small part of which structure is removed or tied up through a small incision on the scrotum?</text>
            <option id="A">Epididymis</option>
            <option id="B">Urethra</option>
            <option id="C">Vas deferens</option>
            <option id="D">Seminal vesicle</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In vasectomy, a small part of the vas deferens is removed or tied up through a small incision on the scrotum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In tubectomy, a small part of the fallopian tube is removed or tied up. How is this typically accessed?</text>
            <option id="A">Through the mouth</option>
            <option id="B">Through a small incision in the abdomen or through vagina</option>
            <option id="C">Through the urethra</option>
            <option id="D">Through the rectum</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In tubectomy, a small part of the fallopian tube is removed or tied up through a small incision in the abdomen or through vagina.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>One of the most disturbing trends associated with MTP in India is that a majority of them are performed illegally by unqualified quacks. What is another dangerous trend related to MTP misuse?</text>
            <option id="A">Using it to select for male babies</option>
            <option id="B">Using it as a primary contraceptive method</option>
            <option id="C">Using it to determine the blood group</option>
            <option id="D">Using it for IVF</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Another dangerous trend is the misuse of amniocentesis to determine the sex of the unborn child. Frequently, if the foetus is found to be female, it is followed by MTP- this is totally against what is legal.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Diseases or infections which are transmitted through sexual intercourse are collectively called Sexually Transmitted Infections (STIs). What is another term for STIs?</text>
            <option id="A">Venereal diseases (VD)</option>
            <option id="B">Congenital diseases</option>
            <option id="C">Autoimmune diseases</option>
            <option id="D">Vector-borne diseases</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Diseases or infections which are transmitted through sexual intercourse are collectively called sexually transmitted infections (STI) or venereal diseases (VD) or reproductive tract infections (RTI).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a Sexually Transmitted Infection?</text>
            <option id="A">Gonorrhoea</option>
            <option id="B">Syphilis</option>
            <option id="C">Genital herpes</option>
            <option id="D">Typhoid</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Gonorrhoea, syphilis, genital herpes, chlamydiasis, genital warts, trichomoniasis, hepatitis-B and of course, the most discussed infection in the recent years, HIV leading to AIDS are some of the common STIs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Among all the Sexually Transmitted Infections, which one is considered the most dangerous?</text>
            <option id="A">Syphilis</option>
            <option id="B">HIV infection</option>
            <option id="C">Hepatitis-B</option>
            <option id="D">Gonorrhoea</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Among these, HIV infection is most dangerous and is discussed in detail in Chapter 8.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following statements about amniocentesis is INCORRECT?</text>
            <option id="A">It can be used to detect Down syndrome.</option>
            <option id="B">It is based on the chromosomal pattern in the amniotic fluid.</option>
            <option id="C">It is primarily intended to determine the sex of the unborn child.</option>
            <option id="D">It can be used to detect hemophilia.</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Amniocentesis is a fetal sex determination and disorder test based on the chromosomal pattern in the amniotic fluid. However, its primary and legal purpose is to test for the presence of certain genetic disorders (like Down syndrome, hemophilia, sickle-cell anemia), NOT to determine the sex of the child, which is illegal as it leads to female foeticide.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In vivo fertilization followed by embryo transfer (ET) is useful for females who:</text>
            <option id="A">Cannot produce an ovum</option>
            <option id="B">Cannot provide a suitable environment for fertilization but can retain the embryo</option>
            <option id="C">Cannot conceive naturally but can provide a suitable environment for the further development of the embryo</option>
            <option id="D">Have blocked fallopian tubes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In vivo fertilization is the fusion of gametes within the female. Embryos formed by in-vivo fertilisation can be used for transfer to assist those females who cannot conceive naturally but can provide suitable environment for further development.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The natural method of contraception known as 'Lactational amenorrhea' is effective up to a maximum period of:</text>
            <option id="A">Three months</option>
            <option id="B">Six months</option>
            <option id="C">Twelve months</option>
            <option id="D">Two years</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Lactational amenorrhea (absence of menstruation) method is based on the fact that ovulation does not occur during the period of intense lactation following parturition. However, this method has been reported to be effective only up to a maximum period of six months following parturition.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following correctly pairs a sexually transmitted disease with its causative agent?</text>
            <option id="A">Syphilis - Neisseria gonorrhoeae</option>
            <option id="B">Gonorrhoea - Treponema pallidum</option>
            <option id="C">Genital warts - Human papilloma virus (HPV)</option>
            <option id="D">Chlamydiasis - Trichomonas vaginalis</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Genital warts are caused by HPV. Syphilis is caused by Treponema pallidum, Gonorrhoea by Neisseria gonorrhoeae, and Chlamydiasis by Chlamydia trachomatis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During the "fertile period" (day 10 to 17 of the menstrual cycle), couples avoid coitus to prevent conception. This method is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Coitus interruptus</option>
            <option id="B">Periodic abstinence</option>
            <option id="C">Lactational amenorrhea</option>
            <option id="D">Rhythm method</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Periodic abstinence is one such method in which the couples avoid or abstain from coitus from day 10 to 17 of the menstrual cycle when ovulation could be expected. As chances of fertilisation are very high during this period, it is called the fertile period.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following points is INCORRECT regarding MTPs in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Government of India legalized MTP in 1971 with some strict conditions.</option>
            <option id="B">MTP is completely safe even during the third trimester.</option>
            <option id="C">It is an essential method to get rid of unwanted pregnancies.</option>
            <option id="D">MTP is also essential in certain cases where continuation of the pregnancy could be harmful or even fatal either to the mother or to the foetus or both.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>MTPs are considered relatively safe during the first trimester, i.e., up to 12 weeks of pregnancy. Second trimester abortions are much more risky, and they are not safe during the third trimester.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the context of Assisted Reproductive Technologies (ART), what does IVF stand for?</text>
            <option id="A">Intra Vaginal Fertilisation</option>
            <option id="B">In Vivo Fertilisation</option>
            <option id="C">In Vitro Fertilisation</option>
            <option id="D">Intra Vas Deferens Fertilisation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>IVF stands for In vitro fertilisation. It is the fertilisation outside the body in almost similar conditions as that in the body.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During ZIFT (Zygote Intra Fallopian Transfer), the zygote or early embryos up to how many blastomeres are transferred into the fallopian tube?</text>
            <option id="A">4 blastomeres</option>
            <option id="B">8 blastomeres</option>
            <option id="C">16 blastomeres</option>
            <option id="D">32 blastomeres</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The zygote or early embryos (with upto 8 blastomeres) could then be transferred into the fallopian tube (ZIFT-zygote intra fallopian transfer) and embryos with more than 8 blastomeres, into the uterus (IUT - intra uterine transfer).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Artificial Insemination (AI) technique is primarily useful when the:</text>
            <option id="A">Female has blocked fallopian tubes</option>
            <option id="B">Female cannot produce healthy ova</option>
            <option id="C">Male partner is unable to inseminate the female or has very low sperm counts</option>
            <option id="D">Female has an inhospitable uterus</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Infertility cases either due to inability of the male partner to inseminate the female or due to very low sperm counts in the ejaculates, could be corrected by artificial insemination (AI) technique.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) was legalised by the Government of India in the year 1971 with some strict conditions. MTPs are considered relatively safe during which period of pregnancy?</text>
            <option id="A">During the first trimester (up to 12 weeks of pregnancy)</option>
            <option id="B">During the second trimester</option>
            <option id="C">During the third trimester</option>
            <option id="D">Anytime during the pregnancy</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>MTPs are considered relatively safe during the first trimester, i.e., upto 12 weeks of pregnancy. Second trimester abortions are much more riskier.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Diseases or infections which are transmitted through sexual intercourse are collectively called Sexually Transmitted Infections (STIs). Which of the following STIs is NOT completely curable even if detected early and treated properly?</text>
            <option id="A">Gonorrhoea</option>
            <option id="B">Syphilis</option>
            <option id="C">Genital herpes</option>
            <option id="D">Chlamydiasis</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Except for hepatitis-B, genital herpes and HIV infections, other diseases are completely curable if detected early and treated properly.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In Assisted Reproductive Technology (ART), IVF is followed by Embryo Transfer (ET). In ZIFT (Zygote Intra Fallopian Transfer), the zygote or early embryo is transferred into the fallopian tube. Up to how many blastomeres is the embryo transferred in ZIFT?</text>
            <option id="A">Up to 4 blastomeres</option>
            <option id="B">Up to 8 blastomeres</option>
            <option id="C">More than 8 blastomeres</option>
            <option id="D">More than 16 blastomeres</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The zygote or early embryos (with upto 8 blastomeres) could then be transferred into the fallopian tube (ZIFT-zygote intra fallopian transfer) and embryos with more than 8 blastomeres, into the uterus (IUT - intra uterine transfer), to complete its further development.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following sexually transmitted infections is caused by a virus and is characterized by the appearance of warts on the genitalia?</text>
            <option id="A">Syphilis</option>
            <option id="B">Genital herpes</option>
            <option id="C">Genital warts</option>
            <option id="D">Trichomoniasis</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Genital warts are a sexually transmitted infection caused by the Human Papillomavirus (HPV). Genital herpes is caused by HSV, and syphilis by the bacterium Treponema pallidum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Infertility can sometimes be overcome through Assisted Reproductive Technologies (ART). Which ART involves the transfer of an ovum collected from a donor into the fallopian tube of another female who cannot produce one?</text>
            <option id="A">ZIFT (Zygote Intra Fallopian Transfer)</option>
            <option id="B">GIFT (Gamete Intra Fallopian Transfer)</option>
            <option id="C">ICSI (Intra Cytoplasmic Sperm Injection)</option>
            <option id="D">IUI (Intra-uterine Insemination)</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Transfer of an ovum collected from a donor into the fallopian tube (GIFT - gamete intra fallopian transfer) of another female who cannot produce one, but can provide suitable environment for fertilisation and further development is another method attempted.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a specialized ART procedure in which a sperm is directly injected into the ovum in the laboratory to form an embryo?</text>
            <option id="A">ZIFT</option>
            <option id="B">GIFT</option>
            <option id="C">ICSI</option>
            <option id="D">IUT</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Intra cytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI) is another specialised procedure to form an embryo in the laboratory in which a sperm is directly injected into the ovum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In which condition is the Artificial Insemination (AI) technique particularly useful?</text>
            <option id="A">When the female cannot produce an ovum</option>
            <option id="B">When the female has a blockage in the fallopian tubes</option>
            <option id="C">When the male partner is unable to inseminate the female or has very low sperm counts</option>
            <option id="D">When the female has a hostile cervical environment for implantation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Infertility cases either due to inability of the male partner to inseminate the female or due to very low sperm counts in the ejaculates, could be corrected by artificial insemination (AI) technique. In this technique, the semen collected either from the husband or a healthy donor is artificially introduced either into the vagina or into the uterus (IUI - intra-uterine insemination) of the female.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of an Intra Uterine Device (IUD) that releases hormones?</text>
            <option id="A">Lippes loop</option>
            <option id="B">CuT</option>
            <option id="C">Multiload 375</option>
            <option id="D">LNG-20</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>These devices are presently available as the non-medicated IUDs (e.g., Lippes loop), copper releasing IUDs (CuT, Cu7, Multiload 375) and the hormone releasing IUDs (Progestasert, LNG-20).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How do hormone-releasing IUDs work as contraceptives?</text>
            <option id="A">They suppress sperm motility and the fertilizing capacity of sperms</option>
            <option id="B">They make the uterus unsuitable for implantation and the cervix hostile to the sperms</option>
            <option id="C">They act as a physical barrier preventing the sperm from reaching the ovum</option>
            <option id="D">They block the fallopian tubes permanently</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The hormone releasing IUDs, in addition, make the uterus unsuitable for implantation and the cervix hostile to the sperms. Copper ions released suppress sperm motility and fertilising capacity.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Oral contraceptive pills contain small doses of either progestogens or progestogen-estrogen combinations. How do they work?</text>
            <option id="A">They kill the sperms in the vagina</option>
            <option id="B">They inhibit ovulation and implantation as well as alter the quality of cervical mucus</option>
            <option id="C">They physically block the sperm from entering the cervix</option>
            <option id="D">They cause early shedding of the endometrium</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Pills have to be taken daily for a period of 21 days starting preferably within the first five days of menstrual cycle. They inhibit ovulation and implantation as well as alter the quality of cervical mucus to prevent/retard entry of sperms. Pills are very effective with lesser side effects.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>'Saheli' is a new oral contraceptive for females containing a non-steroidal preparation. It is a:</text>
            <option id="A">Daily pill</option>
            <option id="B">Once-a-week pill</option>
            <option id="C">Monthly pill</option>
            <option id="D">Once-a-year implant</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Saheli – the new oral contraceptive for the females– contains a non-steroidal preparation. It is a 'once a week' pill with very few side effects and high contraceptive value.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The surgical method of contraception in males, where a small part of the vas deferens is removed or tied up, is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Tubectomy</option>
            <option id="B">Vasectomy</option>
            <option id="C">Castration</option>
            <option id="D">Ovariectomy</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Surgical methods, also called sterilisation, are generally advised for the male/female partner as a terminal method to prevent any more pregnancies. Sterilisation procedure in the male is called 'vasectomy' and that in the female, 'tubectomy'. In vasectomy, a small part of the vas deferens is removed or tied up through a small incision on the scrotum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The most important step to overcome population growth is to motivate smaller families by using various:</text>
            <option id="A">Contraceptive methods</option>
            <option id="B">Antibiotics</option>
            <option id="C">Vaccines</option>
            <option id="D">Surgical transplants</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The most important step to overcome this problem [population growth] is to motivate smaller families by using various contraceptive methods.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the statutory marriageable age for females and males in India, respectively?</text>
            <option id="A">18 years and 21 years</option>
            <option id="B">16 years and 18 years</option>
            <option id="C">21 years and 25 years</option>
            <option id="D">15 years and 18 years</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Statutory raising of marriageable age of the female to 18 years and that of males to 21 years, and incentives given to couples with small families are two of the other measures taken to tackle this problem.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>An ideal contraceptive should NOT be:</text>
            <option id="A">User-friendly</option>
            <option id="B">Easily available</option>
            <option id="C">Effective and reversible</option>
            <option id="D">Interfering with the sexual drive, desire, and/or the sexual act of the user</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>An ideal contraceptive should be user-friendly, easily available, effective and reversible with no or least side-effects. It also should in no way interfere with the sexual drive, desire and/or the sexual act of the user.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Condoms are barriers made of thin rubber/latex sheath used to cover the penis in the male or vagina and cervix in the female. Besides preventing pregnancy, what is another significant benefit of using condoms?</text>
            <option id="A">They provide nutrients to the female reproductive tract</option>
            <option id="B">They protect the user from contracting STIs and AIDS</option>
            <option id="C">They regulate the menstrual cycle</option>
            <option id="D">They increase sperm count</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Both the male and the female condoms are disposable, can be self-inserted and thereby gives privacy to the user. 'Nirodh' is a popular brand of condom for the male. Use of condoms has increased in recent years due to its additional benefit of protecting the user from contracting STIs and AIDS.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Diaphragms, cervical caps, and vaults are barrier methods made of rubber that are inserted into the female reproductive tract to cover the cervix during coitus. They are:</text>
            <option id="A">Disposable after single use</option>
            <option id="B">Reusable</option>
            <option id="C">Used only by males</option>
            <option id="D">Inserted surgically</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Diaphragms, cervical caps and vaults are also barriers made of rubber that are inserted into the female reproductive tract to cover the cervix during coitus. They prevent conception by blocking the entry of sperms through the cervix. They are reusable.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Spermicidal creams, jellies, and foams are usually used along with which barrier methods to increase their contraceptive efficiency?</text>
            <option id="A">Male condoms only</option>
            <option id="B">Diaphragms, cervical caps, and vaults</option>
            <option id="C">IUDs</option>
            <option id="D">Oral pills</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Diaphragms, cervical caps and vaults are also barriers... They are reusable. Spermicidal creams, jellies and foams are usually used along with these barriers to increase their contraceptive efficiency.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How are oral contraceptive pills generally taken by women?</text>
            <option id="A">Once a month on the first day of menstruation</option>
            <option id="B">Daily for a period of 21 days starting preferably within the first five days of menstrual cycle</option>
            <option id="C">Only on the day of coitus</option>
            <option id="D">Every alternate day throughout the month</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>They are used in the form of tablets and hence are popularly called the pills. Pills have to be taken daily for a period of 21 days starting preferably within the first five days of menstrual cycle.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>After taking oral pills for 21 days, a gap of 7 days is required before starting the next pack. What happens during these 7 days?</text>
            <option id="A">Ovulation</option>
            <option id="B">Menstruation occurs</option>
            <option id="C">Implantation</option>
            <option id="D">Fertilization</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Pills have to be taken daily for a period of 21 days... After a gap of 7 days (during which menstruation occurs) it has to be repeated in the same pattern till the female desires to prevent conception.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Oral pills work mainly by preventing ovulation and implantation. What additional effect do they have that makes them effective contraceptives?</text>
            <option id="A">They destroy the unfertilized egg</option>
            <option id="B">They alter the quality of cervical mucus to prevent/retard entry of sperms</option>
            <option id="C">They induce early menstruation</option>
            <option id="D">They block the fallopian tubes</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>They inhibit ovulation and implantation as well as alter the quality of cervical mucus to prevent/ retard entry of sperms. Pills are very effective with lesser side effects and are well accepted by the females.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Surgical methods of sterilization block gamete transport and thereby prevent conception. What is the reversibility of these surgical techniques?</text>
            <option id="A">Highly reversible</option>
            <option id="B">Easily reversible with medication</option>
            <option id="C">Very poor reversibility</option>
            <option id="D">Reversible only within the first week</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>These techniques are highly effective but their reversibility is very poor.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a potential ill-effect of contraceptive methods that one should be aware of?</text>
            <option id="A">Nausea and abdominal pain</option>
            <option id="B">Breakthrough bleeding and irregular menstrual bleeding</option>
            <option id="C">Increased bone density</option>
            <option id="D">Breast cancer</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>However, their possible ill-effects like nausea, abdominal pain, breakthrough bleeding, irregular menstrual bleeding or even breast cancer, though not very significant, should not be totally ignored.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Intentional or voluntary termination of pregnancy before full term is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Miscarriage</option>
            <option id="B">Medical termination of pregnancy (MTP)</option>
            <option id="C">Ectopic pregnancy</option>
            <option id="D">Parturition</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Intentional or voluntary termination of pregnancy before full term is called medical termination of pregnancy (MTP) or induced abortion.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Some STIs can also be transmitted by sharing of injection needles, surgical instruments, or from an infected mother to the foetus. Which of the following diseases fall into this category?</text>
            <option id="A">Gonorrhoea and Syphilis</option>
            <option id="B">Hepatitis-B and HIV</option>
            <option id="C">Genital herpes and Trichomoniasis</option>
            <option id="D">Chlamydiasis and Genital warts</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some of these infections like hepatitis-B and HIV can also be transmitted by sharing of injection needles, surgical instruments, etc., with infected persons, transfusion of blood, or from an infected mother to the foetus too.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Except for Hepatitis-B, genital herpes, and HIV infections, are other STIs completely curable?</text>
            <option id="A">Yes, if detected early and treated properly</option>
            <option id="B">No, they are never completely curable</option>
            <option id="C">Yes, but only with surgery</option>
            <option id="D">Only in males</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Except for hepatitis-B, genital herpes and HIV infections, other diseases are completely curable if detected early and treated properly.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Early symptoms of most STIs are minor and include itching, fluid discharge, slight pain, and swellings. Where do these symptoms typically appear?</text>
            <option id="A">On the arms and legs</option>
            <option id="B">In the genital region</option>
            <option id="C">In the respiratory tract</option>
            <option id="D">In the digestive system</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Early symptoms of most of these are minor and include itching, fluid discharge, slight pain, swellings, etc., in the genital region.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>