<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="326" name="Reproductive Health">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a non-medicated IUD?</text>
            <option id="A">CuT</option>
            <option id="B">Lippes loop</option>
            <option id="C">Cu7</option>
            <option id="D">LNG-20</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Intra Uterine Devices (IUDs) are of three main types: non-medicated IUDs (e.g., Lippes loop), copper releasing IUDs (CuT, Cu7, Multiload 375), and the hormone releasing IUDs (Progestasert, LNG-20).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The technique in which sperm is directly injected into the ovum in the laboratory is called:</text>
            <option id="A">ZIFT</option>
            <option id="B">GIFT</option>
            <option id="C">ICSI</option>
            <option id="D">IUI</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>ICSI (Intra cytoplasmic sperm injection) is a specialized procedure to form an embryo in the laboratory in which a sperm is directly injected into the ovum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) is considered relatively safe up to how many weeks of pregnancy?</text>
            <option id="A">8 weeks</option>
            <option id="B">12 weeks</option>
            <option id="C">20 weeks</option>
            <option id="D">24 weeks</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>MTPs are considered relatively safe during the first trimester, i.e., up to 12 weeks of pregnancy. Second trimester abortions are much more risky.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The statutory ban on amniocentesis for sex-determination in India is primarily aimed at preventing:</text>
            <option id="A">Genetic disorders</option>
            <option id="B">Female foeticide</option>
            <option id="C">Maternal mortality</option>
            <option id="D">Multiple pregnancies</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Statutory ban on amniocentesis for sex-determination is to legally check increasing menace of female foeticide.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a barrier method of contraception?</text>
            <option id="A">Diaphragm</option>
            <option id="B">IUD</option>
            <option id="C">Oral pills</option>
            <option id="D">Tubectomy</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In barrier methods, ovum and sperms are prevented from physically meeting with the help of barriers. Diaphragms, cervical caps and vaults are barriers made of rubber that are inserted into the female reproductive tract.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the full form of RCH?</text>
            <option id="A">Reproductive and Child Health Care</option>
            <option id="B">Reproduction and Contraceptive Healthcare</option>
            <option id="C">Regional Child Health</option>
            <option id="D">Reproductive Care and Health</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>India was amongst the first countries in the world to initiate action plans and programmes at a national level to attain total reproductive health as a social goal. These programmes are currently in operation under the popular name 'Reproductive and Child Health Care (RCH) programmes'.</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>How do copper-releasing IUDs prevent conception?</text>
            <option id="A">They suppress sperm motility and the fertilizing capacity of sperms.</option>
            <option id="B">They make the uterus unsuitable for implantation.</option>
            <option id="C">They inhibit ovulation.</option>
            <option id="D">They block the entry of sperms through the cervix.</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>IUDs increase phagocytosis of sperms within the uterus and the Cu ions released suppress sperm motility and the fertilising capacity of sperms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the context of ART, what does ZIFT stand for?</text>
            <option id="A">Zygote internal fallopian transfer</option>
            <option id="B">Zygote intra fallopian transfer</option>
            <option id="C">Zygote in vitro fertilization technique</option>
            <option id="D">Zygote inter fallopian transfer</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>ZIFT stands for Zygote intra fallopian transfer. In this technique, the zygote or early embryos (with up to 8 blastomeres) are transferred into the fallopian tube.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following sexually transmitted infections is completely curable if detected early and treated properly?</text>
            <option id="A">Hepatitis-B</option>
            <option id="B">Genital herpes</option>
            <option id="C">HIV infections</option>
            <option id="D">Syphilis</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Except for hepatitis-B, genital herpes and HIV infections, other sexually transmitted diseases (like syphilis, gonorrhoea, chlamydiasis) are completely curable if detected early and treated properly.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Saheli, an oral contraceptive pill for females, contains a non-steroidal preparation and is taken:</text>
            <option id="A">Daily</option>
            <option id="B">Weekly</option>
            <option id="C">Monthly</option>
            <option id="D">Only after coitus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>'Saheli' is a new oral contraceptive for the females. It contains a non-steroidal preparation. It is a 'once a week' pill with very few side effects and high contraceptive value.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following hormone-releasing IUDs makes the uterus unsuitable for implantation and the cervix hostile to the sperms?</text>
            <option id="A">Lippes loop</option>
            <option id="B">CuT</option>
            <option id="C">Multiload 375</option>
            <option id="D">LNG-20</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The hormone releasing IUDs, such as Progestasert and LNG-20, make the uterus unsuitable for implantation and the cervix hostile to the sperms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The surgical method of contraception in males is called vasectomy. In this procedure, a small part of the:</text>
            <option id="A">Epididymis is removed or tied up</option>
            <option id="B">Vas deferens is removed or tied up</option>
            <option id="C">Urethra is blocked</option>
            <option id="D">Seminal vesicle is removed</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In vasectomy, a small part of the vas deferens is removed or tied up through a small incision on the scrotum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Emergency contraceptives can be used to prevent pregnancy if taken within how many hours of unprotected coitus?</text>
            <option id="A">24 hours</option>
            <option id="B">48 hours</option>
            <option id="C">72 hours</option>
            <option id="D">7 days</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Administration of progestogens or progestogen-estrogen combinations or IUDs within 72 hours of coitus have been found to be very effective as emergency contraceptives.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following ART procedures involves the transfer of an ovum collected from a donor into the fallopian tube of another female who cannot produce one?</text>
            <option id="A">ZIFT</option>
            <option id="B">GIFT</option>
            <option id="C">ICSI</option>
            <option id="D">IUI</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>GIFT stands for Gamete intra fallopian transfer. It is the transfer of an ovum collected from a donor into the fallopian tube of another female who cannot produce one, but can provide suitable environment for fertilization and further development.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following statements about amniocentesis is INCORRECT?</text>
            <option id="A">It can be used to detect Down syndrome.</option>
            <option id="B">It is based on the chromosomal pattern in the amniotic fluid.</option>
            <option id="C">It is primarily intended to determine the sex of the unborn child.</option>
            <option id="D">It can be used to detect hemophilia.</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Amniocentesis is a fetal sex determination and disorder test based on the chromosomal pattern in the amniotic fluid. However, its primary and legal purpose is to test for the presence of certain genetic disorders (like Down syndrome, hemophilia, sickle-cell anemia), NOT to determine the sex of the child, which is illegal as it leads to female foeticide.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In vivo fertilization followed by embryo transfer (ET) is useful for females who:</text>
            <option id="A">Cannot produce an ovum</option>
            <option id="B">Cannot provide a suitable environment for fertilization but can retain the embryo</option>
            <option id="C">Cannot conceive naturally but can provide a suitable environment for the further development of the embryo</option>
            <option id="D">Have blocked fallopian tubes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In vivo fertilization is the fusion of gametes within the female. Embryos formed by in-vivo fertilisation can be used for transfer to assist those females who cannot conceive naturally but can provide suitable environment for further development.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The natural method of contraception known as 'Lactational amenorrhea' is effective up to a maximum period of:</text>
            <option id="A">Three months</option>
            <option id="B">Six months</option>
            <option id="C">Twelve months</option>
            <option id="D">Two years</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Lactational amenorrhea (absence of menstruation) method is based on the fact that ovulation does not occur during the period of intense lactation following parturition. However, this method has been reported to be effective only up to a maximum period of six months following parturition.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following correctly pairs a sexually transmitted disease with its causative agent?</text>
            <option id="A">Syphilis - Neisseria gonorrhoeae</option>
            <option id="B">Gonorrhoea - Treponema pallidum</option>
            <option id="C">Genital warts - Human papilloma virus (HPV)</option>
            <option id="D">Chlamydiasis - Trichomonas vaginalis</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Genital warts are caused by HPV. Syphilis is caused by Treponema pallidum, Gonorrhoea by Neisseria gonorrhoeae, and Chlamydiasis by Chlamydia trachomatis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During the "fertile period" (day 10 to 17 of the menstrual cycle), couples avoid coitus to prevent conception. This method is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Coitus interruptus</option>
            <option id="B">Periodic abstinence</option>
            <option id="C">Lactational amenorrhea</option>
            <option id="D">Rhythm method</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Periodic abstinence is one such method in which the couples avoid or abstain from coitus from day 10 to 17 of the menstrual cycle when ovulation could be expected. As chances of fertilisation are very high during this period, it is called the fertile period.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following points is INCORRECT regarding MTPs in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Government of India legalized MTP in 1971 with some strict conditions.</option>
            <option id="B">MTP is completely safe even during the third trimester.</option>
            <option id="C">It is an essential method to get rid of unwanted pregnancies.</option>
            <option id="D">MTP is also essential in certain cases where continuation of the pregnancy could be harmful or even fatal either to the mother or to the foetus or both.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>MTPs are considered relatively safe during the first trimester, i.e., up to 12 weeks of pregnancy. Second trimester abortions are much more risky, and they are not safe during the third trimester.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>