<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="324" name="Sexual Reproduction in Flowering Plants">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>The innermost wall layer of the microsporangium which nourishes the developing pollen grains is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Epidermis</option>
            <option id="B">Endothecium</option>
            <option id="C">Middle layers</option>
            <option id="D">Tapetum</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The innermost wall layer is the tapetum. It nourishes the developing pollen grains. Cells of the tapetum possess dense cytoplasm and generally have more than one nucleus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Pollination by wind is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Anemophily</option>
            <option id="B">Hydrophily</option>
            <option id="C">Entomophily</option>
            <option id="D">Ornithophily</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Pollination by wind is termed anemophily. It is the most common amongst abiotic pollinations.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In angiosperms, functional megaspore develops into:</text>
            <option id="A">Embryo sac</option>
            <option id="B">Ovule</option>
            <option id="C">Endosperm</option>
            <option id="D">Pollen sac</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In a majority of angiosperms, one of the megaspores is functional while the other three degenerate. Only the functional megaspore develops into the female gametophyte (embryo sac).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the male reproductive organ of a flower called?</text>
            <option id="A">Carpel</option>
            <option id="B">Pistil</option>
            <option id="C">Stamen</option>
            <option id="D">Sepal</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The stamen represents the male reproductive organ of a flower, consisting of an anther and a filament.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following serves as the landing platform for pollen grains?</text>
            <option id="A">Ovary</option>
            <option id="B">Style</option>
            <option id="C">Stigma</option>
            <option id="D">Anther</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The pistil consists of three parts: stigma, style, and ovary. The stigma serves as a landing platform for pollen grains.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The protective coverings of the ovule are known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Integuments</option>
            <option id="B">Nucellus</option>
            <option id="C">Chalaza</option>
            <option id="D">Micropyle</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The ovule has one or two protective envelopes called integuments. Integuments encircle the ovule except at the tip where a small opening called the micropyle is organised.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The innermost wall layer of the microsporangium, which nourishes the developing pollen grains, is the:</text>
            <option id="A">Epidermis</option>
            <option id="B">Endothecium</option>
            <option id="C">Middle layer</option>
            <option id="D">Tapetum</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The innermost wall layer is the tapetum. It nourishes the developing pollen grains. Cells of the tapetum possess dense cytoplasm and generally have more than one nucleus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The hard outer layer of a pollen grain is called exine. It is highly resistant because it is made of:</text>
            <option id="A">Cellulose and pectin</option>
            <option id="B">Sporopollenin</option>
            <option id="C">Lignin</option>
            <option id="D">Suberin</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Pollen grains have a prominent two-layered wall. The hard outer layer called the exine is made up of sporopollenin which is one of the most resistant organic material known.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In a typical angiosperm, the fully developed embryo sac (female gametophyte) consists of how many cells and nuclei?</text>
            <option id="A">8 cells, 8 nuclei</option>
            <option id="B">7 cells, 8 nuclei</option>
            <option id="C">8 cells, 7 nuclei</option>
            <option id="D">7 cells, 7 nuclei</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A typical angiosperm embryo sac, at maturity, though 8-nucleate is 7-celled. It consists of 3 antipodal cells, 1 central cell (with 2 polar nuclei), 2 synergids, and 1 egg cell.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The typical angiosperm anther is bilobed with each lobe having two theca. Therefore, it is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Monothecous</option>
            <option id="B">Dithecous</option>
            <option id="C">Polythecous</option>
            <option id="D">Athecous</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A typical angiosperm anther is bilobed with each lobe having two theca, i.e., they are dithecous. Often a longitudinal groove runs lengthwise separating the theca.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of formation of microspores from a pollen mother cell (PMC) through meiosis is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Megasporogenesis</option>
            <option id="B">Microsporogenesis</option>
            <option id="C">Embryogenesis</option>
            <option id="D">Parthenogenesis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>As the anther develops, the cells of the sporogenous tissue undergo meiotic divisions to form microspore tetrads. The process of formation of microspores from a pollen mother cell (PMC) through meiosis is called microsporogenesis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Pollen grains represent the male gametophytes. The hard outer layer of the pollen grain is called exine. It is made up of which of the following highly resistant organic materials?</text>
            <option id="A">Cellulose</option>
            <option id="B">Pectin</option>
            <option id="C">Sporopollenin</option>
            <option id="D">Lignin</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Pollen grains have a prominent two-layered wall. The hard outer layer called the exine is made up of sporopollenin which is one of the most resistant organic material known. It can withstand high temperatures and strong acids and alkali.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following best describes the function of the tapetum in a microsporangium?</text>
            <option id="A">Protection</option>
            <option id="B">Dehiscence of the anther</option>
            <option id="C">Nourishment of developing pollen grains</option>
            <option id="D">Formation of microspore mother cells</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The innermost wall layer is the tapetum. It nourishes the developing pollen grains. Cells of the tapetum possess dense cytoplasm and generally have more than one nucleus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The generative cell of a pollen grain is spindle-shaped and floats in the cytoplasm of the vegetative cell. What is its main function?</text>
            <option id="A">To provide nutrition</option>
            <option id="B">To divide and form two male gametes</option>
            <option id="C">To form the pollen tube</option>
            <option id="D">To form the exine</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The generative cell is small and floats in the cytoplasm of the vegetative cell. It is spindle shaped with dense cytoplasm and a nucleus. In over 60 per cent of angiosperms, pollen grains are shed at this 2-celled stage. In the remaining species, the generative cell divides mitotically to give rise to the two male gametes before pollen grains are shed (3-celled stage).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The viability of pollen grains depends greatly on prevailing temperature and humidity. In cereals such as wheat and rice, how long do pollen grains remain viable after their release?</text>
            <option id="A">30 minutes</option>
            <option id="B">A few hours</option>
            <option id="C">Several months</option>
            <option id="D">Years</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The period for which pollen grains remain viable is highly variable and to some extent depends on the prevailing temperature and humidity. In some cereals such as rice and wheat, pollen grains lose viability within 30 minutes of their release.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In water hyacinth and water lily, which are aquatic plants, how does pollination take place?</text>
            <option id="A">By water currents</option>
            <option id="B">By fish</option>
            <option id="C">By insects or wind</option>
            <option id="D">Only by autogamy</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Not all aquatic plants use water for pollination. In a majority of aquatic plants such as water hyacinth and water lily, the flowers emerge above the level of water and are pollinated by insects or wind as in most of the land plants.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In Vallisneria, how do the male flowers or pollen grains reach the female flower?</text>
            <option id="A">They are carried by insects</option>
            <option id="B">The female flower reaches the surface of water and pollen grains are carried passively by water currents</option>
            <option id="C">They are released underwater and sink to the bottom</option>
            <option id="D">They are dispersed by wind</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In Vallisneria, the female flower reaches the surface of water by the long stalk and the male flowers or pollen grains are released on to the surface of water. They are carried passively by water currents; some of them eventually reach the female flowers and the stigma.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How are pollen grains of water-pollinated species protected from wetting?</text>
            <option id="A">By a thick exine</option>
            <option id="B">By a mucilaginous covering</option>
            <option id="C">By a waxy layer</option>
            <option id="D">By sporopollenin</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In most of the water-pollinated species, pollen grains are protected from wetting by a mucilaginous covering.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A typical angiosperm anther is usually:</text>
            <option id="A">Monothecous and bisporangiate</option>
            <option id="B">Dithecous and tetrasporangiate</option>
            <option id="C">Monothecous and tetrasporangiate</option>
            <option id="D">Dithecous and bisporangiate</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A typical angiosperm anther is bilobed with each lobe having two theca, i.e., they are dithecous. Often a longitudinal groove runs lengthwise separating the theca. The anther is a four-sided (tetragonal) structure consisting of four microsporangia located at the corners, two in each lobe.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which layer of the microsporangium provides nourishment to the developing pollen grains?</text>
            <option id="A">Epidermis</option>
            <option id="B">Endothecium</option>
            <option id="C">Middle layers</option>
            <option id="D">Tapetum</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>In a transverse section, a typical microsporangium appears near circular in outline. It is generally surrounded by four wall layers – the epidermis, endothecium, middle layers and the tapetum. The innermost wall layer is the tapetum. It nourishes the developing pollen grains.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The hard outer layer of a pollen grain, called the exine, is made up of a highly resistant organic material known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Cellulose</option>
            <option id="B">Pectin</option>
            <option id="C">Sporopollenin</option>
            <option id="D">Lignin</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Pollen grains are generally spherical measuring about 25-50 micrometers in diameter. It has a prominent two-layered wall. The hard outer layer called the exine is made up of sporopollenin which is one of the most resistant organic material known.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>To a biologist, flowers are morphological and embryological marvels and the sites of:</text>
            <option id="A">Photosynthesis</option>
            <option id="B">Transpiration</option>
            <option id="C">Sexual reproduction</option>
            <option id="D">Vegetative propagation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>To a biologist, flowers are morphological and embryological marvels and the sites of sexual reproduction.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Much before the actual flower is seen on a plant, the decision that the plant is going to flower has taken place. Several hormonal and structural changes are initiated which lead to the differentiation and further development of the:</text>
            <option id="A">Root apex</option>
            <option id="B">Floral primordium</option>
            <option id="C">Leaf primordium</option>
            <option id="D">Stem nodes</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Much before the actual flower is seen on a plant, the decision that the plant is going to flower has taken place. Several hormonal and structural changes are initiated which lead to the differentiation and further development of the floral primordium.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In a flower, the male reproductive whorl, consisting of a whorl of stamens, is called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Gynoecium</option>
            <option id="B">Androecium</option>
            <option id="C">Corolla</option>
            <option id="D">Calyx</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In the flower the male and female reproductive structures, the androecium and the gynoecium differentiate and develop. You would recollect that the androecium consists of a whorl of stamens representing the male reproductive organ.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the prominent two-layered wall of a pollen grain called?</text>
            <option id="A">Epidermis and endothecium</option>
            <option id="B">Exine and intine</option>
            <option id="C">Testa and tegmen</option>
            <option id="D">Ectoderm and endoderm</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Pollen grains are generally spherical measuring about 25-50 micrometers in diameter. It has a prominent two-layered wall. The hard outer layer called the exine is made up of sporopollenin... The inner wall of the pollen grain is called the intine.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The hard outer layer of the pollen grain, the exine, is made of one of the most resistant organic materials known. What is this material?</text>
            <option id="A">Cellulose</option>
            <option id="B">Pectin</option>
            <option id="C">Sporopollenin</option>
            <option id="D">Chitin</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The hard outer layer called the exine is made up of sporopollenin which is one of the most resistant organic material known.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following statements about sporopollenin is correct?</text>
            <option id="A">It is easily degraded by enzymes</option>
            <option id="B">It cannot withstand high temperatures</option>
            <option id="C">It can withstand high temperatures, strong acids, and alkali</option>
            <option id="D">It is only found in the intine layer</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>It can withstand high temperatures and strong acids and alkali. No enzyme that degrades sporopollenin is so far known.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Pollen grains of many species, such as Parthenium, are known to cause severe problems in humans. What kind of problems do they cause?</text>
            <option id="A">Digestive disorders</option>
            <option id="B">Severe allergies and bronchial afflictions like asthma and bronchitis</option>
            <option id="C">Skin infections and rashes</option>
            <option id="D">Vision problems</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Pollen grains of many species cause severe allergies and bronchial afflictions in some people often leading to chronic respiratory disorders-- asthma, bronchitis, etc. It may be mentioned that Parthenium or carrot grass that came into India as a contaminant with imported wheat, has become ubiquitous in occurrence and causes pollen allergy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Parthenium, also known as carrot grass, causes pollen allergy in India. How did it enter the country?</text>
            <option id="A">It was deliberately planted for its flowers</option>
            <option id="B">It came as a contaminant with imported wheat</option>
            <option id="C">It is a native species of India</option>
            <option id="D">It was brought by migratory birds</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>It may be mentioned that Parthenium or carrot grass that came into India as a contaminant with imported wheat, has become ubiquitous in occurrence and causes pollen allergy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Pollen grains are rich in nutrients and have become popular in recent years to be used as:</text>
            <option id="A">Fertilizers for crops</option>
            <option id="B">Food supplements in the form of tablets and syrups</option>
            <option id="C">Fuel for engines</option>
            <option id="D">Building materials</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Pollen grains are rich in nutrients. It has become a fashion in recent years to use pollen tablets as food supplements. In western countries, a large number of pollen products in the form of tablets and syrups are available in the market.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The style is the elongated slender part beneath the stigma. What is the basal bulged part of the pistil called?</text>
            <option id="A">Thalamus</option>
            <option id="B">Ovary</option>
            <option id="C">Placenta</option>
            <option id="D">Locule</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The style is the elongated slender part beneath the stigma. The basal bulged part of the pistil is the ovary.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Inside the ovary is the ovarian cavity. What is another name for this cavity?</text>
            <option id="A">Locule</option>
            <option id="B">Placenta</option>
            <option id="C">Ovule</option>
            <option id="D">Funicle</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Inside the ovary is the ovarian cavity (locule).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What tissue is located inside the ovarian cavity, from which the megasporangia arise?</text>
            <option id="A">Endosperm</option>
            <option id="B">Placenta</option>
            <option id="C">Nucellus</option>
            <option id="D">Integuments</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The placenta is located inside the ovarian cavity... Arising from the placenta are the megasporangia, commonly called ovules.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Enclosed within the integuments of the ovule is a mass of cells called the nucellus. What is a characteristic of the cells of the nucellus?</text>
            <option id="A">They are empty and dead</option>
            <option id="B">They have abundant reserve food materials</option>
            <option id="C">They form the pollen tube</option>
            <option id="D">They become the endosperm immediately</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Enclosed within the integuments is a mass of cells called the nucellus. Cells of the nucellus have abundant reserve food materials.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Located within the nucellus is the female gametophyte, which is also known as the:</text>
            <option id="A">Embryo sac</option>
            <option id="B">Pollen sac</option>
            <option id="C">Megaspore mother cell</option>
            <option id="D">Micropyle</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Located in the nucellus is the embryo sac or female gametophyte. An ovule generally has a single embryo sac formed from a megaspore.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of formation of megaspores from the megaspore mother cell is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Microsporogenesis</option>
            <option id="B">Megasporogenesis</option>
            <option id="C">Pollination</option>
            <option id="D">Fertilization</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The process of formation of megaspores from the megaspore mother cell is called megasporogenesis.</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of a false fruit?</text>
            <option id="A">Mango</option>
            <option id="B">Apple</option>
            <option id="C">Banana</option>
            <option id="D">Grape</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In most plants, by the time the fruit develops from the ovary, other floral parts degenerate and fall off. However, in a few species such as apple, strawberry, cashew, etc., the thalamus also contributes to fruit formation. Such fruits are called false fruits.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The phenomenon where seed develops without fertilization is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Parthenocarpy</option>
            <option id="B">Apomixis</option>
            <option id="C">Polyembryony</option>
            <option id="D">Amphimixis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Although seeds, in general, are the products of fertilisation, a few flowering plants such as some species of Asteraceae and grasses, have evolved a special mechanism, to produce seeds without fertilisation, called apomixis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Double fertilization is an event unique to angiosperms. It involves:</text>
            <option id="A">Syngamy and triple fusion</option>
            <option id="B">Fusion of two male gametes with one egg</option>
            <option id="C">Fusion of one male gamete with two eggs</option>
            <option id="D">Fusion of two male gametes with polar nuclei</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Double fertilization involves two types of fusions, syngamy (fusion of one male gamete with the egg to form a zygote) and triple fusion (fusion of the other male gamete with the two polar nuclei to form the Primary Endosperm Nucleus - PEN).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The exine of a pollen grain is highly resistant to chemical and biological degradation because it is made of:</text>
            <option id="A">Cellulose and pectin</option>
            <option id="B">Sporopollenin</option>
            <option id="C">Lignin</option>
            <option id="D">Suberin</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The hard outer layer called the exine is made up of sporopollenin which is one of the most resistant organic material known. It can withstand high temperatures and strong acids and alkali. No enzyme that degrades sporopollenin is so far known.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During microsporogenesis, the microspore tetrad is formed from the microspore mother cell (MMC) through which type of division?</text>
            <option id="A">Mitosis</option>
            <option id="B">Meiosis</option>
            <option id="C">Amitosis</option>
            <option id="D">Endomitosis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>As the anther develops, the cells of the sporogenous tissue (microspore mother cells or MMCs) undergo meiotic divisions to form microspore tetrads.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In over 60% of angiosperms, pollen grains are shed at which stage?</text>
            <option id="A">1-celled stage</option>
            <option id="B">2-celled stage</option>
            <option id="C">3-celled stage</option>
            <option id="D">4-celled stage</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In over 60 per cent of angiosperms, pollen grains are shed at the 2-celled stage (consisting of the vegetative cell and the generative cell). In the remaining species, the generative cell divides to form the two male gametes before pollen grains are shed (3-celled stage).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The transfer of pollen grains from the anther to the stigma of a different plant is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Autogamy</option>
            <option id="B">Geitonogamy</option>
            <option id="C">Xenogamy</option>
            <option id="D">Cleistogamy</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Xenogamy is the transfer of pollen grains from anther to the stigma of a different plant. This is the only type of pollination which during pollination brings genetically different types of pollen grains to the stigma.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Water pollination (hydrophily) is quite rare in flowering plants. Which of the following is an example of a water-pollinated plant?</text>
            <option id="A">Water hyacinth</option>
            <option id="B">Water lily</option>
            <option id="C">Vallisneria</option>
            <option id="D">Lotus</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Pollination by water is quite rare in flowering plants. Some examples of water pollinated plants are Vallisneria and Hydrilla. In water hyacinth and water lily, the flowers emerge above the level of water and are pollinated by insects or wind.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following processes involves the transfer of pollen grains from the anther to the stigma of the same flower?</text>
            <option id="A">Autogamy</option>
            <option id="B">Geitonogamy</option>
            <option id="C">Xenogamy</option>
            <option id="D">Allogamy</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In autogamy, pollination is achieved within the same flower. Transfer of pollen grains from the anther to the stigma of the same flower is termed autogamy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Flowers which do not open at all are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Chasmogamous</option>
            <option id="B">Cleistogamous</option>
            <option id="C">Dioecious</option>
            <option id="D">Monoecious</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some plants such as Viola, Oxalis, and Commelina produce two types of flowers. Cleistogamous flowers do not open at all, and are invariably autogamous as there is no chance of cross-pollen landing on the stigma.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a characteristic of wind-pollinated (anemophilous) flowers?</text>
            <option id="A">Large, brightly colored petals</option>
            <option id="B">Production of nectar and strong fragrance</option>
            <option id="C">Light, non-sticky pollen and well-exposed stamens</option>
            <option id="D">Presence of a single ovule per ovary</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Wind pollination requires that the pollen grains are light and non-sticky so that they can be transported in wind currents. They often possess well-exposed stamens and large often-feathery stigma to easily trap air-borne pollen grains.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In double fertilization, one male gamete fuses with the egg cell to form the zygote. What does the other male gamete fuse with?</text>
            <option id="A">The synergids</option>
            <option id="B">The antipodal cells</option>
            <option id="C">The secondary nucleus (two polar nuclei)</option>
            <option id="D">The generative cell</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The other male gamete moves towards the two polar nuclei located in the central cell and fuses with them to produce a triploid primary endosperm nucleus (PEN). As this involves the fusion of three haploid nuclei it is termed triple fusion.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In over 60 percent of angiosperms, pollen grains are shed at which stage?</text>
            <option id="A">1-celled stage</option>
            <option id="B">2-celled stage</option>
            <option id="C">3-celled stage</option>
            <option id="D">4-celled stage</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When the pollen grain is mature it contains two cells, the vegetative cell and generative cell. In over 60 per cent of angiosperms, pollen grains are shed at this 2-celled stage.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The stalk of the ovule by which it is attached to the placenta is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Hilum</option>
            <option id="B">Funicle</option>
            <option id="C">Micropyle</option>
            <option id="D">Chalaza</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The ovule is a small structure attached to the placenta by means of a stalk called funicle. The body of the ovule fuses with funicle in the region called hilum.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Inside the ovule, a mass of cells enclosed within the integuments forms the nucellus. Cells of the nucellus have abundant reserve food materials. Located in the nucellus is the embryo sac, which is also known as the:</text>
            <option id="A">Male gametophyte</option>
            <option id="B">Female gametophyte</option>
            <option id="C">Endosperm</option>
            <option id="D">Microsporangium</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Enclosed within the integuments is a mass of cells called the nucellus. Cells of the nucellus have abundant reserve food materials. Located in the nucellus is the embryo sac or female gametophyte.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A typical angiosperm embryo sac, at maturity, though 8-nucleate, is:</text>
            <option id="A">7-celled</option>
            <option id="B">8-celled</option>
            <option id="C">6-celled</option>
            <option id="D">4-celled</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Three cells are grouped together at the micropylar end and constitute the egg apparatus. Three cells are at the chalazal end and are called the antipodals. The large central cell has two polar nuclei. Thus, a typical angiosperm embryo sac, at maturity, though 8-nucleate is 7-celled.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The single megaspore mother cell (MMC) present in the micropylar region of the nucellus undergoes meiosis to form four megaspores. Usually, how many of these are functional?</text>
            <option id="A">Four</option>
            <option id="B">Three</option>
            <option id="C">Two</option>
            <option id="D">One</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>In a majority of flowering plants, one of the megaspores is functional while the other three degenerate. Only the functional megaspore develops into the female gametophyte (embryo sac).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The formation of an embryo sac from a single megaspore is termed as:</text>
            <option id="A">Monosporic development</option>
            <option id="B">Bisporic development</option>
            <option id="C">Tetrasporic development</option>
            <option id="D">Apomixis</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Only the functional megaspore develops into the female gametophyte (embryo sac). This method of embryo sac formation from a single megaspore is termed monosporic development.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the embryo sac, which cells have special cellular thickenings at the micropylar tip called the filiform apparatus?</text>
            <option id="A">Antipodals</option>
            <option id="B">Egg cell</option>
            <option id="C">Synergids</option>
            <option id="D">Central cell</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Three cells are grouped together at the micropylar end and constitute the egg apparatus. The egg apparatus, in turn, consists of two synergids and one egg cell. The synergids have special cellular thickenings at the micropylar tip called filiform apparatus, which play an important role in guiding the pollen tubes into the synergid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Chasmogamous flowers are similar to flowers of other species with exposed anthers and stigma. In contrast, what is unique about cleistogamous flowers?</text>
            <option id="A">They only open at night</option>
            <option id="B">They do not open at all</option>
            <option id="C">They lack nectar</option>
            <option id="D">They are unisexual</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some plants such as Viola (common pansy), Oxalis, and Commelina produce two types of flowers- chasmogamous flowers which are similar to flowers of other species with exposed anthers and stigma, and cleistogamous flowers which do not open at all.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Many insects may consume pollen or the nectar without bringing about pollination. Such floral visitors are referred to as:</text>
            <option id="A">Pollinators</option>
            <option id="B">Pollen/nectar robbers</option>
            <option id="C">Mutualists</option>
            <option id="D">Symbionts</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Many insects may consume pollen or the nectar without bringing about pollination. Such floral visitors are referred to as pollen/nectar robbers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which outbreeding device prevents both autogamy and geitonogamy?</text>
            <option id="A">Pollen release and stigma receptivity are not synchronised</option>
            <option id="B">Anther and stigma are placed at different positions</option>
            <option id="C">Self-incompatibility</option>
            <option id="D">Production of unisexual flowers on different plants (dioecy)</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>If both male and female flowers are present on the same plant such as castor and maize (monoecious), it prevents autogamy but not geitonogamy. In several species such as papaya, male and female flowers are present on different plants, that is each plant is either male or female (dioecy). This condition prevents both autogamy and geitonogamy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Self-incompatibility is a genetic mechanism that prevents self-pollen from fertilising the ovules by:</text>
            <option id="A">Inhibiting pollen germination or pollen tube growth in the pistil</option>
            <option id="B">Preventing the opening of the flower</option>
            <option id="C">Destroying the male gametes</option>
            <option id="D">Causing the stigma to dry up</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The third device to prevent inbreeding is self-incompatibility. This is a genetic mechanism and prevents self-pollen (from the same flower or other flowers of the same plant) from fertilising the ovules by inhibiting pollen germination or pollen tube growth in the pistil.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is emasculation in artificial hybridisation?</text>
            <option id="A">Covering the stigma with a bag</option>
            <option id="B">Removal of anthers from the flower bud before the anther dehisces</option>
            <option id="C">Dusting the stigma with desired pollen</option>
            <option id="D">Developing an embryo artificially</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>If the female parent bears bisexual flowers, removal of anthers from the flower bud before the anther dehisces using a pair of forceps is necessary. This step is referred to as emasculation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In over 60% of angiosperms, pollen grains are shed at which stage?</text>
            <option id="A">1-celled stage</option>
            <option id="B">2-celled stage</option>
            <option id="C">3-celled stage</option>
            <option id="D">4-celled stage</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When the pollen grain is mature it contains two cells, the vegetative cell and generative cell. In over 60 per cent of angiosperms, pollen grains are shed at this 2-celled stage.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The functional megaspore in an angiosperm develops into:</text>
            <option id="A">Endosperm</option>
            <option id="B">Embryo sac</option>
            <option id="C">Embryo</option>
            <option id="D">Ovule</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In a majority of angiosperms, one of the megaspores is functional while the other three degenerate. Only the functional megaspore develops into the female gametophyte (embryo sac).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A typical angiosperm embryo sac, at maturity, though 8-nucleate is:</text>
            <option id="A">7-celled</option>
            <option id="B">8-celled</option>
            <option id="C">6-celled</option>
            <option id="D">4-celled</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Six of the eight nuclei are surrounded by cell walls and organised into cells; the remaining two nuclei, called polar nuclei are situated below the egg apparatus in the large central cell. Thus, a typical angiosperm embryo sac, at maturity, though 8-nucleate is 7-celled.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Pollination achieved within the same flower is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Geitonogamy</option>
            <option id="B">Xenogamy</option>
            <option id="C">Autogamy</option>
            <option id="D">Allogamy</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Autogamy: In this type, pollination is achieved within the same flower. Transfer of pollen grains from the anther to the stigma of the same flower.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The female reproductive organ of a flower is called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Androecium</option>
            <option id="B">Gynoecium</option>
            <option id="C">Stamen</option>
            <option id="D">Anther</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The gynoecium represents the female reproductive organ.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A typical stamen consists of a long and slender stalk called the filament, and a terminal generally bilobed structure called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Stigma</option>
            <option id="B">Style</option>
            <option id="C">Anther</option>
            <option id="D">Ovary</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>A typical stamen has two parts – the long and slender stalk called the filament, and the terminal generally bilobed structure called the anther.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The proximal end of the stamen filament is attached to the thalamus or the petal of the flower. The number and length of stamens are:</text>
            <option id="A">Constant across all species</option>
            <option id="B">Variable in flowers of different species</option>
            <option id="C">Always 5 in dicots and 3 in monocots</option>
            <option id="D">Always exactly equal to the number of petals</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The proximal end of the filament is attached to the thalamus or the petal of the flower. The number and length of stamens are variable in flowers of different species.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>As the anther develops, the cells of the sporogenous tissue undergo meiotic divisions to form:</text>
            <option id="A">Megaspore tetrads</option>
            <option id="B">Microspore tetrads</option>
            <option id="C">Pollen mother cells</option>
            <option id="D">Embryo sacs</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>As the anther develops, the cells of the sporogenous tissue undergo meiotic divisions to form microspore tetrads.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The pollen grain exine has prominent apertures where sporopollenin is absent. These apertures are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Micropyles</option>
            <option id="B">Germ pores</option>
            <option id="C">Stomata</option>
            <option id="D">Lenticels</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Pollen grain exine has prominent apertures called germ pores where sporopollenin is absent.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Because of the presence of sporopollenin, pollen grains are well preserved as:</text>
            <option id="A">Fossils</option>
            <option id="B">Seeds</option>
            <option id="C">Spores</option>
            <option id="D">Crystals</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Pollen grains are well-preserved as fossils because of the presence of sporopollenin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The inner wall of the pollen grain, the intine, is a thin and continuous layer made up of:</text>
            <option id="A">Sporopollenin and lignin</option>
            <option id="B">Cellulose and pectin</option>
            <option id="C">Chitin and glucan</option>
            <option id="D">Suberin and cutin</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The inner wall of the pollen grain is called the intine. It is a thin and continuous layer made up of cellulose and pectin.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When a pollen grain is mature, it contains two cells. What are they called?</text>
            <option id="A">Vegetative cell and generative cell</option>
            <option id="B">Tube cell and central cell</option>
            <option id="C">Synergid and egg cell</option>
            <option id="D">Antipodal cell and polar nucleus</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>When the pollen grain is mature it contains two cells, the vegetative cell and generative cell.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Pollen consumption has been claimed to increase the performance of:</text>
            <option id="A">Athletes and race horses</option>
            <option id="B">Students before exams</option>
            <option id="C">Farmers in the field</option>
            <option id="D">Musicians</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In western countries, a large number of pollen products in the form of tablets and syrups are available in the market. Pollen consumption has been claimed to increase the performance of athletes and race horses.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Once shed, pollen grains must land on the stigma before they lose their viability if they are to bring about fertilization. How long do pollen grains of some cereals like wheat and rice remain viable?</text>
            <option id="A">For several months</option>
            <option id="B">Within 30 minutes of their release</option>
            <option id="C">For one year</option>
            <option id="D">Only a few seconds</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The period for which pollen grains remain viable is highly variable and to some extent depends on the prevailing temperature and humidity. In some cereals such as rice and wheat, pollen grains lose viability within 30 minutes of their release.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>While pollen from wheat and rice loses viability quickly, pollen from some members of Rosaceae, Leguminosae, and Solanaceae can maintain viability for:</text>
            <option id="A">1 hour</option>
            <option id="B">1 day</option>
            <option id="C">Months</option>
            <option id="D">Years</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In some cereals such as rice and wheat, pollen grains lose viability within 30 minutes of their release, and in some members of Rosaceae, Leguminosae and Solanaceae, they maintain viability for months.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>It is possible to store pollen grains of a large number of species for years in pollen banks for use in crop breeding programs. What is the storage medium and temperature used?</text>
            <option id="A">Liquid nitrogen (-196°C)</option>
            <option id="B">Dry ice (-78°C)</option>
            <option id="C">Refrigerator (4°C)</option>
            <option id="D">Room temperature (25°C) in a vacuum</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>You may have heard of storing semen/ sperms of many animals including humans for artificial insemination. It is possible to store pollen grains of a large number of species for years in liquid nitrogen (-1960C). Such stored pollen can be used as pollen banks, similar to seed banks, in crop breeding programmes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What are the megasporangia arising from the placenta commonly called?</text>
            <option id="A">Pollen grains</option>
            <option id="B">Ovules</option>
            <option id="C">Stigmas</option>
            <option id="D">Anthers</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Arising from the placenta are the megasporangia, commonly called ovules.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The number of ovules in an ovary may be one, as in wheat, paddy, and mango, or many, as in:</text>
            <option id="A">Papaya, water melon, and orchids</option>
            <option id="B">Pea, bean, and gram</option>
            <option id="C">Sunflower and marigold</option>
            <option id="D">Mustard and radish</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The number of ovules in an ovary may be one (wheat, paddy, mango) to many (papaya, water melon, orchids).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The ovule is a small structure attached to the placenta by means of a stalk called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Hilum</option>
            <option id="B">Funicle</option>
            <option id="C">Micropyle</option>
            <option id="D">Chalaza</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Let us familiarise ourselves with the structure of a typical angiosperm ovule. The ovule is a small structure attached to the placenta by means of a stalk called funicle.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The body of the ovule fuses with the funicle in a region called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Micropyle</option>
            <option id="B">Hilum</option>
            <option id="C">Chalaza</option>
            <option id="D">Nucellus</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The body of the ovule fuses with funicle in the region called hilum. Thus, hilum represents the junction between ovule and funicle.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Ovules generally differentiate a single megaspore mother cell (MMC) in the micropylar region of the nucellus. What is the characteristic of this MMC?</text>
            <option id="A">It is a small cell containing little cytoplasm</option>
            <option id="B">It is a large cell containing dense cytoplasm and a prominent nucleus</option>
            <option id="C">It undergoes mitosis only</option>
            <option id="D">It is haploid</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Ovules generally differentiate a single megaspore mother cell (MMC) in the micropylar region of the nucellus. It is a large cell containing dense cytoplasm and a prominent nucleus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Megaspore Mother Cell (MMC) undergoes which type of division to produce four megaspores?</text>
            <option id="A">Mitotic division</option>
            <option id="B">Meiotic division</option>
            <option id="C">Amitosis</option>
            <option id="D">Binary fission</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The MMC undergoes meiotic division. What is the importance of the MMC undergoing meiosis? Meiosis results in the production of four megaspores.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In a majority of angiosperms, one of the megaspores is functional while the other three degenerate. What happens to the functional megaspore?</text>
            <option id="A">It develops into a pollen grain</option>
            <option id="B">It develops into the female gametophyte (embryo sac)</option>
            <option id="C">It becomes the endosperm</option>
            <option id="D">It forms the seed coat</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In a majority of angiosperms, one of the megaspores is functional while the other three degenerate. Only the functional megaspore develops into the female gametophyte (embryo sac).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The method of embryo sac formation from a single megaspore is termed:</text>
            <option id="A">Monosporic development</option>
            <option id="B">Bisporic development</option>
            <option id="C">Tetrasporic development</option>
            <option id="D">Apomixis</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>This method of embryo sac formation from a single megaspore is termed monosporic development.</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>Geitonogamy involves:</text>
            <option id="A">Fertilization of a flower by the pollen from another flower of the same plant.</option>
            <option id="B">Fertilization of a flower by the pollen from the same flower.</option>
            <option id="C">Fertilization of a flower by the pollen from a flower of another plant in the same population.</option>
            <option id="D">Fertilization of a flower by the pollen from a flower of another plant belonging to a distant population.</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Geitonogamy is the transfer of pollen grains from the anther to the stigma of another flower of the same plant. Although geitonogamy is functionally cross-pollination involving a pollinating agent, genetically it is similar to autogamy since the pollen grains come from the same plant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In a typical angiosperm embryo sac, the filiform apparatus is present at the micropylar part of the synergids. Its function is to:</text>
            <option id="A">Nourish the egg cell</option>
            <option id="B">Guide the entry of the pollen tube</option>
            <option id="C">Produce nectar</option>
            <option id="D">Develop into the endosperm</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The synergids have special cellular thickenings at the micropylar tip called filiform apparatus, which play an important role in guiding the pollen tubes into the synergid.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following plants exhibits cleistogamous flowers?</text>
            <option id="A">Papaya</option>
            <option id="B">Viola (Common pansy)</option>
            <option id="C">Vallisneria</option>
            <option id="D">Zostera</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some plants such as Viola (common pansy), Oxalis, and Commelina produce two types of flowers: chasmogamous flowers (open) and cleistogamous flowers which do not open at all. Cleistogamous flowers are invariably autogamous.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a mechanism to prevent autogamy but not geitonogamy?</text>
            <option id="A">Self-incompatibility</option>
            <option id="B">Production of unisexual flowers on the same plant (monoecious)</option>
            <option id="C">Production of unisexual flowers on different plants (dioecious)</option>
            <option id="D">Cleistogamy</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>If both male and female flowers are present on the same plant such as castor and maize (monoecious), it prevents autogamy but not geitonogamy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The central cell of the embryo sac, after triple fusion, becomes the:</text>
            <option id="A">Zygote</option>
            <option id="B">Primary endosperm cell (PEC)</option>
            <option id="C">Synergid</option>
            <option id="D">Antipodal cell</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The central cell after triple fusion becomes the primary endosperm cell (PEC) and develops into the endosperm while the zygote develops into an embryo.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which part of the embryo axis in a dicot embryo lies above the level of cotyledons and terminates with the plumule?</text>
            <option id="A">Hypocotyl</option>
            <option id="B">Radicle</option>
            <option id="C">Epicotyl</option>
            <option id="D">Root cap</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The portion of embryonal axis above the level of cotyledons is the epicotyl, which terminates with the plumule or stem tip. The cylindrical portion below the level of cotyledons is hypocotyl that terminates at its lower end in the radicle.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The portion of the embryonal axis below the level of cotyledons in a dicot embryo is called the:</text>
            <option id="A">Epicotyl</option>
            <option id="B">Hypocotyl</option>
            <option id="C">Plumule</option>
            <option id="D">Radicle</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The cylindrical portion below the level of cotyledons is hypocotyl that terminates at its lower end in the radicle or root tip.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The residual, persistent nucellus found in some seeds like black pepper and beet is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Perisperm</option>
            <option id="B">Endosperm</option>
            <option id="C">Pericarp</option>
            <option id="D">Coleoptile</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In some seeds such as black pepper and beet, remnants of nucellus are also persistent. This residual, persistent nucellus is the perisperm.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The phenomenon of producing seeds without fertilization is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Parthenocarpy</option>
            <option id="B">Apomixis</option>
            <option id="C">Polyembryony</option>
            <option id="D">Vegetative propagation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Although seeds, in general are the products of fertilisation, a few flowering plants such as some species of Asteraceae and grasses, have evolved a special mechanism, to produce seeds without fertilisation, called apomixis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Transfer of pollen grains from the anther to the stigma of another flower of the same plant is termed as:</text>
            <option id="A">Autogamy</option>
            <option id="B">Geitonogamy</option>
            <option id="C">Xenogamy</option>
            <option id="D">Cleistogamy</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Geitonogamy is the transfer of pollen grains from the anther to the stigma of another flower of the same plant. Although geitonogamy is functionally cross-pollination involving a pollinating agent, genetically it is similar to autogamy since the pollen grains come from the same plant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Double fertilisation is an event unique to angiosperms. It involves syngamy and triple fusion. What is the product of triple fusion?</text>
            <option id="A">Zygote</option>
            <option id="B">Primary Endosperm Nucleus (PEN)</option>
            <option id="C">Embryo</option>
            <option id="D">Synergid</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The other male gamete moves towards the two polar nuclei located in the central cell and fuses with them to produce a triploid primary endosperm nucleus (PEN). As this involves the fusion of three haploid nuclei it is termed triple fusion.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In some species like apple, strawberry, and cashew, the thalamus also contributes to fruit formation. Such fruits are called:</text>
            <option id="A">True fruits</option>
            <option id="B">False fruits</option>
            <option id="C">Parthenocarpic fruits</option>
            <option id="D">Multiple fruits</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In most plants, by the time the fruit develops from the ovary, other floral parts degenerate and fall off. However, in a few species such as apple, strawberry, cashew, etc., the thalamus also contributes to fruit formation. Such fruits are called false fruits.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A dioecious plant bearing only male or female flowers prevents:</text>
            <option id="A">Both autogamy and geitonogamy</option>
            <option id="B">Autogamy but not geitonogamy</option>
            <option id="C">Geitonogamy but not autogamy</option>
            <option id="D">Only xenogamy</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>If both male and female flowers are present on the same plant such as castor and maize (monoecious), it prevents autogamy but not geitonogamy. In several species such as papaya, male and female flowers are present on different plants, that is each plant is either male or female (dioecy). This condition prevents both autogamy and geitonogamy.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The endosperm development precedes embryo development. What is the ploidy level of the cells of the primary endosperm tissue?</text>
            <option id="A">Haploid (n)</option>
            <option id="B">Diploid (2n)</option>
            <option id="C">Triploid (3n)</option>
            <option id="D">Tetraploid (4n)</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Endosperm development precedes embryo development. Why? The primary endosperm cell divides repeatedly and forms a triploid endosperm tissue. The cells of this tissue are filled with reserve food materials and are used for the nutrition of the developing embryo.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In some seeds like black pepper and beet, remnants of nucellus are also persistent. This residual, persistent nucellus is the:</text>
            <option id="A">Pericarp</option>
            <option id="B">Perisperm</option>
            <option id="C">Endosperm</option>
            <option id="D">Scutellum</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In some seeds such as black pepper and beet, remnants of nucellus are also persistent. This residual, persistent nucellus is the perisperm.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Double fertilisation is an event unique to angiosperms. It involves:</text>
            <option id="A">Syngamy and triple fusion</option>
            <option id="B">Two syngamy events</option>
            <option id="C">Fusion of two male gametes with the egg cell</option>
            <option id="D">Fusion of the egg cell with two polar nuclei</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Since two types of fusions, syngamy and triple fusion take place in an embryo sac the phenomenon is termed double fertilisation, an event unique to angiosperms. The central cell after triple fusion becomes the primary endosperm cell (PEC) and develops into the endosperm while the zygote develops into an embryo.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The portion of embryonal axis above the level of cotyledons is the:</text>
            <option id="A">Hypocotyl</option>
            <option id="B">Epicotyl</option>
            <option id="C">Radicle</option>
            <option id="D">Plumule</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A typical dicotyledonous embryo consists of an embryonal axis and two cotyledons. The portion of embryonal axis above the level of cotyledons is the epicotyl, which terminates with the plumule or stem tip.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The cylindrical portion below the level of cotyledons is hypocotyl that terminates at its lower end in the radicle or root tip. The root tip is covered by a:</text>
            <option id="A">Coleoptile</option>
            <option id="B">Coleorhiza</option>
            <option id="C">Root cap</option>
            <option id="D">Scutellum</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The cylindrical portion below the level of cotyledons is hypocotyl that terminates at its lower end in the radicle or root tip. The root tip is covered with a root cap.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Flowers that do not open at all are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Chasmogamous flowers</option>
            <option id="B">Cleistogamous flowers</option>
            <option id="C">Dioecious flowers</option>
            <option id="D">Monoecious flowers</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some plants such as Viola (common pansy), Oxalis, and Commelina produce two types of flowers: chasmogamous flowers which are similar to flowers of other species with exposed anthers and stigma, and cleistogamous flowers which do not open at all. In such flowers, the anthers and stigma lie close to each other.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Transfer of pollen grains from the anther to the stigma of another flower of the same plant is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Autogamy</option>
            <option id="B">Geitonogamy</option>
            <option id="C">Xenogamy</option>
            <option id="D">Cleistogamy</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Geitonogamy – Transfer of pollen grains from the anther to the stigma of another flower of the same plant. Although geitonogamy is functionally cross-pollination involving a pollinating agent, genetically it is similar to autogamy since the pollen grains come from the same plant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In which type of pollination is the transfer of pollen grains brought about by water?</text>
            <option id="A">Anemophily</option>
            <option id="B">Hydrophily</option>
            <option id="C">Entomophily</option>
            <option id="D">Ornithophily</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Pollination by water is called hydrophily. It is quite rare in flowering plants and is limited to about 30 genera, mostly monocotyledons. Some examples of water pollinated plants are Vallisneria and Hydrilla which grow in fresh water and several marine sea-grasses such as Zostera.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of formation of microspores from a pollen mother cell (PMC) through meiosis is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Megasporogenesis</option>
            <option id="B">Microsporogenesis</option>
            <option id="C">Gametogenesis</option>
            <option id="D">Embryogenesis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>As each cell of the sporogenous tissue is capable of giving rise to a microspore tetrad. Each one is a potential pollen or microspore mother cell (PMC). The process of formation of microspores from a pollen mother cell through meiosis is called microsporogenesis.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>As the anthers mature and dehydrate, the microspores dissociate from each other and develop into:</text>
            <option id="A">Seeds</option>
            <option id="B">Pollen grains</option>
            <option id="C">Ovules</option>
            <option id="D">Fruit</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>As the anthers mature and dehydrate, the microspores dissociate from each other and develop into pollen grains.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Pollen grains represent the:</text>
            <option id="A">Male gametophyte</option>
            <option id="B">Female gametophyte</option>
            <option id="C">Male sporophyte</option>
            <option id="D">Female sporophyte</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The pollen grains represent the male gametophytes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the two cells in a mature pollen grain is bigger, has abundant food reserve, and a large irregularly shaped nucleus?</text>
            <option id="A">Generative cell</option>
            <option id="B">Vegetative cell</option>
            <option id="C">Male gamete</option>
            <option id="D">Sperm cell</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The vegetative cell is bigger, has abundant food reserve and a large irregularly shaped nucleus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The generative cell in a mature pollen grain is small and floats in the cytoplasm of the:</text>
            <option id="A">Synergid</option>
            <option id="B">Vegetative cell</option>
            <option id="C">Egg cell</option>
            <option id="D">Central cell</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The generative cell is small and floats in the cytoplasm of the vegetative cell. It is spindle shaped with dense cytoplasm and a nucleus.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In over 60 percent of angiosperms, pollen grains are shed at the 2-celled stage. In the remaining species, the generative cell divides mitotically to give rise to the two male gametes before pollen grains are shed. What stage is this called?</text>
            <option id="A">1-celled stage</option>
            <option id="B">2-celled stage</option>
            <option id="C">3-celled stage</option>
            <option id="D">4-celled stage</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In over 60 per cent of angiosperms, pollen grains are shed at this 2-celled stage. In the remaining species, the generative cell divides mitotically to give rise to the two male gametes before pollen grains are shed (3-celled stage).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The gynoecium represents the female reproductive part of the flower. If a gynoecium consists of a single pistil, it is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Multicarpellary</option>
            <option id="B">Monocarpellary</option>
            <option id="C">Syncarpous</option>
            <option id="D">Apocarpous</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The gynoecium represents the female reproductive part of the flower. The gynoecium may consist of a single pistil (monocarpellary) or may have more than one pistil (multicarpellary).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When there are more than one pistil in a flower and they are fused together, the condition is termed:</text>
            <option id="A">Apocarpous</option>
            <option id="B">Syncarpous</option>
            <option id="C">Monocarpellary</option>
            <option id="D">Polyandrous</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When there are more than one, the pistils may be fused together (syncarpous) or may be free (apocarpous).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A typical pistil has three parts: the stigma, style, and ovary. Which part serves as a landing platform for pollen grains?</text>
            <option id="A">Ovary</option>
            <option id="B">Style</option>
            <option id="C">Stigma</option>
            <option id="D">Thalamus</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Each pistil has three parts, the stigma, style and ovary. The stigma serves as a landing platform for pollen grains.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Each ovule has one or two protective envelopes that encircle the nucellus except at the tip. What are these envelopes called?</text>
            <option id="A">Integuments</option>
            <option id="B">Carpels</option>
            <option id="C">Sepals</option>
            <option id="D">Bracts</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Each ovule has one or two protective envelopes called integuments. Integuments encircle the nucellus except at the tip...</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>At the tip of the ovule where the integuments are absent, a small opening is organized. What is this opening called?</text>
            <option id="A">Chalaza</option>
            <option id="B">Hilum</option>
            <option id="C">Micropyle</option>
            <option id="D">Funicle</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Integuments encircle the nucellus except at the tip where a small opening called the micropyle is organised.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Opposite the micropylar end is the chalaza. What does the chalaza represent in the ovule?</text>
            <option id="A">The junction between funicle and ovule</option>
            <option id="B">The basal part of the ovule</option>
            <option id="C">The point of entry for the pollen tube</option>
            <option id="D">The female gamete</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Opposite the micropylar end, is the chalaza, representing the basal part of the ovule.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The nucleus of the functional megaspore divides mitotically to form two nuclei which move to the opposite poles, forming the:</text>
            <option id="A">2-nucleate embryo sac</option>
            <option id="B">4-nucleate embryo sac</option>
            <option id="C">8-nucleate embryo sac</option>
            <option id="D">Endosperm</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Let us study formation of the embryo sac in a little more detail. The nucleus of the functional megaspore divides mitotically to form two nuclei which move to the opposite poles, forming the 2-nucleate embryo sac.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Two more sequential mitotic nuclear divisions result in the formation of the 4-nucleate and later the 8-nucleate stages of the embryo sac. What is special about these mitotic divisions?</text>
            <option id="A">They are followed by immediate cell wall formation</option>
            <option id="B">They are strictly free nuclear</option>
            <option id="C">They involve meiosis</option>
            <option id="D">They occur in the cytoplasm</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Two more sequential mitotic nuclear divisions result in the formation of the 4-nucleate and later the 8-nucleate stages of the embryo sac. It is of interest to note that these mitotic divisions are strictly free nuclear, that is, nuclear divisions are not followed immediately by cell wall formation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>After the 8-nucleate stage, cell walls are laid down leading to the organization of the typical female gametophyte or embryo sac. How many of the eight nuclei are surrounded by cell walls and organized into cells?</text>
            <option id="A">Eight</option>
            <option id="B">Four</option>
            <option id="C">Six</option>
            <option id="D">Two</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>After the 8-nucleate stage, cell walls are laid down leading to the organisation of the typical female gametophyte or embryo sac. Observe the distribution of cells inside the embryo sac. Six of the eight nuclei are surrounded by cell walls and organised into cells; the remaining two nuclei, called polar nuclei are situated below the egg apparatus in the large central cell.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>