<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter subject="Biology" id="331" name="Strategies for Enhancement in Food Production">
    <easy>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is considered the "Father of the Green Revolution" in the world?</text>
            <option id="A">M.S. Swaminathan</option>
            <option id="B">Norman E. Borlaug</option>
            <option id="C">Verghese Kurien</option>
            <option id="D">Hargobind Khorana</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Norman E. Borlaug, an American agronomist, is considered the father of the Green Revolution worldwide for his work in developing semi-dwarf, high-yielding varieties of wheat. M.S. Swaminathan is the father of the Green Revolution in India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The term "totipotency" refers to the ability of:</text>
            <option id="A">A single cell to divide and produce all of the differentiated cells in an organism.</option>
            <option id="B">An animal to regenerate lost parts.</option>
            <option id="C">A plant to resist viral infections.</option>
            <option id="D">A cell to undergo meiosis.</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Totipotency is the capacity to generate a whole plant from any cell/explant. This property is heavily utilized in plant tissue culture to rapidly produce thousands of plants.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Sonalika and Kalyan Sona are high yielding and disease-resistant varieties of:</text>
            <option id="A">Rice</option>
            <option id="B">Wheat</option>
            <option id="C">Maize</option>
            <option id="D">Sugarcane</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In 1963, several varieties such as Sonalika and Kalyan Sona, which were high yielding and disease resistant, were introduced all over the wheat-growing belt of India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of a freshwater fish widely cultured in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Hilsa</option>
            <option id="B">Rohu</option>
            <option id="C">Sardines</option>
            <option id="D">Mackerel</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some of the freshwater fishes which are very common include Catla, Rohu and common carp. Hilsa, Sardines, Mackerel and Pomfrets are some of the marine fishes that are eaten.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The management of animals for milk and its products for human consumption is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Poultry farming</option>
            <option id="B">Dairy farming</option>
            <option id="C">Apiculture</option>
            <option id="D">Pisciculture</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Dairying is the management of animals for milk and its products for human consumption.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following refers to the rearing of honey bees?</text>
            <option id="A">Sericulture</option>
            <option id="B">Pisciculture</option>
            <option id="C">Apiculture</option>
            <option id="D">Silviculture</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Bee-keeping or apiculture is the maintenance of hives of honeybees for the production of honey and beeswax.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the main objective of animal breeding?</text>
            <option id="A">To increase the number of wild animals</option>
            <option id="B">To increase the yield of animals and improve the desirable qualities of the produce</option>
            <option id="C">To prevent diseases in animals</option>
            <option id="D">To domesticate new species</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Animal breeding aims at increasing the yield of animals and improving the desirable qualities of the produce.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is NOT a freshwater fish?</text>
            <option id="A">Catla</option>
            <option id="B">Rohu</option>
            <option id="C">Common carp</option>
            <option id="D">Mackerel</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Catla, Rohu and common carp are freshwater fishes. Mackerel, Hilsa, Sardines and Pomfrets are marine fishes.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The agricultural practice of breeding and raising livestock is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Agriculture</option>
            <option id="B">Animal husbandry</option>
            <option id="C">Silviculture</option>
            <option id="D">Pisciculture</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Animal husbandry is the agricultural practice of breeding and raising livestock.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The term 'Apiculture' refers to the rearing of:</text>
            <option id="A">Silkworms</option>
            <option id="B">Honey bees</option>
            <option id="C">Fishes</option>
            <option id="D">Poultry</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Bee-keeping or apiculture is the maintenance of hives of honeybees for the production of honey.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is the most common species of honey bee reared in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Apis mellifera</option>
            <option id="B">Apis dorsata</option>
            <option id="C">Apis indica</option>
            <option id="D">Apis florea</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>There are several species of honeybees which can be reared. Of these, the most common species is Apis indica.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The management of animals for milk and its products for human consumption is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Poultry farm management</option>
            <option id="B">Dairy farm management</option>
            <option id="C">Pisciculture</option>
            <option id="D">Animal breeding</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Dairying is the management of animals for milk and its products for human consumption.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following viral diseases affects poultry?</text>
            <option id="A">Ranikhet disease</option>
            <option id="B">Foot and mouth disease</option>
            <option id="C">Anthrax</option>
            <option id="D">Mastitis</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Poultry refers to domesticated birds like chickens, ducks, turkeys and geese. They are susceptible to several viral, bacterial and fungal diseases. Ranikhet disease (Newcastle disease) is a very common and highly infectious viral disease of poultry.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a marine fish commonly consumed in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Catla</option>
            <option id="B">Rohu</option>
            <option id="C">Common carp</option>
            <option id="D">Hilsa</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Freshwater fishes which are very common include Catla, Rohu and common carp. Some of the marine fishes that are eaten include - Hilsa, Sardines, Mackerel and Pomfrets.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Blue Revolution is associated with a significant increase in the production of:</text>
            <option id="A">Milk</option>
            <option id="B">Cereals</option>
            <option id="C">Fish and aquatic products</option>
            <option id="D">Poultry</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Aquaculture and pisciculture have been able to increase the production of aquatic plants and animals, both fresh-water and marine. This has led to the development and flourishing of the fishery industry, and it has brought a lot of income to the farmers in particular and the country in general. We now talk about 'Blue Revolution' as being implemented along the same lines as 'Green Revolution'.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of crossing two different plant varieties, each having a specific desired character, to get a single variety with both desired characters is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Mutation breeding</option>
            <option id="B">Hybridisation</option>
            <option id="C">Tissue culture</option>
            <option id="D">Biofortification</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Cross hybridisation among the selected parents: The desired characters have very often to be combined from two different plants (parents), for example high protein quality of one parent may need to be combined with disease resistance from another parent. This is possible by cross hybridising the two parents to produce hybrids that genetically combine the desired characters in one plant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which crop variety is resistant to the white rust disease?</text>
            <option id="A">Himgiri</option>
            <option id="B">Pusa Swarnim (Karan rai)</option>
            <option id="C">Pusa Shubhra</option>
            <option id="D">Pusa Sadabahar</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Pusa Swarnim (Karan rai) is a variety of Brassica that is bred by hybridisation and selection for resistance to white rust disease.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Pusa Komal is a disease-resistant variety of which crop?</text>
            <option id="A">Wheat</option>
            <option id="B">Brassica</option>
            <option id="C">Cowpea</option>
            <option id="D">Chilli</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Pusa Komal is a variety of Cowpea that is resistant to the bacterial blight disease.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following describes animal husbandry?</text>
            <option id="A">The agricultural practice of cultivating crops</option>
            <option id="B">The agricultural practice of breeding and raising livestock</option>
            <option id="C">The industrial processing of animal products</option>
            <option id="D">The management of wild animals in sanctuaries</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Animal husbandry is the agricultural practice of breeding and raising livestock. As such it is a vital skill for farmers and is as much science as it is art. Animal husbandry deals with the care and breeding of livestock like buffaloes, cows, pigs, horses, cattle, sheep, camels, goats, etc.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>It is estimated that more than 70 per cent of the world livestock population is in:</text>
            <option id="A">North America and Europe</option>
            <option id="B">India and China</option>
            <option id="C">Australia and New Zealand</option>
            <option id="D">South America and Africa</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>It is estimated that more than 70 per cent of the world livestock population is in India and China. However, it is surprising to note that the contribution to the world farm produce is only 25 per cent, i.e., the productivity per unit is very low.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Dairy management deals with processes and systems that increase yield and improve quality of milk. Milk yield is primarily dependent on the:</text>
            <option id="A">Quality of breeds in the farm</option>
            <option id="B">Type of fodder provided</option>
            <option id="C">Frequency of milking</option>
            <option id="D">Size of the dairy farm</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Dairying is the management of animals for milk and its products for human consumption. Milk yield is primarily dependent on the quality of breeds in the farm. Selection of good breeds having high yielding potential (under the climatic conditions of the area), combined with resistance to diseases is very important.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is an example of an infectious disease that can spread through contaminated food?</text>
            <option id="A">Typhoid</option>
            <option id="B">Malaria</option>
            <option id="C">Dengue</option>
            <option id="D">Filariasis</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Salmonella typhi is a pathogenic bacterium which causes typhoid fever in human beings. These pathogens generally enter the small intestine through food and water contaminated with them.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Fish, shell-fish, prawns, and crabs are caught, processed, or sold in which industry?</text>
            <option id="A">Apiculture</option>
            <option id="B">Sericulture</option>
            <option id="C">Fisheries</option>
            <option id="D">Silviculture</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Fishery is an industry devoted to the catching, processing or selling of fish, shellfish or other aquatic animals. A large number of our population is dependent on fish, fish products and other aquatic animals such as prawn, crab, lobster, edible oyster, etc., for food.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a common freshwater fish?</text>
            <option id="A">Hilsa</option>
            <option id="B">Sardine</option>
            <option id="C">Mackerel</option>
            <option id="D">Rohu</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Some of the freshwater fishes which are very common include Catla, Rohu and common carp. Some of the marine fishes that are eaten include – Hilsa, Sardines, Mackerel and Pomfrets.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In India, agriculture accounts for approximately what percentage of the country's GDP?</text>
            <option id="A">10 per cent</option>
            <option id="B">33 per cent</option>
            <option id="C">62 per cent</option>
            <option id="D">90 per cent</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>India is mainly an agricultural country. Agriculture accounts for approximately 33 per cent of India's GDP and employs nearly 62 per cent of the population.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What percentage of the Indian population is employed by agriculture?</text>
            <option id="A">25 per cent</option>
            <option id="B">33 per cent</option>
            <option id="C">62 per cent</option>
            <option id="D">85 per cent</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Agriculture accounts for approximately 33 per cent of India's GDP and employs nearly 62 per cent of the population.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a semi-dwarf variety of wheat developed by Nobel laureate Norman E. Borlaug?</text>
            <option id="A">Kalyan Sona</option>
            <option id="B">IR-8</option>
            <option id="C">Sonalika</option>
            <option id="D">The question asks for the creator, but Kalyan Sona and Sonalika were derived from Borlaug's varieties.</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Nobel laureate Norman E. Borlaug, at International Centre for Wheat and Maize Improvement in Mexico, developed semi-dwarf wheat. In 1963, several varieties such as Sonalika and Kalyan Sona, which were high yielding and disease resistant, were introduced all over the wheat-growing belt of India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following methods is conventionally used for breeding disease resistance in plants?</text>
            <option id="A">Hybridisation and selection</option>
            <option id="B">Mutation breeding</option>
            <option id="C">Genetic engineering</option>
            <option id="D">Tissue culture</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Breeding is carried out by the conventional breeding techniques (described earlier) or by mutation breeding. The conventional method of breeding for disease resistance is that of hybridisation and selection.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which wheat variety was developed to be resistant to leaf and stripe rust and hill bunt?</text>
            <option id="A">Pusa swarnim</option>
            <option id="B">Himgiri</option>
            <option id="C">Pusa shubhra</option>
            <option id="D">Pusa Komal</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Wheat variety Himgiri is resistant to Leaf and stripe rust, hill bunt.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Brassica variety Pusa swarnim (Karan rai) was bred for resistance against which disease?</text>
            <option id="A">White rust</option>
            <option id="B">Black rot</option>
            <option id="C">Bacterial blight</option>
            <option id="D">Tobacco mosaic virus</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Brassica variety Pusa swarnim (Karan rai) is resistant to White rust.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Another major cause for large scale destruction of crop plants and crop produce is insect and pest infestation. Insect resistance in host crop plants may be due to morphological, biochemical, or physiological characteristics. Hairy leaves in several plants are associated with resistance to which pests?</text>
            <option id="A">Jassids in cotton and cereal leaf beetle in wheat</option>
            <option id="B">Bollworms in cotton</option>
            <option id="C">Stem borers in maize</option>
            <option id="D">Aphids in mustard</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Insect resistance in host crop plants may be due to morphological, biochemical or physiological characteristics. Hairy leaves in several plants are associated with resistance to insect pests, e.g, resistance to jassids in cotton and cereal leaf beetle in wheat.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In wheat, solid stems lead to non-preference by which pest?</text>
            <option id="A">Stem sawfly</option>
            <option id="B">Cereal leaf beetle</option>
            <option id="C">Aphids</option>
            <option id="D">Jassids</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In wheat, solid stems lead to non-preference by the stem sawfly.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Smooth leaved and nectar-less cotton varieties do not attract which common pest?</text>
            <option id="A">Jassids</option>
            <option id="B">Bollworms</option>
            <option id="C">Aphids</option>
            <option id="D">Whiteflies</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Smooth leaved and nectar-less cotton varieties do not attract bollworms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which wheat variety, developed in 2000, has a high protein content and has been used as a donor for improving cultivated wheat?</text>
            <option id="A">Kalyan Sona</option>
            <option id="B">Sonalika</option>
            <option id="C">Atlas 66</option>
            <option id="D">Himgiri</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Wheat variety, Atlas 66, having a high protein content, has been used as a donor for improving cultivated wheat.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>It has been possible to develop an iron-fortified rice variety containing over how many times as much iron as in commonly consumed varieties?</text>
            <option id="A">Two times</option>
            <option id="B">Three times</option>
            <option id="C">Five times</option>
            <option id="D">Ten times</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>It has been possible to develop an iron-fortified rice variety containing over five times as much iron as in commonly consumed varieties.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) in New Delhi has released several vegetable crops rich in vitamins and minerals. Which vitamin is enriched in their bitter gourd, bathua, mustard, and tomato varieties?</text>
            <option id="A">Vitamin A</option>
            <option id="B">Vitamin B12</option>
            <option id="C">Vitamin C</option>
            <option id="D">Vitamin D</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The Indian Agricultural Research Institute, New Delhi has also released several vegetable crops that are rich in vitamins and minerals, e.g., Vitamin A enriched carrots, spinach, pumpkin; Vitamin C enriched bitter gourd, bathua, mustard, tomato...</explanation>
        </question>
    </easy>
    <medium>
        <question>
            <text>Mating of closely related individuals within the same breed for 4-6 generations is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Out-crossing</option>
            <option id="B">Cross-breeding</option>
            <option id="C">Inbreeding</option>
            <option id="D">Interspecific hybridization</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>When breeding is between animals of the same breed for 4-6 generations, it is called inbreeding. Continued inbreeding, especially close inbreeding, usually reduces fertility and even productivity (inbreeding depression).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following techniques is employed to produce virus-free plants from an infected plant?</text>
            <option id="A">Protoplast fusion</option>
            <option id="B">Meristem culture</option>
            <option id="C">Anther culture</option>
            <option id="D">Somatic embryogenesis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Even if the plant is infected with a virus, the meristem (apical and axillary) is free of virus. Hence, one can remove the meristem and grow it in vitro to obtain virus-free plants.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Pomato is a somatic hybrid produced by the fusion of protoplasts of:</text>
            <option id="A">Potato and Tomato</option>
            <option id="B">Pomegranate and Tomato</option>
            <option id="C">Poppy and Tomato</option>
            <option id="D">Potato and Mango</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Isolated protoplasts from two different varieties of plants can be fused to get hybrid protoplasts, called somatic hybrids. Fusion of protoplasts of tomato and potato resulted in a new plant, the pomato.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The technique of Multiple Ovulation Embryo Transfer Technology (MOET) is primarily used for:</text>
            <option id="A">Increasing the production of honey</option>
            <option id="B">Herd improvement in cattle</option>
            <option id="C">Producing disease-resistant crops</option>
            <option id="D">Cloning sheep</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>MOET is a programme for herd improvement. In this method, a cow is administered hormones, with FSH-like activity, to induce follicular maturation and super ovulation. The embryos at 8-32 cell stages, are recovered non-surgically and transferred to surrogate mothers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which mating method is used to combine desirable qualities of two different breeds into a single progeny?</text>
            <option id="A">Inbreeding</option>
            <option id="B">Out-crossing</option>
            <option id="C">Cross-breeding</option>
            <option id="D">Interspecific hybridization</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In cross-breeding, superior males of one breed are mated with superior females of another breed. Cross-breeding allows the desirable qualities of two different breeds to be combined.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The mule is a result of:</text>
            <option id="A">Inbreeding</option>
            <option id="B">Out-crossing</option>
            <option id="C">Cross-breeding</option>
            <option id="D">Interspecific hybridization</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>In interspecific hybridization, male and female animals of two different related species are mated. For example, a mule is produced from a cross between a male donkey and a female horse.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a breed of cattle?</text>
            <option id="A">Leghorn</option>
            <option id="B">Jersey</option>
            <option id="C">Rhode Island Red</option>
            <option id="D">Hisardale</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Jersey is a breed of cattle (cow). Leghorn and Rhode Island Red are poultry breeds, and Hisardale is a sheep breed.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>To overcome 'inbreeding depression', which of the following practices is recommended?</text>
            <option id="A">Continuous inbreeding for 10 generations</option>
            <option id="B">A single outcross with an unrelated superior animal of the same breed</option>
            <option id="C">Mating with a completely different species</option>
            <option id="D">Isolating the herd from all other animals</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>It often helps to overcome inbreeding depression by a single outcross. This means mating the selected animals with unrelated superior animals of the same breed (having no common ancestors for 4-6 generations).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Inbreeding refers to the mating of:</text>
            <option id="A">Animals of different breeds</option>
            <option id="B">More closely related individuals within the same breed for 4-6 generations</option>
            <option id="C">Unrelated animals of the same breed</option>
            <option id="D">Animals of different species</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When breeding is between animals of the same breed it is called inbreeding. Inbreeding refers to the mating of more closely related individuals within the same breed for 4-6 generations.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a severe consequence of continued close inbreeding?</text>
            <option id="A">Heterosis</option>
            <option id="B">Hybrid vigour</option>
            <option id="C">Inbreeding depression</option>
            <option id="D">Increased fertility</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Continued inbreeding, especially close inbreeding, usually reduces fertility and even productivity. This is called inbreeding depression.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The term "Green Revolution" is associated with a dramatic increase in the production of:</text>
            <option id="A">Milk</option>
            <option id="B">Fish</option>
            <option id="C">Food crops like wheat and rice</option>
            <option id="D">Honey</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Green Revolution was dependent to a large extent on plant breeding techniques for development of high-yielding and disease resistant varieties in wheat, rice, maize, etc.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Sonalika and Kalyan Sona are high yielding varieties of:</text>
            <option id="A">Rice</option>
            <option id="B">Wheat</option>
            <option id="C">Maize</option>
            <option id="D">Sugarcane</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In 1963, several varieties such as Sonalika and Kalyan Sona, which were high yielding and disease resistant, were introduced all over the wheat-growing belt of India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In animal breeding, the term 'inbreeding' refers to:</text>
            <option id="A">Mating of related individuals of the same breed for 4-6 generations</option>
            <option id="B">Mating of unrelated individuals of the same breed</option>
            <option id="C">Mating of individuals of different breeds</option>
            <option id="D">Mating of individuals of different species</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>When breeding is between animals of the same breed it is called inbreeding, while crosses between different breeds are called outbreeding. Inbreeding refers to the mating of more closely related individuals within the same breed for 4-6 generations.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Continued inbreeding, especially close inbreeding, usually reduces fertility and even productivity. This is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Heterosis</option>
            <option id="B">Inbreeding depression</option>
            <option id="C">Hybrid vigour</option>
            <option id="D">Out-crossing</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>However, continued inbreeding, especially close inbreeding, usually reduces fertility and even productivity. This is called inbreeding depression.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Hisardale is a new breed of sheep developed in Punjab by crossing Bikaneri ewes and Marino rams. This is an example of:</text>
            <option id="A">Inbreeding</option>
            <option id="B">Out-crossing</option>
            <option id="C">Cross-breeding</option>
            <option id="D">Interspecific hybridisation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>In this method, superior males of one breed are mated with superior females of another breed. Cross-breeding allows the desirable qualities of two different breeds to be combined. Hisardale is a new breed of sheep developed in Punjab by crossing Bikaneri ewes and Marino rams.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following methods is used to improve the chances of successful production of hybrids by administering hormones like FSH to induce super-ovulation?</text>
            <option id="A">Artificial insemination</option>
            <option id="B">Multiple Ovulation Embryo Transfer Technology (MOET)</option>
            <option id="C">Somatic hybridization</option>
            <option id="D">Tissue culture</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Multiple Ovulation Embryo Transfer Technology (MOET) is one such programme for herd improvement. In this method, a cow is administered hormones, with FSH-like activity, to induce follicular maturation and super ovulation - instead of one egg, which they normally yield per cycle, they produce 6-8 eggs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What is the main advantage of artificial insemination in animal breeding?</text>
            <option id="A">It allows semen from a single superior male to be used to impregnate many females</option>
            <option id="B">It guarantees the birth of a male offspring</option>
            <option id="C">It prevents the spread of genetic diseases completely</option>
            <option id="D">It always results in multiple births</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Controlled breeding experiments are carried out using artificial insemination. The semen is collected from the male that is chosen as a parent and injected into the reproductive tract of the selected female by the breeder. Semen from one superior male can be used to inseminate multiple females, and it can also be frozen and transported.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In the Multiple Ovulation Embryo Transfer (MOET) technique, the fertilised eggs are recovered and transferred to surrogate mothers at which cellular stage?</text>
            <option id="A">2-4 cells</option>
            <option id="B">8-32 cells</option>
            <option id="C">64-128 cells</option>
            <option id="D">Blastocyst</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In MOET, a cow is administered hormones to induce super ovulation. The animal is either mated with an elite bull or artificially inseminated. The fertilised eggs at 8-32 cells stages, are recovered non-surgically and transferred to surrogate mothers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The entire collection of plants/seeds having all the diverse alleles for all genes in a given crop is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Gene pool</option>
            <option id="B">Germplasm collection</option>
            <option id="C">Genome library</option>
            <option id="D">Herbarium</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The entire collection (of plants/seeds) having all the diverse alleles for all genes in a given crop is called germplasm collection. This is the root of any breeding programme.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Taichung Native-1, from which high-yielding semi-dwarf rice varieties were derived, was developed in which country?</text>
            <option id="A">India</option>
            <option id="B">Philippines</option>
            <option id="C">Taiwan</option>
            <option id="D">Mexico</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Semi-dwarf rice varieties were derived from IR-8, (developed at International Rice Research Institute (IRRI), Philippines) and Taichung Native-1 (from Taiwan). The derivatives were introduced in 1966.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Resistance to yellow mosaic virus in bhindi (Abelmoschus esculentus) was transferred from a wild species and resulted in a new variety called:</text>
            <option id="A">Pusa Sawani</option>
            <option id="B">Pusa A-4</option>
            <option id="C">Parbhani kranti</option>
            <option id="D">Kalyan Sona</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Resistance to yellow mosaic virus in bhindi (Abelmoschus esculentus) was transferred from a wild species and resulted in a new variety of A. esculentus called Parbhani kranti.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In mung bean, resistance to yellow mosaic virus and powdery mildew was induced by:</text>
            <option id="A">Hybridisation</option>
            <option id="B">Mutations</option>
            <option id="C">Tissue culture</option>
            <option id="D">Polyploidy</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>It is possible to induce mutations artificially through use of chemicals or radiations (like gamma radiations), and selecting and using the plants that have the desirable character as a source in breeding - this process is called mutation breeding. In mung bean, resistance to yellow mosaic virus and powdery mildew were induced by mutations.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Smooth leaved and nectar-less cotton varieties do not attract which insect pests?</text>
            <option id="A">Jassids</option>
            <option id="B">Bollworms</option>
            <option id="C">Aphids</option>
            <option id="D">Stem borers</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Some morphological, biochemical or physiological characteristics give the plants resistance to insects. Smooth leaved and nectar-less cotton varieties do not attract bollworms.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>High aspartic acid, low nitrogen and sugar content in maize leads to resistance to which pest?</text>
            <option id="A">Jassids</option>
            <option id="B">Maize stem borers</option>
            <option id="C">Cereal leaf beetle</option>
            <option id="D">Aphids</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>High aspartic acid, low nitrogen and sugar content in maize leads to resistance to maize stem borers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What does the term 'breed' refer to in animal husbandry?</text>
            <option id="A">A group of animals found in the same geographical area</option>
            <option id="B">A group of animals related by descent and similar in most characters</option>
            <option id="C">Any two animals that can interbreed naturally</option>
            <option id="D">Animals that share the same diet</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>A group of animals related by descent and similar in most characters like general appearance, features, size, configuration, etc., are said to belong to a breed.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>When breeding is between animals of the same breed it is called inbreeding, while crosses between different breeds are called:</text>
            <option id="A">Out-crossing</option>
            <option id="B">Outbreeding</option>
            <option id="C">Cross-breeding</option>
            <option id="D">Interspecific hybridisation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>When breeding is between animals of the same breed it is called inbreeding, while crosses between different breeds are called outbreeding.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Inbreeding depression, which is a reduction in fertility and productivity, is caused by:</text>
            <option id="A">Cross-breeding</option>
            <option id="B">Out-crossing</option>
            <option id="C">Continued inbreeding, especially close inbreeding</option>
            <option id="D">Interspecific hybridisation</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>However, continued inbreeding, especially close inbreeding, usually reduces fertility and even productivity. This is called inbreeding depression.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The practice of mating of animals within the same breed, but having no common ancestors on either side of their pedigree up to 4-6 generations, is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Inbreeding</option>
            <option id="B">Out-crossing</option>
            <option id="C">Cross-breeding</option>
            <option id="D">Interspecific hybridisation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Out-crossing: This is the practice of mating of animals within the same breed, but having no common ancestors on either side of their pedigree up to 4-6 generations. The offspring of such a mating is known as an out-cross.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The development and flourishing of the fishery industry is closely associated with which revolution?</text>
            <option id="A">Green Revolution</option>
            <option id="B">White Revolution</option>
            <option id="C">Blue Revolution</option>
            <option id="D">Yellow Revolution</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Fisheries has an important place in Indian economy. It provides income and employment to millions of fishermen and farmers, particularly in the coastal states. For many, it is the only source of their livelihood. In order to meet the increasing demands on fisheries, different techniques have been applied to increase catch. Through aquaculture and pisciculture we have been able to increase the production of aquatic plants and animals, both fresh-water and marine. This has led to the development and flourishing of the fishery industry, and it has brought a lot of income to the farmers in particular and the country in general. We now talk about 'Blue Revolution' as being implemented along the same lines as 'Green Revolution'.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Traditional farming can only yield a limited biomass. What practice helped increase crop yields to meet the demands of a growing human population?</text>
            <option id="A">Plant breeding</option>
            <option id="B">Deforestation</option>
            <option id="C">Decreased irrigation</option>
            <option id="D">Monoculture</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Traditional farming can only yield a limited biomass, as food for humans and animals. Better management practices and increase in acreage can increase yield, but only to a limited extent. Plant breeding as a technology has helped increase yields to a very large extent.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The purposeful manipulation of plant species in order to create desired plant types that are better suited for cultivation, give better yields and are disease resistant is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Genetic engineering</option>
            <option id="B">Plant breeding</option>
            <option id="C">Tissue culture</option>
            <option id="D">Somatic hybridization</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Plant breeding is the purposeful manipulation of plant species in order to create desired plant types that are better suited for cultivation, give better yields and are disease resistant.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>What was the phase of dramatically increased agricultural production in India called?</text>
            <option id="A">White Revolution</option>
            <option id="B">Green Revolution</option>
            <option id="C">Industrial Revolution</option>
            <option id="D">Blue Revolution</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Who in India has not heard of Green Revolution which was responsible for our country to not merely meet the national requirements in food production but also helped us even to export it? Green revolution was dependent to a large extent on plant breeding techniques for development of high-yielding and disease resistant varieties in wheat, rice, maize, etc.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which varieties of semi-dwarf wheat were introduced in India in 1963 that were high yielding and disease resistant?</text>
            <option id="A">IR-8 and Taichung Native-1</option>
            <option id="B">Sonalika and Kalyan Sona</option>
            <option id="C">Jaya and Ratna</option>
            <option id="D">Saccharum barberi and Saccharum officinarum</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In 1963, several varieties such as Sonalika and Kalyan Sona, which were high yielding and disease resistant, were introduced all over the wheat-growing belt of India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Semi-dwarf rice varieties IR-8 and Taichung Native-1 were derived from which locations respectively?</text>
            <option id="A">Mexico and Taiwan</option>
            <option id="B">IRRI, Philippines and Taiwan</option>
            <option id="C">India and China</option>
            <option id="D">USA and Japan</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Semi-dwarf rice varieties were derived from IR-8, (developed at International Rice Research Institute (IRRI), Philippines) and Taichung Native-1 (from Taiwan).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Later in India, better-yielding semi-dwarf rice varieties were developed. Two prominent examples are:</text>
            <option id="A">Sonalika and Kalyan Sona</option>
            <option id="B">Jaya and Ratna</option>
            <option id="C">Himgiri and Pusa swarnim</option>
            <option id="D">Pusa shubhra and Pusa Snowball K-1</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Later better-yielding semi-dwarf varieties Jaya and Ratna were developed in India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which sugarcane species was originally grown in North India, but had poor sugar content and yield?</text>
            <option id="A">Saccharum officinarum</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharum spontaneum</option>
            <option id="C">Saccharum barberi</option>
            <option id="D">Saccharum robustum</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Saccharum barberi was originally grown in north India, but had poor sugar content and yield.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which cauliflower varieties were developed to resist black rot and curl blight black rot?</text>
            <option id="A">Pusa swarnim</option>
            <option id="B">Pusa shubhra and Pusa Snowball K-1</option>
            <option id="C">Pusa Komal</option>
            <option id="D">Pusa Sadabahar</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Cauliflower varieties Pusa shubhra and Pusa Snowball K-1 are resistant to Black rot and Curl blight black rot.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The cowpea variety Pusa Komal was developed for resistance against which bacterial disease?</text>
            <option id="A">Bacterial blight</option>
            <option id="B">White rust</option>
            <option id="C">Hill bunt</option>
            <option id="D">Leaf curl</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Cowpea variety Pusa Komal is resistant to Bacterial blight.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which disease is the chilli variety Pusa Sadabahar resistant to?</text>
            <option id="A">Black rot</option>
            <option id="B">White rust</option>
            <option id="C">Chilly mosaic virus, Tobacco mosaic virus, and Leaf curl</option>
            <option id="D">Hill bunt</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Chilli variety Pusa Sadabahar is resistant to Chilly mosaic virus, Tobacco mosaic virus and Leaf curl.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A major limitation of using conventional breeding for disease resistance is:</text>
            <option id="A">It is too expensive</option>
            <option id="B">The limited number of disease resistance genes available in the crop varieties and wild relatives</option>
            <option id="C">The resulting plants are toxic</option>
            <option id="D">It takes too much land to perform</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Conventional breeding is often constrained by the availability of limited number of disease resistance genes that are present and identified in various crop varieties or wild relatives.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Maize varieties with high aspartic acid, low nitrogen, and sugar content exhibit resistance to which pest?</text>
            <option id="A">Maize stem borers</option>
            <option id="B">Bollworms</option>
            <option id="C">Jassids</option>
            <option id="D">Cereal leaf beetles</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>High aspartic acid, low nitrogen and sugar content in maize leads to resistance to maize stem borers.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Brassica (rapeseed mustard) variety Pusa Gaurav was bred for resistance against which pest?</text>
            <option id="A">Jassids</option>
            <option id="B">Aphids</option>
            <option id="C">Shoot and fruit borer</option>
            <option id="D">Bollworms</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Brassica (rapeseed mustard) variety Pusa Gaurav is resistant to Aphids.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which flat bean varieties were developed to resist Jassids, aphids, and fruit borer?</text>
            <option id="A">Pusa Gaurav</option>
            <option id="B">Pusa Sem 2 and Pusa Sem 3</option>
            <option id="C">Pusa Sawani and Pusa A-4</option>
            <option id="D">Pusa Komal</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Flat bean varieties Pusa Sem 2 and Pusa Sem 3 are resistant to Jassids, aphids and fruit borer.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Okra (Bhindi) varieties Pusa Sawani and Pusa A-4 are resistant to which insects?</text>
            <option id="A">Shoot and fruit borer</option>
            <option id="B">Aphids and Jassids</option>
            <option id="C">Bollworms</option>
            <option id="D">Stem sawfly</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Okra (Bhindi) varieties Pusa Sawani and Pusa A-4 are resistant to Shoot and Fruit borer.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which IARI released vegetable crops are specifically mentioned as being enriched with Vitamin A?</text>
            <option id="A">Carrots, spinach, and pumpkin</option>
            <option id="B">Bitter gourd, bathua, and mustard</option>
            <option id="C">Tomato, pea, and beans</option>
            <option id="D">Wheat, rice, and maize</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Vitamin A enriched carrots, spinach, pumpkin...</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which minerals are enriched in the IARI released spinach and bathua varieties?</text>
            <option id="A">Calcium and magnesium</option>
            <option id="B">Iron and calcium</option>
            <option id="C">Zinc and iodine</option>
            <option id="D">Potassium and sodium</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>...iron and calcium enriched spinach and bathua...</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which IARI released crops are protein enriched?</text>
            <option id="A">Carrots and spinach</option>
            <option id="B">Broad lablab, French, and garden peas</option>
            <option id="C">Bitter gourd and tomato</option>
            <option id="D">Pumpkin and mustard</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>...and protein enriched broad lablab, French and garden peas.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Traditional farming can only yield a limited biomass. What is the alternative that is being considered as an alternate source of proteins for animal and human nutrition?</text>
            <option id="A">Micro-propagation</option>
            <option id="B">Single Cell Protein (SCP)</option>
            <option id="C">Somatic hybridization</option>
            <option id="D">Tissue culture</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>One of the alternate sources of proteins for animal and human nutrition is Single Cell Protein (SCP).</explanation>
        </question>
    </medium>
    <hard>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following crosses led to the development of the new sheep breed "Hisardale" in Punjab?</text>
            <option id="A">Bikaneri ewes and Marino rams</option>
            <option id="B">Marino ewes and Bikaneri rams</option>
            <option id="C">Nali ewes and Corriedale rams</option>
            <option id="D">Deccani ewes and Marino rams</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Hisardale is a new breed of sheep developed in Punjab by crossing Bikaneri ewes and Marino rams. This is an example of cross-breeding, where superior males of one breed are mated with superior females of another breed.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Saccharum barberi was originally grown in north India, but had poor sugar content and yield. It was successfully crossed with which tropical cane to get the desirable qualities?</text>
            <option id="A">Saccharum spontaneum</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharum officinarum</option>
            <option id="C">Saccharum sinense</option>
            <option id="D">Saccharum robustum</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Saccharum barberi was originally grown in north India, but had poor sugar content and yield. Tropical canes grown in south India Saccharum officinarum had thicker stems and higher sugar content. These two species were successfully crossed to get sugar cane varieties combining the desirable qualities.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Biofortification refers to:</text>
            <option id="A">The use of microbes to extract heavy metals from soil.</option>
            <option id="B">Breeding crops with higher levels of vitamins and minerals, or higher protein and healthier fats.</option>
            <option id="C">The artificial addition of nutrients to food during processing.</option>
            <option id="D">The fortification of natural habitats to protect endangered species.</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Breeding crops with higher levels of vitamins and minerals, or higher protein and healthier fats is the most practical means to improve public health. This process is called biofortification. Examples include iron-fortified rice and vitamin A enriched carrots.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During plant tissue culture, what determines whether the explant differentiates into roots or shoots?</text>
            <option id="A">The size of the explant</option>
            <option id="B">The temperature of the culture room</option>
            <option id="C">The concentration and ratio of auxins and cytokinins</option>
            <option id="D">The amount of sucrose in the medium</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The nutrient medium must provide a carbon source such as sucrose and also inorganic salts, vitamins, amino acids and growth regulators like auxins, cytokinins etc. The ratio of auxins to cytokinins determines whether roots or shoots will develop.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following statements about Single Cell Protein (SCP) is FALSE?</text>
            <option id="A">It is an alternate source of proteins for animal and human nutrition.</option>
            <option id="B">Microbes like Spirulina can be grown easily to produce large quantities of protein.</option>
            <option id="C">Methylophilus methylotrophus can produce 25 tonnes of protein.</option>
            <option id="D">It requires large tracts of fertile agricultural land to produce.</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>SCP reduces the pressure on agricultural land. Microbes like Spirulina can be grown easily on materials like waste water from potato processing plants, straw, molasses, animal manure and even sewage.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following crop varieties is specifically bred for resistance to White rust?</text>
            <option id="A">Pusa Swarnim</option>
            <option id="B">Pusa Shubhra</option>
            <option id="C">Pusa Snowball K-1</option>
            <option id="D">Pusa Komal</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Pusa Swarnim (Karan rai), a variety of Brassica, was bred for resistance to the disease White rust.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Saccharum barberi was originally grown in north India, but had poor sugar content and yield. It was crossed with a south Indian species to get desirable qualities. What was the south Indian species?</text>
            <option id="A">Saccharum spontaneum</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharum officinarum</option>
            <option id="C">Saccharum robustum</option>
            <option id="D">Saccharum sinense</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Saccharum barberi was originally grown in north India, but had poor sugar content and yield. Tropical canes grown in south India Saccharum officinarum had thicker stems and higher sugar content but did not grow well in north India. These two species were successfully crossed.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following plant parts is generally free of viruses and is therefore used as an explant in tissue culture to recover healthy plants from diseased ones?</text>
            <option id="A">Leaf</option>
            <option id="B">Stem</option>
            <option id="C">Meristem (apical and axillary)</option>
            <option id="D">Root</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Even if the plant is infected with a virus, the meristem (apical and axillary) is free of virus. Hence, one can remove the meristem and grow it in vitro to obtain virus-free plants.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The capacity to generate a whole plant from any cell/explant is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Pluripotency</option>
            <option id="B">Totipotency</option>
            <option id="C">Micropropagation</option>
            <option id="D">Somatic hybridization</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The capacity to generate a whole plant from any cell/explant is called totipotency. This property is extensively utilized in plant tissue culture.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The green revolution in India was highly dependent on plant breeding techniques. Who is known as the Father of the Green Revolution in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Norman Borlaug</option>
            <option id="B">M.S. Swaminathan</option>
            <option id="C">V. Kurien</option>
            <option id="D">Hargobind Khorana</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The Green Revolution in India was led by Dr. M. S. Swaminathan, known as the 'Father of the Green Revolution in India' for his role in introducing and further developing high-yielding varieties of wheat in India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Saccharum barberi was originally grown in north India, but had poor sugar content and yield. It was crossed with a species from south India that had thicker stems and higher sugar content. Which species was it?</text>
            <option id="A">Saccharum spontaneum</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharum officinarum</option>
            <option id="C">Saccharum sinense</option>
            <option id="D">Saccharum robustum</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Saccharum barberi was originally grown in north India, but had poor sugar content and yield. Tropical canes grown in south India Saccharum officinarum had thicker stems and higher sugar content but did not grow well in north India. These two species were successfully crossed to get sugar cane varieties combining the desirable qualities of high yield, thick stems, high sugar and ability to grow in the sugar cane areas of north India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Breeding crops with higher levels of vitamins and minerals, or higher protein and healthier fats, is the most practical means to improve public health. This process is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Biomagnification</option>
            <option id="B">Bioremediation</option>
            <option id="C">Biofortification</option>
            <option id="D">Bioprospecting</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Breeding crops with higher levels of vitamins and minerals, or higher protein and healthier fats - is the most practical means to improve public health. This process is called biofortification.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Spirulina is a microbe that can be grown on a large scale on materials like waste water from potato processing plants, straw, molasses, animal manure and even sewage. It serves as a rich source of:</text>
            <option id="A">Carbohydrates</option>
            <option id="B">Single Cell Protein (SCP)</option>
            <option id="C">Antibiotics</option>
            <option id="D">Vitamins</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Microbes are being grown on an industrial scale as source of good protein. Microbes like Spirulina can be grown easily on materials like waste water from potato processing plants (containing starch), straw, molasses, animal manure and even sewage, to produce large quantities and can serve as food rich in protein, minerals, fats, carbohydrate and vitamins. This is known as Single Cell Protein (SCP).</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A bacterial species, Methylophilus methylotrophus, because of its high rate of biomass production and growth, can be expected to produce roughly how many tonnes of protein?</text>
            <option id="A">25 grams</option>
            <option id="B">25 kg</option>
            <option id="C">25 tonnes</option>
            <option id="D">250 tonnes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>It has been calculated that a 250 Kg cow produces 200 g of protein per day. In the same period, 250g of a micro-organism like Methylophilus methylotrophus, because of its high rate of biomass production and growth, can be expected to produce 25 tonnes of protein.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The process of growing cells, tissues, or organs in an artificial nutrient medium under aseptic conditions is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Hydroponics</option>
            <option id="B">Tissue culture</option>
            <option id="C">Aeroponics</option>
            <option id="D">Micropropagation</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The whole plant could be regenerated from explants, i.e., any part of a plant taken out and grown in a test tube, under sterile conditions in special nutrient media. This capacity to generate a whole plant from any cell/explant is called totipotency. This method of growing plants is called tissue culture.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Hidden hunger refers to the deficiency of which of the following in the diet?</text>
            <option id="A">Carbohydrates and proteins</option>
            <option id="B">Fats and lipids</option>
            <option id="C">Micronutrients, proteins, and vitamins</option>
            <option id="D">Water and roughage</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>More than 840 million people in the world do not have adequate food to meet their daily food and nutritional requirements. A far greater number - three billion people - suffer from micronutrient, protein and vitamin deficiencies or 'hidden hunger'.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In 2000, maize hybrids that had twice the amount of the amino acids ______ and ______ compared to existing maize hybrids were developed.</text>
            <option id="A">Lysine and tryptophan</option>
            <option id="B">Valine and leucine</option>
            <option id="C">Methionine and cysteine</option>
            <option id="D">Phenylalanine and tyrosine</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In 2000, maize hybrids that had twice the amount of the amino acids, lysine and tryptophan, compared to existing maize hybrids were developed. Wheat variety, Atlas 66, having a high protein content, has been used as a donor for improving cultivated wheat.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI), New Delhi, has released several vegetable crops that are rich in vitamins and minerals. Which of the following is an example?</text>
            <option id="A">Vitamin A enriched carrots, spinach, pumpkin</option>
            <option id="B">Vitamin C enriched bitter gourd, bathua, mustard, tomato</option>
            <option id="C">Iron and calcium enriched spinach and bathua</option>
            <option id="D">All of the above</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>The Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI), New Delhi has also released several vegetable crops that are rich in vitamins and minerals, e.g., Vitamin A enriched carrots, spinach, pumpkin; Vitamin C enriched bitter gourd, bathua, mustard, tomato; iron and calcium enriched spinach and bathua; and protein enriched beans – broad, lablab, French and garden peas.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Multiple Ovulation Embryo Transfer Technology (MOET) is a programme for herd improvement. In this method, a cow is administered hormones with FSH-like activity. This induces:</text>
            <option id="A">Follicular maturation and super ovulation</option>
            <option id="B">Immediate birth of calves</option>
            <option id="C">Inhibition of estrus</option>
            <option id="D">Development of multiple udders</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>In this method, a cow is administered hormones, with FSH-like activity, to induce follicular maturation and super ovulation - instead of one egg, which they normally yield per cycle, they produce 6-8 eggs.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In MOET, after the fertilized eggs at the 8–32 cell stage are recovered non-surgically, they are transferred to:</text>
            <option id="A">The same genetic mother</option>
            <option id="B">Surrogate mothers</option>
            <option id="C">An incubator</option>
            <option id="D">A deep freeze</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>The fertilised eggs at 8–32 cells stages, are recovered non-surgically and transferred to surrogate mothers. The genetic mother is available for another round of super ovulation.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Apiculture is the maintenance of hives of honeybees for the production of honey. Which is the most common species of honeybee reared in India?</text>
            <option id="A">Apis dorsata</option>
            <option id="B">Apis florea</option>
            <option id="C">Apis indica</option>
            <option id="D">Apis mellifera</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Bee-keeping or apiculture is the maintenance of hives of honeybees for the production of honey. There are several species of honeybees which can be reared. Of these, the most common species is Apis indica.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>The entire collection (of plants/seeds) having all the diverse alleles for all genes in a given crop is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Genetic drift</option>
            <option id="B">Gene pool</option>
            <option id="C">Germplasm collection</option>
            <option id="D">Genome library</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>The entire collection (of plants/seeds) having all the diverse alleles for all genes in a given crop is called germplasm collection.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During plant breeding, after superior recombinants have been selected and tested, they are multiplied and made available to farmers. This process is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Collection of variability</option>
            <option id="B">Evaluation and selection of parents</option>
            <option id="C">Cross hybridisation</option>
            <option id="D">Testing, release and commercialisation of new cultivars</option>
            <answer>D</answer>
            <explanation>Testing, release and commercialisation of new cultivars: The newly selected lines are evaluated for their yield and other agronomic traits of quality, disease resistance, etc. The material is then tested in farmer's fields, for at least three growing seasons. The material thus evaluated is compared with the best available local crop cultivar and is finally released as a variety.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>During the period 1960 to 2000, wheat production in India increased from 11 million tonnes to:</text>
            <option id="A">25 million tonnes</option>
            <option id="B">50 million tonnes</option>
            <option id="C">75 million tonnes</option>
            <option id="D">100 million tonnes</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>During the period 1960 to 2000, wheat production increased from 11 million tonnes to 75 million tonnes while rice production went up from 35 million tonnes to 89.5 million tonnes. This was due to the development of semi-dwarf varieties of wheat and rice.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which sugarcane species had thicker stems and higher sugar content but did not grow well in North India?</text>
            <option id="A">Saccharum barberi</option>
            <option id="B">Saccharum officinarum</option>
            <option id="C">Saccharum spontaneum</option>
            <option id="D">Saccharum sinense</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Tropical canes grown in south India Saccharum officinarum had thicker stems and higher sugar content but did not grow well in north India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>How did plant breeders successfully develop a sugarcane variety with high yield, thick stems, high sugar, and the ability to grow in North India?</text>
            <option id="A">By mutating Saccharum barberi</option>
            <option id="B">By crossing Saccharum barberi and Saccharum officinarum</option>
            <option id="C">By introducing genes from maize</option>
            <option id="D">By using tissue culture alone</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>These two species were successfully crossed to get sugar cane varieties combining the desirable qualities of high yield, thick stems, high sugar and ability to grow in the sugar cane areas of north India.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>A wide range of fungal, bacterial, and viral pathogens affect the yield of cultivated crop species. Which of the following diseases is caused by a fungus?</text>
            <option id="A">Black rot of crucifers</option>
            <option id="B">Tobacco mosaic</option>
            <option id="C">Brown rust of wheat</option>
            <option id="D">Turnip mosaic</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Some of the diseases caused by fungi are rusts, e.g., brown rust of wheat, red rot of sugarcane and late blight of potato; by bacteria– black rot of crucifers; and by viruses– tobacco mosaic, turnip mosaic, etc.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Inducing mutations artificially and then selecting plants with desirable characters to use as a source in breeding is known as:</text>
            <option id="A">Conventional breeding</option>
            <option id="B">Mutation breeding</option>
            <option id="C">Genetic engineering</option>
            <option id="D">Inbreeding</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>It is possible to induce mutations artificially through use of chemicals or radiations (like gamma radiations), and selecting and using the plants that have the desirable character as a source in breeding – this process is called mutation breeding.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In mung bean, resistance to yellow mosaic virus and powdery mildew were induced by:</text>
            <option id="A">Hybridisation</option>
            <option id="B">Mutations</option>
            <option id="C">Cross-pollination</option>
            <option id="D">Grafting</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In mung bean, resistance to yellow mosaic virus and powdery mildew were induced by mutations.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Resistance to yellow mosaic virus in bhindi (Abelmoschus esculentus) was transferred from a wild species, resulting in a new variety called:</text>
            <option id="A">Pusa Komal</option>
            <option id="B">Pusa Sadabahar</option>
            <option id="C">Parbhani kranti</option>
            <option id="D">Himgiri</option>
            <answer>C</answer>
            <explanation>Resistance to yellow mosaic virus in bhindi (Abelmoschus esculentus) was transferred from a wild species and resulted in a new variety of A. esculentus called Parbhani kranti.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Diets lacking essential micronutrients like iron, vitamin A, iodine, and zinc increase the risk for disease and reduce lifespan. What is this hidden form of hunger called?</text>
            <option id="A">Malnutrition</option>
            <option id="B">Hidden hunger</option>
            <option id="C">Starvation</option>
            <option id="D">Anemia</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Diets lacking essential micronutrients – particularly iron, vitamin A, iodine and zinc – increase the risk for disease, reduce lifespan and reduce mental abilities. Over three billion people suffer from micronutrient, protein and vitamin deficiencies or 'hidden hunger' because they cannot afford to buy enough fruits, vegetables, legumes, fish and meat.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Breeding crops with higher levels of vitamins and minerals, or higher protein and healthier fats is called:</text>
            <option id="A">Biomagnification</option>
            <option id="B">Biofortification</option>
            <option id="C">Bioremediation</option>
            <option id="D">Mutagenesis</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>Biofortification – breeding crops with higher levels of vitamins and minerals, or higher protein and healthier fats – is the most practical means to improve public health.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>In 2000, maize hybrids were developed that had twice the amount of which two essential amino acids compared to existing hybrids?</text>
            <option id="A">Leucine and valine</option>
            <option id="B">Lysine and tryptophan</option>
            <option id="C">Methionine and cysteine</option>
            <option id="D">Alanine and glycine</option>
            <answer>B</answer>
            <explanation>In 2000, maize hybrids that had twice the amount of the amino acids, lysine and tryptophan, compared to existing maize hybrids were developed.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Microbes are being grown on an industrial scale as a source of good protein. Which blue-green alga can be grown easily on materials like waste water from potato processing plants, straw, molasses, animal manure, and even sewage, to produce large quantities of food rich in protein, minerals, fats, carbohydrate and vitamins?</text>
            <option id="A">Spirulina</option>
            <option id="B">Nostoc</option>
            <option id="C">Anabaena</option>
            <option id="D">Oscillatoria</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>Microbes are being grown on an industrial scale as source of good protein. Blue-green algae like Spirulina can be grown easily on materials like waste water from potato processing plants... to produce large quantities and can serve as food rich in protein, minerals, fats, carbohydrate and vitamins.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>It has been calculated that a 250 Kg cow produces 200 g of protein per day. In the same period, 250g of a micro-organism like Methylophilus methylotrophus can be expected to produce how much protein?</text>
            <option id="A">25 tons</option>
            <option id="B">200 grams</option>
            <option id="C">2.5 tons</option>
            <option id="D">250 kg</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>It has been calculated that a 250 Kg cow produces 200 g of protein per day. In the same period, 250g of a micro-organism like Methylophilus methylotrophus, because of its high rate of biomass production and growth, can be expected to produce 25 tonnes of protein.</explanation>
        </question>
        <question>
            <text>Which of the following is a common fungus that many people eat, indicating that large-scale mushroom culture is a growing industry?</text>
            <option id="A">Agaricus</option>
            <option id="B">Methylophilus</option>
            <option id="C">Spirulina</option>
            <option id="D">Penicillium</option>
            <answer>A</answer>
            <explanation>The fact that edible mushrooms are eaten by many people and large scale mushroom culture is a growing industry makes it believable that microscopic fungi too would become acceptable as food.</explanation>
        </question>
    </hard>
</chapter>